Pride and
Prejudice by
Jane Austen.
Chapter one.
It is a truth
universally.
Acknowledged
that a single man
in possession of a.
Good fortune
must be in want.
Of a wife.
However little known
the feelings
or views of such
a man may be
on his first entering
a neighborhood.
This truth is.
So well
fixed in the minds
of the
surrounding families
that he is
considered
the rightful property
of some one
or other of their.
Daughters.
My dear Mr.
Bennett.
Said his lady to him
one day.
Have you heard that
Netherfield Park
is let it last?
Mr.
Bennett replied
that he had not.
But it is returned.
She, for Mrs.
long,
has just been here.
And she told me
all about it.
Mr.
Bennett made no answer.
Do you not want to know
who has taken it?
Cried his
wife impatiently.
You want to tell me?
And I
have no objection
to hearing it.
This was invitation
enough.
Why, my dear.
You must know Mrs.
Long says that.
Netherfield is taken by.
A young man
of large fortune
from the north
of England.
That he came down
on Monday in Natchez,
and for to see the place
and was so much
delighted with it
that he agreed with Mr.
Morris immediately
that he is to
take possession
before Michaelmas
and some of his servants
ought to.
Be in the house
by the end of.
Next week.
What is his name?
Bingley.
Is he married
or single?
Oh, single,
my dear, to be sure.
A single man
of large Fortune
four or 5000 a year.
What a fine
thing for our girls.
How so?
How can it affect them?
My dear Mr.
Bennett.
Replied his wife.
How can you
be so tiresome?
You must know
that I am thinking
of his marrying
one of them.
Is that his design
in settling here?
Design.
Nonsense.
How can you talk?
So.
But it is very likely
that he may fall in love
with one of them.
And therefore,
you must visit him
as soon as he comes.
I see no occasion
for that.
You and the girls may go
or you may
send them by themselves,
which perhaps
will be still better
for as you are
as handsome
as any of them.
Mr.
Bingley might like you
the best of the party.
My dear,
you've flatter me.
I certainly have
had my share of beauty.
But I do not pretend
to be anything
extraordinary now.
When a woman has five
grown up daughters,
she ought to give
over thinking
of her own beauty.
In such cases, a
woman has not often
much beauty to think of.
But, my
dear, you must
indeed go and see Mr.
Bingley
when he comes into
the neighborhood.
It is more than
I engaged for,
I assure you.
But consider
your daughters
only think
what an establishment
it would be for
one of them.
So William and Lady
Lucas are determined
to go
merely on that account.
For in general,
you know, they visit
no new comers.
Indeed, you must go.
For it
will be impossible
for us to visit him
if you do not.
You are over
scrupulous, surely.
I daresay Mr.
Bingley will be
very glad to see you.
And I will send
a few lines by you
to assure him
of my hearty consent
to his marrying
whichever
he chooses of the girls.
Though
I must throw
in a good word
for my little Lizzie.
I desire,
You will do
no such thing.
Lizzie is not a bit
better than the others,
and I am sure
she is not half
so handsome as Jane.
Nor half so good
humored as Lydia.
But you are
always giving her
the preference.
They have
none of them, much
to recommend them.
Replied he.
They're all silly
and ignorant
like other girls.
But Lizzie has something
more of quickness
than her sisters.
Mr.
Bennett,
how can you abuse
your own children
in such a way?
You take delight
in vexing me.
You have no compassion
for my poor nerves.
You mistake me, my dear.
I have a high respect
for your nerves.
They are my old friends.
I have heard
you mention them
with consideration
these 20 years at least.
No.
You do not know
what I suffer.
But I hope
you will get over it
and live to see
many young
men of 4000
a year
come into
the neighborhood.
It would be no use to us
if 20 such would come,
since you will not visit
them.
Depend upon it, my dear,
that when there are 20,
I will visit them all.
Mr.
Bennett was so odd.
A mixture of
quick parts,
sarcastic humor,
reserve and caprice
that the experience
of three and 20 years
had been insufficient
to make
his wife understand
his character.
Her mind was less
difficult to develop.
She was a woman of
mean understanding.
Little information
and uncertain temper.
When she
was discontented,
she fancied herself
nervous.
The business of her life
was to get her
daughters married.
It's Solace was visiting
and news.
Chapter two.
Mr.
Bennett was among
the earliest of those
who waited on Mr.
Bingley.
He had always intended
to visit him,
though, to the last,
always assuring his wife
that he should not go
until the evening after
the visit was paid.
She had no knowledge
of it.
It was then.
Disclosed in
the following manner,
observing his second
daughter employed
in trimming a hat,
he suddenly addressed
her with.
I hope Mr.
Bingley will
like it, Lizzie.
We are not in a way
to know what Mr.
Bingley likes.
Said her
mother resentfully.
Since we are
not to visit.
But she forgets.
Mamma said Elizabeth.
That we shall meet him
at the assemblies
and that Mrs.
Long promised to
introduce him.
I do not believe
this is long
will do any such thing.
She has two
nieces of her own.
She is a selfish,
hypocritical woman.
And I have no
opinion of her.
No more have I?
Said Mr.
Bennett.
And I am glad
to find
that you do not depend
on her serving you.
Mrs.
Bennett deigned
not to make any reply.
But unable
to contain herself,
began.
Scolding
one of her daughters.
Don't keep coughing.
So, Kitty,
for heaven's sake,
have a little compassion
on my nerves.
You tear them to pieces.
Kitty has no
discretion in
her coughs.
Said her father.
She times them ill.
I do not cough
for my own amusement.
Replied Kitty,
frightfully.
When is your next ball
to be, Lizzie?
Tomorrow
fortnight I.
So it is.
Cried her mother.
And Mrs.
Long does not come back
to the day before.
So it will be impossible
for her
to introduce him.
For
she will not know him
herself.
Then, my dear,
you may
have the advantage
of your friend
and introduce Mr.
Bingley to her.
Impossible, Mr.
Bennett.
Impossible.
When I am not acquainted
with him myself,
how can you be
so teasing?
I honor
your circumspection.
A fortnight's
acquaintance
is certainly
very little.
One cannot know
what a man really is
by the end of
a fortnight.
But if we do
not venture,
somebody else will.
And after all, Mrs.
Long and her nieces
must stand their chance.
And therefore,
as she will think
it, an act of kindness.
If you
decline the office,
I will
take it on myself.
The girls
stared at their father.
Mrs.
Bennett said only
nonsense.
Nonsense.
What can be the meaning
of that
emphatic exclamation?
Cried.
Do you consider the
forms of introduction
and the stress that is
laid on
them is nonsense.
I cannot quite agree
with you there.
What say you, Mary?
For?
You are a young lady
of deep reflection.
I know.
And read great books
and make extracts.
Mary wished
to say
something sensible.
But knew not how.
Well Mary is
adjusting her ideas.
He continued.
Let us return to Mr.
Bingley.
I am sick of Mr.
Cried his wife.
I'm sorry to hear that.
But why did you not
tell me so before?
If I had known
as much this morning.
I certainly would
not have called on him.
It is very unlucky.
But as I have
actually paid the visit,
we cannot escape
the acquaintance now.
The astonishment
of the ladies was.
Just what he wished.
That of Mrs.
Bennett,
perhaps
surpassing the rest.
The When the first.
Tumult of joy was over,
she began
to declare that
it was what
she had expected.
All the while.
How good it was.
And you, my dear Mr.
Bennett.
But I knew I should
persuade you at last.
I was sure you loved
all girls too
well to neglect
such an acquaintance.
Well,
how pleased I am.
And it is such
a good joke to that.
You should have gone
this morning
and never said
a word about it
till now.
Now, Kitty,
you may cough
as much as you choose.
Said Mr.
Bennett.
And as he spoke,
he left the room
fatigued.
With the
raptures of his wife.
What an excellent.
Father you have, girls?
Said she.
When the door was shut.
I do not know
how you will ever make
him amends
for his kindness.
Or me either,
for that matter.
At our time of life,
it is not so pleasant.
I can tell you
to be making
new acquaintances
every day.
But for your sake,
we would do anything.
Lydia.
My love,
though
you are the youngest.
I daresay Mr.
Bingley will dance
with you
at the next ball.
Oh, said
Lydia stoutly.
I am not afraid
for their life.
I am the youngest.
I am the tallest.
The rest of the evening
was spent
in conjecturing
how soon
he would return Mr.
Bennett's visit
and determining
when they
should ask
him to dinner.
Chapter three.
Not all that, Mrs.
Bennett, however,
with the assistance
of her five daughters,
could ask
on the subject.
Was.
Sufficient
to draw from her husband
any satisfactory
description of Mr.
Bingley.
They attacked him
in various ways
with barefaced
questions,
ingenious suppositions
and distant surmises.
But he eluded
the skill of them all,
and they were
at last obliged
to accept
the second hand
intelligence
of their neighbor,
Lady Lucas.
Her report was
highly favorable.
Sir William had been
delighted with him.
He was quite young,
wonderfully handsome,
extremely agreeable,
and to crown the whole.
He meant to.
Be at the next assembly
with a large party.
Nothing could be
more delightful.
To be. Fond of.
Dancing was a
certain step
towards falling in love
and very lively hopes
of Mr.
Bailey's heart
were entertained.
If I can
but see
one of my daughters
happily
settled at Netherfield.
Said Mrs.
Bennett to her husband.
And all the others
equally well married.
I shall have nothing
to wish for.
In a few days.
Mr.
Bingley returned Mr.
Bennett's visit
and sat about 10 minutes
with him in his library.
He had entertained hopes
of being admitted
to a sight
of the young ladies.
Of whose beauty.
He had heard much.
But he saw.
Only the father.
The ladies were
somewhat more fortunate,
for they had
the advantage
of ascertaining
from an upper window
that he wore a blue coat
and rode a black horse.
An invitation to dinner
was soon
afterwards dispatched
and already had Mrs.
Bennett planned
the courses
that were to do credit
to her housekeeping.
When an answer arrived
which differed
at all, Mr.
Bingley was obliged
to be in town
the following day
and consequently unable
to accept the honor
of their
invitation, etc..
Mrs.
Bennett was
quite disconcerted.
She could not imagine
what.
Business
he could have in town
so soon
after his arrival
in Hertfordshire,
and she began to fear
that he might be always
flying about
from one place
to another
and never settled
at Netherfield, as he.
Ought to be.
Lady Lucas
quieted her fears
a little by starting
the idea of his
being gone
to London,
only to get
a large party
for the ball.
And a report soon
followed that Mr.
Bingley was to bring
12 ladies and seven
gentlemen with him
to the assembly.
The girls grieved over
such a number of ladies,
but were comforted
the day
before the ball
by hearing
that instead of 12
he brought only six
with him from London.
His five sisters and
a cousin.
And when the party
entered the
assembly room. It.
Consisted
of only five altogether.
Mr.
Bingley,
his two sisters.
The husband.
Of the eldest,
and another young man.
Mr.
Bingley was good
looking and
gentleman like.
He had a
pleasant countenance
and easy,
unaffected manners.
His sisters were fine
women
with an air of decided
fashion.
His brother in law, Mr.
Hurst, merely
looked the gentleman,
but his friend, Mr.
Darcy, soon
drew the attention
of the room by his fine,
tall person.
Handsome features
noble mien
and the report,
which was in
general circulation
within 5 minutes
after his entrance
of his having 10,000
a year.
The gentleman
pronounced him
to be
a fine figure of a man.
The ladies declared
he was much handsomer
than Mr.
Bingley,
and he was looked
at with great admiration
for about half
the evening
till his manners
gave a disgust
which turned the tide
of his popularity.
For he was discovered
to be proud,
to be above his company
and above being pleased.
And not all
his large estate
in Derbyshire
could then save him
from having
a most forbidding,
disagreeable countenance
and being unworthy
to be compared
with his friend.
Mr.
Bingley had soon
made himself
acquainted
with all the principal
people in the room.
He was lively
and unreserved, danced
every dance, was angry
that the ball closed
so early
and talked
of giving one himself
at another field.
Such amiable qualities
must speak
for themselves.
What a contrast
between him
and his friend.
Mr.
Darcy
danced only
once with Mrs.
Hurst
and once with
Miss Bingley declined
being introduced
to any other lady
and spent the rest
of the evening
in walking
about the room, speaking
occasionally
to one of his own party.
His character
was decided
he was the proudest.
Most.
Disagreeable man
in the world,
and everybody hoped that
he would never
come there again.
Amongst the most violent
against him was Mrs.
Bennett.
Whose dislike of his.
General behavior
was sharpened
into particular
resentment
by his having slighted
one of her daughters.
Elizabeth Bennett
had been obliged
by the scarcity of.
Gentlemen to sit.
Down for two dances,
and during
part of that time, Mr.
Darcy had been standing
near enough
for her to hear a.
Conversation
between him and.
Mr.
Bingley,
who came from the dance
for a few minutes
to press his friend
to join it.
Come, Darcy.
Said he.
I must have you dance.
I hate to see you
standing about
by yourself in
this stupid manner.
You had much
better dance.
I certainly shall not.
You know
how I detest it.
Unless I am particularly
acquainted with
my partner
at such an assembly
as this,
it would be
insupportable.
Your sisters are engaged
and there is not
another woman
in the room
whom it would not be
a punishment to me
to stand up with.
I would not be
so fastidious
as you are.
Cried Bingley.
For a kingdom
upon my honor.
I never met with
so many pleasant
girls in my life
as I have this evening,
and there are several
of them
you see uncommonly
pretty.
You are dancing
with the only handsome
girl in the room.
Said Mr.
Darcy, looking
at the eldest,
Miss Bennet.
Oh, she is the most
beautiful creature
I ever beheld.
But there is one
of her
sisters sitting down
just behind you
who is very pretty
and I daresay,
very agreeable.
Do let me ask my partner
to introduce you.
Which
do you mean?
And turning round.
He looked for
a moment at Elizabeth
till catching her eye.
He withdrew his own
and coldly said.
She's tolerable
but not handsome
enough to tempt me.
And I am in no humor
at present
to give consequence
to young ladies
who are slighted
by other men.
You had better return
to your partner
and enjoy her smiles.
For you are wasting
your time with me.
Mr.
Bingley followed
his advice.
Mr.
Darcy walked off
and Elizabeth remained
with no
very cordial feelings
towards him.
She told the.
Story, however,
with great spirit
among her friends,
for she had a lively,
playful disposition,
which delighted
in anything ridiculous.
The evening
altogether passed off
pleasantly to
the whole family.
Mrs.
Bennet had seen
her eldest daughter,
much admired
by the
Netherfield party.
Mr.
Bingley
had danced
with her twice.
And she had
been distinguished
by his sisters.
Jane was as
much gratified by this
as her mother could.
Be, though in a.
Quieter way.
Elizabeth felt
Jane's pleasure.
Mary had heard herself
mentioned to
Miss Bingley
as the most
accomplished girl
in the neighborhood,
and Catherine and Lydia
had been fortunate
enough
never to be
without partners,
which was all that
they had yet
learned to care
for at a ball.
They returned, therefore
in good spirits
to long borne
the village
where they lived.
And of which.
They were
the principal
inhabitants.
They found Mr.
Bennett still up.
With. A book.
He was,
regardless of time,
and on the
present occasion
he had
a good deal of curiosity
as to the events
of an evening.
Which had raised.
Such splendid.
Expectations.
He had rather hoped
that his wife's views on
the stranger
would be disappointed.
But he soon.
Found out that
he had a different story
to hear.
Oh, my dear Mr.
Bennett,
as she entered the room.
We have
had a
most delightful evening,
a most excellent ball.
I wish you had been
there.
Jane was so admired.
Nothing could be
like it.
Everybody said how
well she looked, and Mr.
Bingley
thought her
quite beautiful
and danced
with her twice.
Only think of that,
my dear.
He actually danced
with her twice.
And she was
the only creature
in the room
that he asked
a second time.
First of all,
he asked Mr.
Lucas.
I was so Becks
to see him
stand up with her.
But however, he did
not admire her at all.
Indeed, nobody can,
you know.
And he seemed
quite struck with Jane
as she was
going down the dance.
So he inquired
who she was
and got introduced
and asked her
for the next two.
Then the two third,
he danced with Miss King
and the two fourth
Mariah Lucas
and the 2/5 Jane again.
And the two six with
Lizzie and the Bull.
If he had had any
compassion for me.
Cried her
husband impatiently.
He would not have danced
half so much.
For God's sake,
say no
more of his partners.
Oh, that he had sprained
his ankle
in the first dance.
Oh, my dear.
I am quite
delighted with him.
He is so excessively
handsome
and his sisters
are charming women.
I never in my life
saw anything
more elegant
than their dresses.
I dare say the lace
upon Mrs.
Hurst's gown.
Here she was interrupted
again. Mr.
Bennett
protested against
any description
of finery.
She was
therefore obliged
to seek
another branch
of the subject
and related.
With.
Much bitterness
of spirit
and some exaggeration.
The shocking rudeness
of Mr. Darcy.
But I can assure you,
she added,
that Lizzie
does not lose much
by not suiting
his fancy,
but he is a
most disagreeable,
horrid man.
Not at all
worth pleasing.
So high
and so conceited that
there was no
enduring him.
He walked here
and he walked
that fence,
seeing himself
so very great.
Not handsome
enough to dance with.
I wish you would
be there,
my dear,
to have given him
one of your such downs.
I quite
detest the man.
Chapter four.
When Jane and
Elizabeth were alone,
the former
who had been cautious
in her praise of Mr.
Bingley before,
expressed to her sister
just how very much
she admired him.
He is just what
a young man ought to be,
said she.
Sensible,
good humored.
Live li.
And I never saw such
happy madness.
So much ease
with such perfect
good breeding.
He is also handsome.
Replied Elizabeth.
Which young man ought.
Likewise to be
if he possibly.
Can.
His character is thereby
complete.
I was very much.
Flattered by his
asking me to dance.
A second time.
I did not expect
such a compliment.
Did not you?
I did for you.
But that is one great
difference between us.
Compliments always take
you by surprise.
And me? Never.
What could be
more natural.
That his asking you.
Again?
He could not
help, seeing
that you were
about five times
as pretty
as every other
woman in the room.
No thanks
to his gallantry
for that.
Well,
he certainly is
very agreeable.
And I give you leave to
like him.
You've liked
many a stupider person.
Dear Lizzie.
Oh, you are
a great deal.
Too apt,
you know,
to like
people in general.
You never see a fault
with anybody.
All the world are good
and agreeable
in your eyes.
I never heard you speak
ill of a human
being in your life.
I would not wish
to be hasty
in censuring anyone.
But I always speak
what I think.
I know you do.
And it is that which
makes the wonder
with your good sense
to be so honestly blind
to the follies
and nonsense of others.
Affectation
of candor is
common enough.
One meets
with it everywhere.
But to be candid,
without ostentation
or design,
to take the good
of everybody's character
and make
it still better,
and to say nothing.
Of the.
Bad belongs
to you alone.
And so you like
the Seven Sisters
to do you?
Their manners
are not equal to his.
Certainly
not at first.
But they are very
pleasing women
when you converse
with them.
Miss being
used to live
with her brother
and keep his house.
And I am much mistaken.
If we shall not find
a very charming neighbor
in her.
Elizabeth
listened in silence.
But.
Was not convinced.
Their behavior.
At the assembly
had not been calculated
to please in general,
and with more quickness
of observation
and less pliant
see of temper
than her sister,
and with a judgment
to un assailed
by any
attention to herself.
She was very
little disposed
to approve them.
They were, in fact,
very fine ladies.
Not deficient in.
Good humor
when they were. Pleased.
Nor in the power
of making
themselves agreeable
when they chose it.
But proud
and conceited.
They were rather
handsome,
had been educated
in one of the
first private
seminaries in town.
Had a fortune of.
?20,000, were
in the habit
of spending more than.
They ought and of.
Associating
with people of rank,
and were therefore, in
every respect entitled
to think
well of themselves
and meanly of others.
They were
of a respectable family
in the north of England,
a circumstance
more deeply
impressed on
their memories than that
their brothers, fortune
and their own
had been acquired
by trade.
Mr.
Bingley
inherited property
to the amount
of nearly ?100,000
from his father,
who had intended
to purchase an estate.
But did.
Not live to do it.
Mr.
Bingley intended it
likewise.
And sometimes.
Made a choice
of his county.
But as he now.
Was provided
with a good house
and the
liberty of a manor,
it was doubtful
to many of those
who best knew
the easiness
of his temper,
whether he
might not spend
the remainder
of his days
at Netherfield
and leave
the next generation
to purchase.
His sisters were anxious
for his having
an estate of his own,
but there he was, now
only established
as a tenant.
Miss Bingley
was by no means
unwilling
to preside at his table.
Nor was Mrs.
Hurst,
who had married
a man of more fashion
than fortune, less
disposed to
consider his house
as her home
when it suited her.
Mr.
Bingley had not
been of age to years
when he was tempted
by an
accidental
recommendation
to look at
Netherfield House.
He did look at it and.
In to it for
half an hour
was pleased
with the situation
and the principal rooms,
satisfied with what
the owner said
at its praise.
And took it.
Immediately.
Between him and Darcy,
there was a very
steady friendship,
in spite
of great opposition
of character.
Bingley was endeared
to Darcy
by the easiness.
Openness and.
Ductility of his temper.
Though no disposition.
Could offer
a greater contrast
to his own.
And though with his.
Own, he
never appeared
dissatisfied.
On the strength
of Darcy's regard.
Bingley had the
firmest reliance
and of his judgment,
the highest.
Opinion in.
Understanding that Darcy
was the superior.
Bingley was by
no means deficient, but
Darcy was clever.
He was at the same time
haughty, reserved
and fastidious.
And his manners, though
well-bred,
were not inviting.
In that respect,
his friend had greatly
the advantage.
Bingley was sure of
being liked
wherever he appeared.
Darcy was continually
giving offense.
The manner
in which they
spoke of the merit
and assembly
was sufficiently
characteristic.
Bingley had never met
with more
pleasant people
or prettier girls
in his life.
Everybody had
been most kind
and attentive to him.
There had been
no formality,
no stiffness.
He had soon.
Felt acquainted
with all the room.
And asked him
as Bennett.
He could not
conceive an.
Angel more beautiful.
Darcy,
on the contrary,
had seen a collection
of people in whom
there was little beauty
and no fashion,
for none of whom
he had felt
the smallest interest,
and from none received
either attention
or pleasure.
Miss Bennet.
He acknowledged
to be pretty.
But she smiled too
much.
Mrs.
Hurst
and her sister
allowed it to be so.
But still
they admired her
and liked her
and pronounced her
to be a sweet girl and.
One to whom
they would not object to
no more of.
Miss Bennet
was therefore
established
as a sweet girl,
and their brother felt
authorized by such.
Commendation to think.
Of her as he chose.
Chapter five.
Within a short
walk of long
born lived a family
with whom the Bennetts
were particularly
intimate.
Sir William Lucas
had been formerly
in trade in Meriton,
where he had made
a tolerable fortune
and risen to the honor
of knighthood
by an address
to the King
during his mayoralty.
The distinction had
perhaps been felt
too strongly.
It had given him
a disgust
to his business.
And.
To his residents
in a small market town.
And in quitting them
both,
he had removed with.
His family to a house
about a mile
from Meriton.
Denominated from that
period, Lucas Lodge,
where he could think
with pleasure
of his own importance.
And unshackled
by business, occupied.
Himself
solely in being civil
to all the world.
Four, Though
elated by his rank.
It did.
Not render him
supercilious.
On the contrary,
he was all attention
to everybody.
By.
Nature inoffensive,
friendly and obliging.
His presentation at St
James's had
made him courteous.
Lady Lucas
was a very good
kind of woman.
Not.
Too clever
to be a
valuable neighbor
to Mrs. Bennett.
They had
several children,
the eldest of them,
a sensible, intelligent
young woman, about 27,
was Elizabeth's
intimate friend.
That the Miss Lucas's.
And the Miss Bennet
should meet.
To talk over
a ball
was absolutely
necessary.
And the morning
after the assembly
brought the former
to longboard to hear
and to communicate.
You began the evening.
Well, Charlotte.
Said Mrs.
Bennett with Civil South
Command to Ms..
Lucas.
You were Mr.
Begley's first choice.
Yes.
But he seemed to like
his second better.
No, You mean Jane,
I suppose
because he danced
with her twice,
to be sure that it did
seem as if he
admired her.
Indeed.
I rather believe he did.
I heard
something about it,
but I hardly know what.
Something about Mr.
Robinson.
Perhaps you mean what
I overheard
between him and Mr.
Robinson.
Did not I mention it
to you, Mr.
Robinson, asking him how
he liked
our marriage
and assemblies
and whether he did
not think
there were a great many
pretty women in the room
and which he thought
the prettiest.
And his
answering immediately
to the last question.
Oh, the eldest,
Miss Bennett,
beyond a doubt.
That cannot be
to opinions
on that point.
Upon my word.
Well,
that is very decided
indeed.
That does seem as if.
But however
it may all
come to nothing,
you know.
My of the hearings
are more to the purpose
than yours.
Eliza.
Said Charlotte.
Mr.
Darcy is not so well
worth listening to
as his friend, is he?
For Eliza
to be only just
tolerable.
I beg
you, would not put into
Lizzie's head
to be vexed
by his ill treatment,
for he is
such a disagreeable man
that it would be
a quite a misfortune
to be liked by him.
Mrs.
Long told me last night
that he sat close to her
for half an hour without
once opening his lips.
He's quite sure
Mum is not
there a little mistake?
Said Jane.
I certainly saw Mr.
Darcy speaking to her.
I because she asked him
at last how he liked
know the field
and he could not
help answering her.
But she said
he seemed quite angry
at being spoken to.
Miss Bingley told me,
said Jane,
that he never
speaks much unless
among his
intimate acquaintances
with them
he is
remarkably agreeable.
No, I do not believe
a word of.
It's my dear.
If he had been
so very agreeable,
he would have
talked to Mrs.
Long.
But I can guess
how it was.
Everybody says that
he is at up with pride.
And I daresay he'd
heard somehow that Mrs.
Long was not to
keep a carriage
and had come to the
ball in a chaise.
I do not mind.
Is not talking to Mrs.
Long, said Miss Lucas.
But I wish
she had danced
with Eliza.
Another time, Lizzie.
Said her mother.
I would not dance
with him if I were you.
I believe,
ma'am,
I may safely promise
you never to dance
with him.
His pride,
said, Miss Lucas,
does not offend me
so much
as pride often does,
because there
is an excuse for it.
One cannot wonder that.
So very fine.
A young man
with family fortune.
Everything in his favor
should think
very highly of himself.
If I may so express it.
He has a right
to be proud.
And that is very true.
Replied Elizabeth.
And I could easily
forgive his pride
if he had not
mortified mine.
Pride.
Observed Mary,
who peeked herself upon
the solidity
of her reflections.
Is a very common
fanning, I believe,
by all that
I have ever read.
I am convinced that
it is very common indeed
that human nature
is particularly
prone to it,
and that there are very
few of us
who do not cherish
a feeling
of self complacency
on the score
of some quality
or other,
real or imaginary.
Vanity and pride
are different things,
though
the words are often used
anonymously.
A person may be proud
without being vain.
Pride relates
more to our opinion
of ourselves.
Vanity
to what
we would have others
think of us.
If I were as rich as Mr.
Darcy.
Cried a young Lucas
who came with
his sisters.
I should not care
how proud I was.
I would keep a pack
of fox hounds
and drink a
bottle of wine
every day.
Then you would drink
a great
deal more than you
ought, said Mrs.
Bennet.
And if I were to see you
at it,
I should take away
your bottle directly.
The boy protested
that she should not.
She continued.
To declare that she.
Would.
And the argument
ended only
with the visit.
Chapter six.
The ladies of Long
Borne soon
waited on
those of Netherfield.
The visit was soon
returned in due form.
Miss Bennet's
pleasing manners
grew on the goodwill
of Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley.
And though
the mother was found
to be intolerable
and the younger sister
is not worth
speaking to.
A wish.
Of being better
acquainted with
than was expressed
towards the two eldest.
By. Jane.
This attention
was received
with the
greatest pleasure.
But Elizabeth still
saw supercilious ness
in their treatment
of everybody, hardly
excepting
even her sister,
and could not like them.
Though
their kindness to Jane,
such as it was,
had a value as arising
in all probability
from the influence
of their brother's
admiration.
It was generally evident
whenever they met
that he did admire her,
and to her
it was equally evident
that Jane was yielding
to the preference
which she had begun
to entertain for him
from the first
and was in a way
to be very much in love.
But she considered with
pleasure
that it was not likely
to be discovered
by the world in general.
Since Jane united
with great strength
of feeling a composure
of temper and a uniform
cheerfulness of manner
which would guard her
from the suspicions
of the impertinent.
She mentioned this
to her friend,
Miss Lucas.
It may perhaps
be pleasant,
replied Charlotte.
To be able
to impose on the public.
In such a case.
But it is
sometimes a disadvantage
to be so very guarded.
If a woman conceals
her affection.
With the same
skill from the.
Object of it,
she may lose the
opportunity of
fixing him.
And it will then
be that poor consolation
to believe the world
equally in the dark.
There is so much of.
Gratitude or vanity.
In almost
every attachment
that it is not safe.
To leave any to.
Itself.
We can all begin freely
a slight preference
is natural enough,
but there are very
few of us
who are part enough
to be really in love
without encouragement.
In nine cases
out of ten.
A woman had better show.
More affection
than she feels.
Bingley likes
your sister,
undoubtedly,
but he may never
do more than like her
if she does not
help him on
and that she does
as much as the nature
will allow.
If I can perceive her
regard for him,
he must be a simpleton
indeed not to
discover it. To
remember Eliza,
that he does not know
Jane's disposition
as you do.
But if a woman
is partial to a man
and does
not endeavor
to conceal it,
he must find it out.
Perhaps he must,
if he sees
enough of her.
But there being the end,
Jane, meet
tolerably often.
It has never for.
Many hours together.
And as they always
see each other in large
mixed parties,
it is impossible
that every moment
should be employed
in conversing together.
Jane should therefore
make the
most of every half hour
in which
he can command
his attention
when she is
secure of him.
There should be
more leisure
for falling in love
as much as she chooses.
New plan is a good one,
said Elizabeth.
Where
nothing is in question
but the.
Desire of being, well.
Married.
And if I were determined
to get a rich husband
or any husband,
I daresay
I should adopt it.
But these are not
Jane's feelings.
She is not acting
by design.
As yet,
she can not
even be certain
of the degree
of her own regard, nor
of its reasonableness.
She has known him
only a fortnight.
She danced for dances
with him at Maritain.
She saw him one morning
at his own house
and has since dined
with him in company
four times.
This is not quite enough
to make her understand
his character,
not as you represent it.
Had she
merely dined with him,
she might.
Only have discovered
whether he had a good.
Appetite.
But you must remember
that four evenings
have also
been spent together
and for evenings.
May do a great.
Deal.
Yes, these four evenings
have.
Enabled them
to ascertain
that they both like
Van Taylor
better than Commerce.
But with respect.
To any other leading.
Characteristic,
I do not imagine that
much has been unfolded.
Well said, Charlotte.
I wish
Jane success with.
All my heart.
And if she were married
to him tomorrow,
I should.
Think she had as good
a chance of.
Happiness
as if she were
to be studying
his character
for a 12 month.
Happiness in marriage
is entirely
a matter of chance.
If the dispositions
of the parties are ever
so well
known to each other
or ever so similar
beforehand,
it does not advance
their felicity
in the least.
They always continue
to grow sufficiently
unlike afterwards
to have their
share of vexation.
And it is better to.
Know as little
as possible of the.
Defects of the person
with whom
you ought to cast
your life.
You make me
laugh, Charlotte.
But it is not sound.
You know
it is not sound.
And that you would never
act in this
way yourself.
Occupied in
observing Mr.
Bigley's attentions
to her sister.
Elizabeth was far from
suspecting
that she was herself
becoming an object
of some interest
in the eyes
of his friend.
Mr.
Darcy had at
first scarcely
allowed her
to be pretty.
He had looked at her
without admiration
and at the ball.
And when they next met,
he looked at her
only to criticize.
But no sooner had
he made it
clear to himself
and his friends
that she hardly
had a good feature
in her face.
Then he began to find
it was rendered
uncommonly intelligent
by the
beautiful expression
of her dark eyes.
To this discovery
succeeded
some others
equally mortifying.
Though he had detected
with a critical eye
more than one failure
of perfect
symmetry in her form.
He was forced
to acknowledge her
figure to be
light and pleasing,
and in spite of his
asserting that
her manners
were not those
of the
fashionable world.
He was caught
by their easy
playfulness.
Of this,
she was
perfectly unaware.
To her,
he was only the man
who made
himself agreeable
nowhere
and who had not thought
her handsome enough
to dance with.
He began to wish
to know.
More of her
and as a step towards
conversing
with her himself,
attended to
her conversation
with others.
His doing so
drew her notice.
It was at Sir
William Lucas's where a
large party
were assembled.
What does Mr.
Darcy mean?
Said she.
To Charlotte.
By listening
to my conversation
with Colonel Foster.
That is a question
which only Mr.
Darcy can answer.
But if he does it
any more,
I shall certainly
let him know that
I see what he is about.
He has a very
satirical eye.
And if I do not
begin by.
Being
impertinent myself.
I shall soon grow
afraid of him.
On his approaching them
soon afterwards, though,
without seeming
to have any intention
of speaking.
Miss Lucas defied her
friend to mention
such a subject to him,
which immediately
provoking
Elizabeth to do it.
She turned to him
and said.
Did you not think, Mr.
Darcy,
that I expressed myself
uncommonly well just now
when I was teasing
Colonel Foster
to give us all
a ball at Meriton.
With great energy.
But it is
a subject
which always makes
a lady energetic.
He was severe on us.
It will be her turn soon
to be teased, said Ms..
Lucas.
I am going to open
the instrument, Eliza.
And you know
what follows.
You are a
very strange creature
by way of a friend
always wanting me
to play
and sing before anybody
and everybody.
If my vanity had taken
a musical turn,
you would have
been invaluable.
But as it is,
I would really
rather not
sit down
before those
who must be in the habit
of hearing
the very
best performers.
On Miss Lucas
is persevering, however,
she added.
Very well.
If it must be so,
it must.
And gravely
glancing at Mr.
Darcy.
There is a fine old.
Saying
which everybody here is,
of course,
familiar with.
Keep your breath
to cool your porridge
and I shall keep mine.
To spell my song.
Her performance
was pleasing,
though
by no means capital
after a song or two
and before
she could reply
to the entreaties
of several
that she would
sing again,
she was
eagerly succeeded
at the instrument
by her sister Mary,
who, having
in consequence
of being the only plain
one in the family,
worked hard
for knowledge
and accomplishments,
was always impatient
for display.
Mary had neither
genius nor taste,
and though vanity
given her application.
It had given.
Her likewise a pedantic
and conceited manner,
which would have ensured
a higher degree
of excellence
than she had reached.
Elizabeth.
Easy and unaffected
she had been listened to
with much more
pleasure, though
not playing
half so well.
And Mary,
at the end of
a long concerto,
was glad
to purchase
praise and gratitude
by Scotch and Irish ears
at the request of her
younger sisters, who,
with some of the Lucas's
and two or three.
Officers, joined.
Eagerly in
dancing at one
end of the room.
Mr.
Darcy stood
near them
in silent indignation
at such a mode
of passing the.
Evening to the.
Exclusion
of all conversation,
and was too
much engrossed
by his thoughts
to perceive that Sir
William Lucas
was his neighbor.
Till Sir William thus
began.
What a charming
amusement
for young people.
This is Mr.
Darcy.
There is nothing
like dancing after all.
I consider it
as one of the
first refinements
of polished societies.
Certainly, sir.
And it has the advantage
also of being in vogue
amongst the less
polished societies
of the world.
Every savage can dance.
Sir William
only smiled.
Your friend
performs delightfully.
He continued
after a pause
on seeing Bingley
join the group.
And I doubt
not that
you are an adept
in the science
yourself, Mr.
Darcy.
You saw me dance
at merit,
I believe, sir.
Yes, indeed.
And received
no inconsiderable
pleasure from the sight.
Do you often dance at St
James's?
Never, sir.
Do you not think
it would be
a proper
complement to the place?
It is a compliment
which I never
pay to any place
if I can avoid it.
You have
a house in town,
I conclude.
Mr.
Darcy bowed.
I had one.
Some thoughts
of fixing in town
myself, for
I am fond of
superior society,
but I did not feel
quite certain
that the Air of London
would agree
with Lady Lucas.
He paused in
hopes of an answer,
but his companion
was not disposed
to make any,
and Elizabeth,
at that instant,
moving towards them.
He was struck
with the notion
of doing
a very gallant thing
and called out to her.
My dear Miss Eliza,
why are not you dancing,
Mr. Darcy?
You must allow me
to present this
young lady to you
as a very
desirable partner.
You cannot refuse
to dance.
I'm sure,
when so much beauty
is before you.
And taking her hand.
He would have
given it to Mr.
Darcy, who, though
extremely surprised,
was not unwilling
to receive it.
When she instantly
drew back and said with
some dis composure
to Sir William.
Indeed, sir.
I have not the
least intention
of dancing.
I entreat you
not to suppose
that I moved this way
in order to beg
for a partner.
Mr.
Darcy,
with grave propriety
requested to be allowed
the honor of her hand.
But. In vain.
Elizabeth was
determined.
Nor did Sir
William at all
shake her purpose
by his attempt
at persuasion.
Excel
so much in the dance,
Miss Eliza,
that it is cruel
to deny me the happiness
of seeing you.
And though
this gentleman dislikes
the amusements
in general,
he can have
no objection.
I am sure to oblige us
for one half hour.
Mr.
Darcy is all politeness.
Said Elizabeth, smiling.
He is indeed.
But considering
the inducement, my dear
Miss Eliza,
we cannot wonder
at his complacence
for who would object
to such a partner.
Elizabeth looked archly
and turned away
her resistance,
as had not injured her
with the gentleman,
and he was
thinking of her
with some complacency
when thus accosted
by Miss Bingley.
I can guess the subject
of your reverie.
I should imagine not.
You are considering
how insupportable
it would be to pass
many evenings
in this manner.
In such society.
And indeed, I.
Am quite
of your opinion.
I was never more
annoyed the insipidity
and hear to the noise
than nothingness.
And yet
the self-importance
of all those people.
What would I give
to hear your strictures
on them?
Your conjecture
is totally wrong.
I assure you
my mind was
more agreeably engaged.
I have been meditating
on the
very great pleasure,
which a pair
of fine eyes in the face
of a pretty
woman can bestow.
Miss Bingley immediately
fixed her
eyes on his face
and desired
he would tell her
what lady
had the credit
of inspiring
such reflections.
Mr.
Darcy replied
with great intrepid
pity.
Miss Elizabeth Bennett.
Mrs.
Lizabeth Bennett.
Repeated Miss Bingley.
I am all astonishment.
How long has she been
such a favorite
and prey?
When am I
to wish you joy?
That Is exactly
the question
which I expected you
to ask.
A lady's
imagination is
very rapid.
It jumps from admiration
to love.
From love to matrimony
in a moment.
I knew you would be
wishing me joy.
Nay, if you are serious
about it,
I shall consider.
The matter
is absolutely settled.
You will be having
a charming mother
in law.
Indeed.
And of course,
she will
always be
at Pemberley with you.
He listened to her
with perfect
indifference
while she chose
to entertain herself
in this manner,
and as his composure
convinced her
that all was safe, her
wit flowed along.
Chapter seven
Mr.
Bennett's
property consisted
almost entirely
in an estate of 2000
a year,
which unfortunately for
his daughters,
was entailed in
default of heirs mail
on a distant relation
and their
mother's fortune.
Though ample
for his situation
in life
could but ill supply
the deficiency of his.
Her father had been
an attorney in Meriton
and had left her ?4,000.
She had a sister
married to a mr.
Phillips
who had been a clerk
to their father
and succeeded him
in the business,
and her brother
settled in London
in a respectable
line of trade.
The village of
Long Bourn
was only one
mile from Meriton.
A most convenient.
Distance
for the young ladies
who were usually tempted
thither three
or four times a week
to pay their duty
to their aunt
and to a milliners shop.
Just over the way
the two youngest
of the family Catherine
and Lydia
were particularly
frequent
in these attentions.
Their minds
were more vacant
than their sisters,
and when nothing better
offered a walk to
Meriton was necessary
to amuse their
morning hours
and furnish conversation
for the evening.
And however bare of news
the country
in general might.
Be, they always.
Contrive to learn some
from their aunt
at present.
Indeed,
they were well supplied,
both with news
and happiness
by the recent arrival
of a militia regiment
in the neighborhood.
It was to remain
the whole winter,
and Burton was
the headquarters.
Their visits to Mrs.
Phillips were now
productive of the most
interesting
intelligence.
Every day
added something
to their knowledge
of the officers
names and connections.
Their lodgings were
not long a secret,
and at length
they began to know
the officers themselves.
Mr.
Phillips
visited them all.
And this open to
his niece
is a story
of Felicity, unknown.
They could talk
of nothing but officers
and Mr. Big.
These large fortune,
the mention
of which gave
animation to
their mother,
was worthless
in their eyes
when opposed to
the regimental odds
of an ensign.
After listening
one morning
to their effusions
on this subject.
Mr.
Bennett coolly observed.
From all that
I can collect
by your manner
of talking,
you must be
two of the
silliest girls
in the country.
I have suspected it
some time, but I am now
convinced.
Catherine
was disconcerted
and made no answer.
But with
perfect indifference,
continued to express her
admiration
of Captain Carter
and her hope
of seeing him
in the course of the day
as he was going
the next morning
to London.
I am astonished,
my dear, said Mrs..
Bennett.
That you should be
so ready
to think
your own children silly.
If I wish to think
slighting
of anybody's children,
it should not be
of my own.
However.
If my children
are silly,
I must hope to be
always sensible of it.
Yes, but
as it happens,
they are all of them.
Very clever.
This is the only point
I flatter myself
on which we
do not agree.
I had hoped
that our sentiments
coincided
in every particular,
but I must so far differ
from use
to think our
two youngest daughters
uncommonly foolish.
My dear Mr.
Bennett, you must not
expect such girls
to have the.
Sense of their
father and.
Mother
when they get
to our age.
I dare say
they will not think
about officers
any more than we do.
I remember the time
when I liked
a red coat myself
very well,
and indeed so
I do still at my heart.
And if a smart
young colonel
with five or 6000
a year
should want one
of my girls,
I shall not say
nay to him.
And I thought,
Colonel Force
looked very becoming
the other night
at the Williams
in his regimental
mama.
Cried Lydia.
My aunt.
Says that Colonel.
Foster
and Captain
Carter do not go
so often, Miss Watson's,
as they did
when they first came.
She sees them now,
very often,
standing in
Clark's library.
Mrs.
Bennett was prevented,
replying
by the entrance
of the footman
with a note
from Bennett.
It came from.
Netherfield,
and the servant
waited for an answer.
Mrs.
Bennett's eyes
sparkled with pleasure,
and she was eagerly
calling out
while her daughter read.
Well, Jane,
who is it from?
What is it about?
What does he say?
Well, Jane, make haste
and tell us.
Make haste, my love.
It is from Miss Bingley.
That Jane,
and then read it aloud.
My dear friend,
if you are not so
compassionate as.
To dine today with.
Louisa and me,
we shall be in danger
of hating.
Each other
for the rest
of our lives.
For a whole day's tete
a tete between two women
can never end
without a quarrel.
Come as soon as you can.
On receipt of this,
my brother
and the gentleman
out to dine
with the officers.
Josepha
Caroline Bingley
with the officer's,
cried Lydia.
I wonder.
My aunt
did not tell us at that
dining out, said Mrs.
Bennett.
That is very unlucky.
Can I have the carriage?
Said Jane.
No, my dear,
you had
better go on horseback
because it seems likely
to rain.
And then you must stay
all night.
And that would be
a good scheme.
Said.
Elizabeth.
If you.
Were sure
that they would not.
Offer to send her home.
Oh, but
the gentleman
will have Mr.
Bingley
Shays to go to Mountain
and the hosts have no
horses to theirs.
I had much rather
go in the coach.
But, my dear,
your father
cannot spare the horses.
I am sure they are
wanted in the fall, Mr.
Bennett, are they not?
They are wanted
in the farm much oftener
than I can get them.
But if you have got them
today, said Elizabeth.
My mother's purpose
would be answered.
She did at last
extort from her father
an acknowledgment
that the horses
were engaged.
Jane was therefore
obliged
to go on horseback
and her mother
attended her to the door
with many cheerful
prognostic cause
of a bad day.
Her hopes were answered.
Jane had not been gone
long before
it rained hard.
Her sisters
were uneasy for her,
but her mother
was delighted.
The rain continued
the whole evening
without intermission.
Jane certainly
could not come back.
This was a
lucky idea of mine.
Indeed.
Said Mrs.
Bennett,
more than once, as if
the credit
of making it rain
were all her own.
Till the next morning,
however,
she was not aware
of all the felicity
of her contrivance.
Breakfast was scarcely
over when a servant
from Netherfield
brought the
following note
for Elizabeth.
My dearest Lizzie.
I find myself
very unwell
this morning.
Which I suppose is to.
Be imputed
to my getting wet
through yesterday.
My kind friends
will not hear
my returning.
To lie in. Better.
They insist
also on my seeing Mr.
Jones.
Therefore,
do not be alarmed
if you should hear
of his
having been to see me
and excepting
a sore throat
and headache.
There is not much
the matter with me,
yours, etc..
Well, my dear.
Said Mr.
Bennett,
when Elizabeth had read
the note aloud.
If your daughter
should have
a dangerous
fit of illness,
if she should die,
it would be a comfort
to know
that it was
all in pursuit of Mr.
Bingley
and under your orders.
Oh, I am not
afraid of her dying
People do not die
of little
trifling colds.
She would be taken
good care of.
As long as she stays.
There.
It is all very well.
I would go and see her
if I could have
the carriage.
Elizabeth,
feeling really anxious,
was determined
to go to her,
though the carriage
was not to be had.
And as she was, no,
horsewoman walking
was her
only alternative.
She declared
her resolution.
How can you be
so silly?
Cried her mother.
As to think of
such a thing
in all this dirt.
You will not be fit
to be seen
when you get there.
I shall be very
fit to see Jane,
which is all I want.
Is this a hint to me,
Lizzie?
Said her father.
To send for the horses.
No, indeed.
I do not wish to avoid.
The walk.
The distance is nothing.
When one has a motive.
Only three miles.
I shall be
back by dinner.
I admire the activity
of you and evidence,
observed Mary.
But every impulse,
a feeling,
should be guided
by reason.
And in my opinion,
exertion
should always
be in proportion to
what is required.
We would go
as far as merit.
And with you, said
Catherine and Lydia.
Elizabeth
accepted their company
and the three
young ladies
set off together.
If we make haste.
Said Lydia,
as they walked along,
perhaps you may see
something of Captain.
Carter before he goes.
In.
Merritt and they parted.
The two youngest
repaired to the lodgings
of one of
the officer's wives.
And Elizabeth
continued her
walk alone, crossing
field after
field at a quick pace,
jumping over styles
and springing
over puddles
with impatient activity.
And finding.
Herself at last within
view of the house
with weary ankles,
dirty stockings
and a face glowing
with the warmth
of exercise.
She was.
Shown into the
breakfast parlor
where all but
Jane were assembled
and where her appearance
created
a great deal
of surprise.
That she should
have walked.
Three miles
so early in the day
in such dirty weather
and by herself was.
Almost.
Incredible to Mrs.
Hurst and Mrs.
Bingley.
And Elizabeth
was convinced
that they held her
in contempt for it.
She was received.
However,
very politely by them
and in their brothers
manners.
There was something
better than politeness.
There was good
humor and kindness.
Mr.
Darcy said Very little.
And Mr.
Hurst, nothing at all.
The former was divided
between admiration
of the brilliancy,
which exercise
had given
to her complexion
and doubt
as to the occasions
justifying her
coming so far alone.
The latter was thinking
only of his breakfast.
Her inquiries
after her
sister were not very
favorably answered.
Miss Bennett
had slept ill,
and though
up was very feverish.
And not.
Well enough to leave
her room.
Elizabeth was glad
to be taken
to her immediately.
And Jane,
who had only
been withheld
by the fear
of giving alarm
or inconvenience
or expressing
in her note
how much she longed
for such a visit.
Was delighted
at her entrance.
She was not.
Equal, however,
to much conversation.
And when Miss Bingley
left them together
could attempt
little
besides expressions
of gratitude
for the
extraordinary kindness
she was treated with.
Elizabeth silently
attended her.
When breakfast was over,
they were joined
by the sisters.
And Elizabeth began
to like them herself.
When she saw how.
Much affection
and solicitude
they showed for Jane.
The apothecary came
had, having examined
his patient,
said, as
might be supposed.
That she.
Had caught
a violent cold
and that
they must endeavor
to get the better of it.
Advise her
to return to bed
and promised her
some drafts.
The advice was followed
readily
for the
feverish symptoms
increased and her head
ached acutely.
Elizabeth did not
quit her room
for a moment.
Nor were the
other ladies
often absent.
The gentleman being out,
they had in fact,
nothing to do elsewhere.
When the clock
struck three,
Elizabeth felt
that she must go
and very unwillingly
said so.
Miss Bingley
offered her the carriage
and she only wanted
a little pressing
to accept it.
When Jane testified,
such concern
in parting with her
that Miss Bingley
was obliged
to convert
the offer of the shares
to an invitation
to remain
at Netherfield
for the present,
Elizabeth most
thankfully, consented,
and a servant
was dispatched
along, born
to acquaint the family
with her
stay and bring back
a supply of clothes.
Chapter eight.
At 5:00,
the two ladies
retired to dress,
and at 6:30,
Elizabeth was summoned
to dinner
to the civil inquiries,
which then poured in,
and amongst
which she had
the pleasure
of distinguishing
the much superior
solicitude of Mr.
Bingley.
She could not make
a very favorable answer.
Jane was by
no means better.
The sisters,
on hearing this repeated
three or four times,
how much they
were grieved,
how shocking it was
to have a bad cold, and.
How excessively.
They disliked
being ill themselves
and then thought no
more of the matter
and their
indifference
towards Jane
when not immediately
before them
restored Elizabeth
to the enjoyment
of all
her former dislike.
Their brother indeed
was the only
one of the party
whom she could regard
with any complacency.
His anxiety for
Jane was evident
and his attentions
to herself
most pleasing,
and they prevented her
feeling herself
so much an intruder
as she believed
she was considered
by the others.
She had very
little notice
from any but him.
Miss Bingley
was engrossed by Mr.
Darcy,
her sister scarcely less
so, and asked for Mr.
Hirst,
by whom Elizabeth sat.
He was an indolent man
who lived.
Only to eat.
Drink and play at cards.
Who, when he found her
to prefer a plain
dish to a ragout,
had nothing to say
to her.
When dinner was over,
she returned
directly to Jane
and Ms..
Bingley began
abusing her.
As soon as she was
out of the. Room.
Her manners
were pronounced
to be very bad indeed.
A mixture of pride
and impertinence.
She had no conversation,
no style, no beauty.
Mrs.
thought
the same and added.
She has nothing in short
to recommend her.
But being an excellent
walker,
I shall never forget
to her parents.
This morning,
she really looked
almost wild.
Oh, she did
indeed, Louisa.
I could hardly keep
my countenance.
Very nonsensical
to come at all.
Why must she
be scampering
about the country?
Because her
sister had a cold,
her hair so untidy,
so blousy.
Oh, yes.
And a petticoat.
I hope you saw her
petticoat six
inches deep in mud.
I'm absolutely certain.
And the gown
which had
been let down to hide
it not doing its office.
Your picture may
be very exact, Louisa,
said Bingley.
But this was all lost
upon me.
I thought Miss Elizabeth
Bennet looked remarkably
well when she came
into the room
this morning.
Her dirty
petticoat quite
escaped my notice.
You observed it, Mr.
Darcy?
I'm sure,
said Miss Bingley,
and I am inclined
to think
that you would not wish
to see your sister
make such an exhibition.
Certainly
not to walk three miles
or four miles
or five miles, whatever
it is, above her
ankles in dirt.
And to learn one
quite alone.
What could she mean
by it?
It seems to me
to show
an abominable, sort
of conceited
independence.
Her most country town
indifference to decorum.
It shows an affection
for her sister.
That is very pleasing.
Said Bingley.
I am afraid, Mr.
Darcy.
Observed Miss Bingley
in a half, whisper.
That this.
Adventure
has rather affected.
Your admiration
of her fine eyes.
Not at all.
He replied.
They were brightened
by the exercise.
A short pause
followed the speech,
and Mrs.
Hurst began again.
I have an
excessive regard
for Miss Jane Bennet.
She is really a
very sweet girl,
and I wish
with all my heart
she be well settled.
But with such a.
Father and.
Mother in such
low connections.
I am afraid there is
no chance of it.
I think I've heard
you say that
their uncle
is an attorney
in Meriton.
Yes.
And they have another
who lives somewhere near
Cheapside.
That is capital.
Added her sister,
and they both laughed
heartily.
If they had uncles
enough to fill
all Cheapside.
Cried Bingley.
It would not make them
one jot less agreeable.
But it must very
materially lessen
their chance
of marrying men of any
consideration in
the world.
Replied Darcy
to this speech,
Bingley made no answer,
but his sisters gave it
their hearty assent
and indulged
their mirth.
For some
at the expense
of their dear friends.
Vulgar relations
with a renewal
of tenderness, however.
They returned
to her room
on leaving the
dining parlor
and sat with her
till summoned to coffee.
She was
still very poorly,
and Elizabeth
would not
quit her at all
till late in
the evening,
when she had the comfort
of seeing her asleep
and when it seemed
to her rather right
and pleasant
that she should go
downstairs herself.
On entering
the drawing room,
she found
the whole party a clue
and was immediately
invited to join them,
but suspecting them
to be playing high,
she declined. It
and making her
sister, the.
Excuse, said
she would amuse.
Herself
for the short time.
She could stay
below with a book.
Mr.
Hurst looked at her
with astonishment.
Do you prefer
reading to cards?
Said he.
That is rather singular.
Miss Eliza Bennet said
Miss Bingley
despises cards.
She is a great reader
and has no pleasure
in anything else.
I deserve neither
such praise
nor such censure.
Cried Elizabeth.
I am not a great reader
and I have pleasure
in many things.
In nursing your sister,
I am sure you have
pleasure.
Said Bingley.
And I hope
it will soon
be increased
by seeing her
quite well.
Elizabeth
thanked him
from her heart
and then walked towards
the table
where a
few books were lying.
He immediately offered
to fetch the others,
all that his
library afforded.
And I wish my collection
were larger
for your benefit
and my own credit.
But I am an idle fellow,
and though
I have not
many,
I have more
than I ever looked into.
Elizabeth assured him
that she could
suit herself
perfectly with
those in the room.
I am astonished,
said Miss Bingley,
that my father
should have left
so small.
A collection of books.
What a
delightful library
you have at
Pemberley, Mr.
Darcy.
It ought to be good,
he replied.
It has been the work
of many generations.
And then you have added
so much to it yourself.
You are always
buying books.
I cannot comprehend
the neglect
of a family library
in such days as these
neglect.
I I'm sure you neglect
nothing that can add
to the beauties
of that noble place.
Charles, when you
build your house,
I wish it may be half
as delightful
as Pemberley.
I wish it may.
But I would really
advise you
to make your purchase
in that neighborhood
and take Pemberley
for a kind of model.
There's not a
finer county in England
than Derbyshire.
With all my
heart, I will
buy Pemberley itself
if Darcy will sell it.
I am talking
of possibilities,
Charles.
Upon my word, Caroline.
I should think
it more possible
to get Pemberley
by purchase
than by imitation.
Elizabeth was
so much caught
with what passed
as to leave
for very
little attention
for her book.
And.
Soon laying it
wholly aside.
She drew
near the car table
and stationed herself
between Mr.
Bingley
and his eldest sister
to observe the game.
Is Ms..
Darcy much grown
since the spring?
Said Ms.
Bingley.
Will she be
as tall as I am?
I think she will.
She is now about Miss
Elizabeth
Bennet's height,
or rather taller.
How I longed
to see her again.
I never met with anybody
who delighted me
as much.
Such a countenance,
such manners,
and so
extremely accomplished
for her age.
Her performance on
the pianoforte is
exquisite.
It is amazing to me,
said Bingley.
How young ladies
can have patience
to be
so very accomplished
as they all are.
All young
ladies accomplished.
My dear Charles,
what do you mean?
Yes, all of them,
I think.
They all paint
tables, cover screens
and net purses.
I scarcely know
anyone who cannot do
all this.
And I am sure
I never heard
a young lady
spoken of
for the first time
without being informed
that she was
very accomplished.
Your list of the common
extent of
accomplishments
said Darcy,
has too much truth.
The word is applied
to many
a woman who deserves it
no otherwise
than by netting a purse
or covering a screen.
But I am very far
from agreeing with you
in your estimation
of ladies in general.
I cannot boast of
knowing more
than half a dozen
in the whole range
of my acquaintance that
are really accomplished.
Nor I,
I am sure.
Said Ms..
Bingley,
then observed Elizabeth.
You must comprehend
great deal in your idea
of an
accomplished woman.
Yes, I do comprehend
a great deal in it.
Though.
Certainly.
Cried
his faithful assistant.
No one can really be
esteemed, accomplished,
who does
not greatly surpass,
which is usually met
with a woman,
must have a thorough
knowledge of music.
Singing, drawing,
dancing
in the modern languages
to deserve the word.
And besides all this,
she must possess
a certain
something in her air
and manner of walking.
The tone of her voice,
her dress
and expressions
or the word will be
but half deserved.
All this
she must possess.
Added Darcy.
And to all
she must yet
add something
more substantial
in the improvement
of her
mind by
extensive reading.
I am no.
Longer surprised at.
Your knowing only six
accomplished women.
I rather wonder now
at your knowing any.
Are you so severe upon
your own sex as to doubt
the possibility
of all this?
I never saw
such a woman.
such capacity and taste.
And application
and elegance as.
You describe United.
Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley
both cried out
against the injustice
of her implied doubt
and were both protesting
that they knew
many women
who answered
this description.
When Mr.
Hurst called them
to order with bitter
complaints
of their inattention
to what was
going forward,
as all conversation
was thereby at an end,
Elizabeth
soon afterwards
left the room.
Elizabeth Bennett
said Miss Bingley,
when the door was closed
on her.
Is one of those
young ladies
who seek to recommend.
Themselves
to the other sex
by undervaluing.
Their own herd.
With many men,
I dare say it succeeds.
But in my opinion,
it is a paltry device.
A very mean art.
Undoubtedly, replied.
Darcy, to whom
this remark
was chiefly addressed.
There is a meanness
in all the arts
which ladies
sometimes condescend
to employ
for captivation.
Whatever Barnes affinity
to cunning
is despicable.
Ms..
Bingley was not
so entirely satisfied
with this reply
as to continue
the subject.
Elizabeth
joined them again,
only to say that
her sister was worse
and that she could
not leave her
being the urged Mr.
Jones
being sent
for immediately
while
his sister is convinced
that no country advice
could be of any service
recommended
and expressed to town
for one
of the most
eminent physicians.
This
she would not hear of.
But she was not
so unwilling
to comply
with her
brother's proposal,
and it was settled
that Mr.
Jones should be sent
for early
in the morning.
If Miss Bennett were not
decidedly better.
Bingley
was quite uncomfortable.
His sisters declared
that they were
miserable.
They saw this
to their wretchedness,
however, by duets
after supper,
while he could find
no better relief
to his feelings
than by giving
his housekeeper
directions
that every attention
might be paid
to the sick lady
and her sister.
Chapter nine.
Elizabeth
passed the chief
of the night
in her sister's room
and in the morning
had the pleasure
of being able
to send
a tolerable answer
to the inquiries
which she very
early received from Mr.
Bingley by a housemaid,
and sometime afterwards
from the
two elegant ladies
who waited
on his sisters.
In spite
of this amendment,
however, she requested
to have a note
sent along borne
desiring her
mother to visit Jane
and form her
own judgment
of her situation.
The note was immediately
dispatched
and its contents.
As quickly
complied with.
Mrs.
Bennett, accompanied
by her two
youngest girls,
reached Netherfield
soon after the family
breakfast.
Had she found Jane in
any apparent
danger, Mrs.
Bennett
would have been
very miserable.
But being satisfied on
seeing her
that her illness
was not alarming.
She had no wish of her
recovering immediately
as her restoration
to health
would probably
remove her
from Netherfield.
She would not
listen, therefore,
to her daughter's
proposal of
being carried home.
Neither did
the apothecary,
who arrived
about the same time
think it at
all advisable.
After sitting a
little while
with Jane
on Miss Bingley
appearance
and invitation.
The mother
and three daughters
all attended her
into the
breakfast parlor.
Bingley met them
with hopes that Mrs.
Bennett had
not found Ms..
Bennett worse
than she expected.
Indeed
I have, sir.
Was her answer.
She is a great deal too
ill to be moved.
Mr.
Jones says we must not
think of moving her.
We must trespass
a little longer
on your kindness.
Removed.
Cried Bingley.
It must not
be thought of.
My sister, I am sure,
will not hear
of her removal.
You may depend
upon it, madam.
Said Miss Bingley,
with cold civility.
That Miss Bennett
will receive
every possible attention
while she
remains with us.
Mrs.
Bennett was profuse
in her acknowledgments.
I am sure, she added,
If it were not
for such good friends,
I do not know
what would
become of her.
For she is very
ill indeed and suffers
a vast deal.
The greatest
patients in the world,
which is always the way
with her,
for she has,
without exception,
the sweetest temper
I have ever met with.
I often tell
my other girls
that they are
nothing to her.
You have a sweet room
here, Mr.
Bingley,
and a charming prospect
over the gravel walk.
I do not know
a place in the country
that is equal
to Netherfield.
You will not think of
quitting it in a hurry.
I hope that you
have but a short lease.
Whatever I
do is done in a hurry,
replied he.
And therefore,
if I should
resolve to
quit Netherfield,
I should
probably be off
in 5 minutes.
At present,
however,
I consider myself
as quite fixed here.
That is exactly
what I should have
supposed of.
You said Elizabeth.
You begin to
comprehend me. Do you?
Cried he, turning
towards her.
Yes.
I understand
you perfectly.
I wish I might take
this for a compliment,
but to be so easily
seen through,
I am afraid, is pitiful.
That is, as it happens,
it does not follow that
a deep, intricate
character is more
or less.
Estimable than such a.
One as yours.
Lizzie
cried her mother.
Remember where you are
and do not run on
in the wild manner
that you are suffered
to do at home.
I did not know before.
Continued Bingley,
immediately.
That you were
a studier of character.
It must be an
amusing study.
Yes, but
intricate characters
are the most amusing.
They have at least
that advantage.
The country.
Said.
Darcy can, in
general supply
but few subjects
for such a study.
In a country
you move in
a very confined
and unvarying society.
But people themselves
alter so much
that there is
something new
to be observed
in them forever.
Yes, indeed.
Cried Mrs.
Bennett,
offended by
his manner of mentioning
a country neighborhood.
I assure you
there is quite
as much of that
going on in the country
as in town.
Everybody was surprised.
And Darcy, after
looking at her
for a moment.
Turned.
Silently away.
Mrs.
Bennett, who fancied
she had gained
a complete victory.
Over him,
continued her triumph.
I cannot see
that London has
any great advantage
over the country
for my part,
except the shops
and public places.
The country is a vast
deal pleasanter, is it
not, Mr.
Bingley.
When I am in
the country.
He replied.
I never wish
to leave it,
and when I am in town
it is pretty
much the same.
They have each
their advantages
and I can be
equally happy.
And either.
I.
That is because you
have the
right disposition.
But that gentleman.
Looking at Darcy.
Seemed to think
the country
was nothing at all.
Indeed, Mama,
you are mistaken.
Said Elizabeth,
blushing for her mother.
You quite mistook Mr..
He only meant that.
There was not such
a variety of people
to be met.
Within the country
as in town.
Which
he must acknowledge
to be true.
Certainly, my dear,
nobody there were.
But as to not meeting
with many people
in this neighborhood,
I believe there are few
neighborhoods larger.
I know we dined
with four
and 20 families.
Nothing but
concern for Elizabeth
could enable Bingley
to keep his countenance.
His sister
was less delicate
and directed her eyes
towards Mr.
Darcy
with a very expressive
smile.
Elizabeth, for the sake
of saying something
that might turn her
mother's thoughts.
Now asked her
if Charlotte
Lucas had been
at Long Bourn
since her coming away.
Yes.
She called
yesterday with
the father
was an agreeable man.
So William is Mr.
Bingley, is he?
Not so much
the man of fashion,
so genteel and easy.
He had always something
to say to everybody.
That is my idea
of good breeding
and those persons
who fancy themselves
very important
and never
open their mouths.
Quite mistake
the matter.
Did Charlotte
dine with you?
No.
She would go home.
I fancy she was wanted
about the mince pies.
For my part, Mr.
Bingley,
I always keep servants
that can do
their own work.
My daughters are
brought up
very differently.
But everybody
is to judge
for themselves.
And the Lucas
are very good
sort of girls,
I assure you.
It is a pity
they are not handsome.
Not that I think.
Charlotte so very plain.
But then she is
our particular friend.
She seems a
very pleasant
young woman.
Oh, dear.
Yes, but she must.
And she is very plain.
Lady Lucas
herself is often said so
and envied me.
Jane's beauty.
I do not like to
boast of my own child,
but to be sure, Jane
does not see often
anybody better looking.
It is what
everybody says.
I do not trust
own partiality.
When she was only 15.
There was a man
at my brother.
As in town,
so much in love with her
that my sister in law
was sure
he would make her
an offer
before we came away.
But however, he did not.
Perhaps he thought
that in Young.
However,
he wrote some verses
on her. And very pretty.
They were.
And so ended
his affection.
Said Elizabeth.
Impatiently.
There has been many
when I fancy overcome
in the same way.
I wonder
who first discovered
the efficacy of poetry
in driving away Love.
I have been
used to consider poetry
as the food of love.
Said Darcy,
of a fine, stout,
healthy love.
It may.
Everything nourishes
what is strong already.
But if it be
only a slight thin
sort of inclination,
I am convinced that one
good sonnet
will starve it entirely
away.
Darcy
only smiled,
and the general pause
which ensued
made Elizabeth
tremble, lest
her mother
should be
exposing herself again.
She longs to speak,
but could think of
nothing to say.
And after a short
silence, Mrs.
Bennet began
repeating her
thanks to Mr.
Bingley for his kindness
to Jane
with an apology
for troubling him.
Also with Lizzie.
Mr.
Bingley was unaffected,
least civil
in his answer,
and forced
his younger sister
to be civil also.
And say what?
The occasion required.
She performed her
part indeed
without
much graciousness.
But Mrs.
Bennet was satisfied
and soon afterwards
ordered her carriage
upon this,
the youngest of
her daughters
put herself forward.
The two
girls had
been whispering
to each other
during the whole visit,
and the result of it
was that
the youngest should
tax Mr.
Bingley, having promised
on his first
coming into the county
to give a ball
at another field.
Lydia was a stout,
well grown girl of 15
with a fine complexion
and good
humored countenance,
a favorite with her
mother whose affection
had brought her
into public
at an early age.
She had.
High animal spirits
and a sort of natural
self consequence.
Which the attention
of the.
Officers
to whom her uncle's
good dinners
and her own easy
manners recommended her,
had increased
into assurance.
She was very equal.
Therefore, to
address Mr.
Bingley
on the subject
of the ball and abruptly
reminded him
of his promise, adding
that it would be
the most shameful
thing in the world
if he did not keep it.
His answer to this
sudden attack
was delightful
to their mother's ear.
I am perfectly ready,
I assure you,
to keep my engagement.
And when your sister
is recovered, you shall,
if you please, name
the very day
of the ball.
But you would not wish
to be dancing
when she is ill.
Lydia declared
herself satisfied.
Oh, yes.
It would be much.
Better to wait
till Jane was well.
And by that time, most
likely,
Captain Carter would be.
At Maritain again.
And when you have given
your ball, she added,
I shall insist on there
giving one also.
I shall tell
Colonel Foster.
It would be
quite a shame
if he does not.
Mrs.
Bennet and her daughters
then departed
and Elizabeth returned
instantly to Jane
leaving her own
and her relations
behavior to the remarks
of the
two ladies and Mr.
Darcy,
the latter of whom,
however, could not
be prevailed on to join
in their censure of her.
In spite
of all Miss Bingley.
Witticisms on Fine Eyes.
Chapter ten.
The day passed
much as the day
before had done.
Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley
had spent some hours
of the morning
with the invalid,
who continued, though
slowly to mend.
And in the.
Evening
Elizabeth joined
their party
the drawing room.
The loo table,
however, did not appear.
Mr.
Darcy was writing
and Ms..
Bingley, seated
near him,
was watching
the progress
of his letter
and repeatedly
calling off
attention by messages
to his sister.
Mr.
Hurst and Mr.
Bingley were at peak
and Mrs.
Hurst was observing
their game.
Elizabeth
took up some needlework
and sufficiently amused
and attending
to what passed
between Darcy
and his companion.
The perpetual
commendations
of the lady
either
on his handwriting or
on the evenness
of the lines,
or on the length
of his letter
with the perfect
unconcern
with which her praises
were received.
Formed a curious dialog
and was exactly in union
with her
opinion of each.
How delighted Ms..
Darcy
would be to receive such
a letter.
He made no answer.
You write
uncommonly fast.
You are mistaken.
I write rather slowly.
How many letters
you must have occasion
to write
in the course of a year.
That is a business too.
How odious
I should think I am.
It is fortunate
then that
they fall to my lot
instead of to yours.
And I tell your sister
that I long to her.
I have already told you
so once by your desire.
I am afraid
you do
not like your pen.
Let me mend it for you.
I mend pens
remarkably well.
Thank you.
But I always
mend my own.
How come you can drive
to write?
So even.
He was silent.
Tell your sister
I am delighted
to hear
of her improvement
on the harp and pray.
Let her know that
I am quite in raptures
with her
beautiful little
design for a table
and I think it
infinitely superior to
Miss Grant. Please.
Will you give
me leave to
defer your raptures
till I write again?
A present.
I have not
room to do them justice.
No,
it is of no consequence.
I shall see her
in January.
But do you always write
such charming
long letters to her, Mr.
Darcy?
They are generally long,
but weather
always charming.
It is not for me
to determine.
It is a rule with me
that a person
who can write
a long letter with ease
cannot write ill.
That will not do
for a compliment
to Darcy.
Caroline.
Cried her brother.
Because he does
not write with ease.
He studies too
for words
of four syllables.
Do not you, Darcy?
My style of writing
is very different
from yours.
No.
Cried Miss Bingley.
Charles writes
in the most
callous way imaginable.
He leaves out
half his words and plots
the rest.
My ideas flow so rapidly
that I have not time
to express them.
By which means
my letters
sometimes convey
no ideas
at all to
my correspondence.
Your humility, Mr.
Bingley said Elizabeth
must disarm
reproof.
Nothing is
more deceitful.
Said Darcy.
Than the appearance
of humility.
It is often only
carelessness of opinion
and sometimes an
indirect boast.
And which of the two
do you call?
My little recent
piece of modesty.
The indirect boast
for your really proud
of your defects
in writing
because you
consider them
as proceeding
from a rapidity
of thought
and carelessness
of execution,
which,
if not estimable,
you think at least
highly interesting.
The power of
doing anything
with quickness
is always much prized
by the possessor
and often
without any attention
to the imperfection
of the performance.
When you told Mrs.
Bennet this morning
that if you
ever resolved
on quitting Netherfield,
you should be gone
in 5 minutes.
You meant it to be
a sort of panegyric
of complement
to yourself.
And yet,
what is there
so very laudable
in a precipitous
which must leave
very necessary
business undone
and can be of
no real advantage
to yourself
or anyone else?
Nay, cried Bingley.
This is too much
to remember at night
all the foolish things
that were said
in the morning.
And yet, upon my honor,
I believed what I said
of myself to be true.
And I believe it
at this moment
at least.
Therefore,
I did not assume
the character
of needless precipitant
merely to show off
before the ladies.
I daresay you
believed it,
but I am by no means
convinced that
you would be gone
with such celerity.
Your conduct
would be quite
as dependent on chance
as that of
any man I know.
And if,
as you were mounting
your horse,
a friend were to say
Bingley,
you'd better
till next week.
You would
probably do it.
probably not go,
and at another word
might stay a month.
You've only
proved by this.
Cried Elizabeth.
That Mr.
Bingley did
not do justice
to his own disposition.
You have shown him off
now much more than he
did himself.
I am exceedingly
gratified, said
Bingley by,
Your converting
what my friend says
into a compliment
on the sweetness
of my temper.
But I'm afraid
you are giving it
a turn,
which that gentleman
did by no means intend
for.
He would certainly
think the better of me
if under such
a circumstance
I were to give
a flat denial
and to write off
as fast as I could.
Would Mr.
D'Arcy then.
Consider the rashness
of your
original intentions
as it turned for
by your obstinacy
in adhering to it?
Upon my word,
I cannot exactly
explain the matter.
Darcy must speak
for himself.
You expect me to account
for opinions
which you
choose to call mine,
but which I have
never acknowledged.
Allowing the case,
however, to stand
according to
your representation.
You must
remember, Miss Bennet,
that the friend
who who's supposed
to decide
his return to the house
and the delay
of his plan
has merely desired it.
Asked it
without offering
one argument in
favor of its propriety.
To yield
readily, easily
to the persuasion
of a friend.
Is no merit with you.
To yield
without conviction
is no compliment
to the understanding
of either.
You appear to me, Mr.
Darcy, to allow nothing
for the influence
of friendship
and affection.
Of regard
for the request.
I would often
make one readily yield
to a request without
for arguments to reason
one into it.
I am not particularly
speaking of such a case
as you have supposed
about Mr.
Bingley.
We may as well wait.
Perhaps till
the circumstance.
Occurs
before we discuss
the discretion
of his behavior
thereupon.
But in general,
and ordinary cases
between friend
and friend, where
one of them is desired
by the other
to change a resolution
of no very great moment,
should you think
ill of that person
for complying
with a desire without
waiting to be
argued into it?
Will it not be
advisable
before we proceed
on this subject,
to arrange
with rather
more precision
the degree of importance
which is to
appertaining to
this request,
as well as the degree
of intimacy subsisting
between the parties.
By all means.
Cried Bingley.
Let us hear
all the particulars,
not forgetting
their comparative
height and size.
For that will
have more weight
in the argument,
Miss Bennet,
than you
may be aware of.
I assure you that
if Darcy were not such
a great tool
fellow in comparison
with myself,
I should not pay him
half so much deference.
I declare
I do not know
a more awful object
than Darcy
on particular occasions
and in particular places
at his own house
especially.
And on a Sunday evening
when he has
nothing to do.
Mr.
Darcy smiled.
But Elizabeth
thought she
could perceive
that he was
rather offended
and therefore
checked her laugh.
Miss Bingley
warmly resented the.
Indignity.
He had received
and an expense relation
with her brother for
talking such nonsense.
I see your
design, Bingley.
Said his friend.
You dislike an argument
and want to
silence this?
Perhaps I do.
Arguments are too
much like disputes.
If you and Miss Bennet
will defer yours
till I am
out of the room,
I shall be
very thankful.
And then you may say
whatever you like of me.
What do you ask?
Said Elizabeth.
Is no sacrifice
on my side.
And Mr.
Darcy had much better
finish his letter.
Mr.
Darcy took her advice.
And did.
Finish his letter.
When that business
was over,
he applied to Ms..
Bingley and Elizabeth
an indulgence
of some music.
Ms..
Bingley moved
with some alacrity
to the pianoforte,
and after a
polite request
that Elizabeth
would lead the way,
which the other asked
politely and more
earnestly negative,
she seated herself.
Mrs.
Hurst
sang with her sister,
and while they were
thus employed, Elizabeth
could not help observing
as she turned.
Over music books that
lay on the instrument.
How frequently Mr.
Darcy's
eyes were fixed on her.
She hardly knew
how to suppose that
she could be an object
of admiration
to so great a.
Man,
and yet that he should.
Look at her
because he disliked
her was
still more strange.
She could only imagine,
however, at last,
that she drew
his notice.
Because there was
something more wrong.
And reprehensible
according to
his ideas of right,
than in any other person
present.
The supposition did not
pain her.
She liked him
to little to
care for
his approbation.
After Playing some
Italian songs, Ms..
Bingley varied the charm
by a lively Scotch air.
And soon.
Afterward, Mr.
Darcy, drawing near,
Elizabeth, said to her.
Do you
not feel
a great inclination,
Miss Bennet, to see such
an opportunity
of dancing?
A real.
She smiled,
but made no answer.
He repeated the question
with some surprise
at her silence.
Oh.
Said she.
I heard you before,
but I could not
immediately determined
what to say in reply.
You wanted me.
I know to say yes.
That you might have
the pleasure
of despising my taste,
but I always delight
in overthrowing
those kind of schemes
and cheating a.
Person
of that premeditated.
Contempt.
I have therefore
made up my mind
to tell you
that I do not
want to dance
with me at all.
And now
despise me if you dare.
Indeed, I
do not dare.
Elizabeth, having rather
expected to affront him.
Was amazed at his.
Gallantry.
But there was a mixture
of sweetness
and archness
in her manner,
which made it difficult
for her
to affront anybody.
Hence, Darcy
had never been
so bewitched.
By any woman
as he was by her.
He really believed that
if it were not
for the inferiority
of her connections,
he should be
in some danger.
Miss Bingley
saw or suspected
enough to be jealous
and her great anxiety
for the recovery
of her dear friend Jane
received some assistance
from her desire
of getting
rid of Elizabeth.
She often tried
to provoke Darcy
into disliking her guest
by talking
of their
supposed marriage
and planning
his happiness
in such an alliance.
No, I hope.
Said she,
as they were
walking together
in the strawberry.
The next day
you will give
your mother in law
a few hints
when this desirable
event place.
As to the advantage
of holding her tongue
hand if you can
composite to cure
the younger
girls of running
after officers.
And if I may mention
so delicate
a subject endeavor
to check that
little something
bordering on conceit
and impertinence which
your lady possesses.
Have you
anything else to
propose for
my domestic Felicity?
Oh, yes.
Do you let the portraits
of your uncle
and Aunt Philips
be placed
in the gallery?
Pemberley.
Put them next
to your great uncle,
The judge.
They are
in the same profession,
you know,
only in different lines.
As if you were
Elizabeth's picture.
You not have it taken
for what?
Painter could do justice
to those beautiful eyes.
It would not be easy,
indeed, to
catch their expression.
But their color
and shape
and the eyelashes
so remarkably fine
might be copied.
At that moment,
they were met
from another walk
by Mrs.
Hurst
and Elizabeth herself.
No, I did not know that
you intended to walk.
Said Miss Bingley,
in some confusion, lest
they'd been overheard.
You used us
abominably, ill.
Answered Mrs.
Hurst.
Running away
without telling us that
you were coming out.
Then taking the
disengaged arm of Mr.
Darcy.
She left Elizabeth
to walk by herself.
The path
just admitted three.
Mr.
Darcy fell
to their rudeness
and immediately said.
This walk is not wide
enough for our party.
We had better
go into the avenue.
But Elizabeth,
who had not
the least inclination
to remain with them,
laughingly answered.
No, no.
Stay where you are.
You are
charmingly grouped
and appear
to one common advantage.
The picturesque
would be spoiled
by admitting
a fourth goodbye.
She then ran
gaily off, rejoicing
as she rambled about.
In the hope
of being at home.
Again in a day or two.
Jane was already
so much recovered
as to intend
leaving her room
for a couple of hours
that evening.
Chapter 11.
When the ladies removed
after dinner, Elizabeth
ran up to her sister
and seeing her
well guarded from cold,
attended her
into the drawing room
where she was
welcomed by her
two friends
with many professions
of pleasure.
And Elizabeth
had never seen them
so agreeable
as they were
during the hour
which passed before
the gentleman appeared.
Their powers
of conversation
were considerable.
They could describe
in entertainment
with accuracy, relate
an anecdote with humor
and laugh
at their acquaintance
with spirit.
But when the
gentleman entered,
Jane was no longer
the first object.
Miss Bailey's
eyes were instantly
turned toward Darcy,
and she had
something to say to him
before he had advanced
many steps.
He addressed himself
to Miss Bennett
with a polite
congratulation.
Mr.
Hurst
also made her
a slight bow
and said he.
Was very glad.
But a few and.
Warmth remained
for Bingley salutation.
He was full of.
Joy and attention.
The first half hour
was spent
in piling up
the fire, lest
she should suffer
from the change of room.
And she removed at his.
Desire to the other side
of the fireplace
that she might
be further
from the door.
He then sat down by her
and talked scarcely
to anyone else.
Elizabeth, at work
in the opposite corner,
saw it all
with great delight.
When he was over, Mr.
Hurst reminded
his sister in
law of the card table,
but in vain
she had obtained
private intelligence
that Mr.
Darcy did not
wish for cards.
Had Mr.
Hurst soon
found even his open
petition rejected.
She assured him that
no one intended to play,
and the silence
of the whole party
on the subject
seemed to justify her.
Mr.
Hurst
had therefore
nothing to do
but to stretch himself
on one of the.
Sofas and go to sleep.
Darcy took up a book.
Miss Bingley
did the same.
Had Mrs.
Hurst
principally occupied
in playing
with her bracelets
and rings, joined now
and then
in her
brother's conversation
with Miss Bennet.
Miss Begley's
attention was.
Quite as engaged
in watching Mr.
Darcy's progress
through his book
as in reading her own.
And she was perpetually
either
making some inquiry
or looking at his page.
She could not win.
Him, however, to
any conversation.
He merely answered
your question
and read on
at length,
quite
exhausted by the attempt
to be amused
with her own.
Book, which she had.
Only chosen
because it was the
second volume of his.
She gave a great yarn
and said.
How pleasant it is
to spend
an evening in this way.
I declare, After all,
there is no enjoyment
like reading.
How much sooner one.
Tears of anything than.
Of a book.
When I have
a house of my own,
I shall be miserable
if I have not an
excellent library.
No one made any reply.
She then yawned again.
Threw aside her.
Book.
And cast her eyes
round the room in quest
for some amusement.
When hearing her brother
mentioning a ball to,
Miss Bennet.
She turned
suddenly towards him
and said,
By the by Charles,
Are you very serious
in meditating a dance
at Netherfield?
I would advise you
before you determine it,
to consult
the wishes
of the present party.
I am much mistaken
if there are not
some among us to
whom a ball
would rather be a
punishment than
a pleasure.
If you mean Darcy.
Cried her brother.
He may go to bed
if he chooses
before it begins.
But as for the ball,
it is quite a
settled thing.
And as soon as
has made
white soup enough,
I shall send
round my cards.
I should like balls
infinitely better.
She replied.
If they were carried on
in a different manner.
But there is something
insufferably tedious,
the usual process
of such a meeting.
It would surely
be more rational
a conversation
instead of dancing.
Made the order
of the day.
Much more rational.
My dear Caroline,
I daresay.
But it would not be near
so much like a ball.
Miss Bingley
made no answer.
And soon.
Afterwards
she got up
and walked
about the room.
Her figure was elegant
and she walked well.
But Darcy,
at whom it was all.
Aimed. Was still.
In flexibly studious
in the desperation
of her feelings.
She resolved
on one effort more.
And turning
to Elizabeth, said Ms..
Eliza Bennet,
Let me persuade you
to follow my example
and to take a turn
about the room.
I assure you,
it is very refreshing
after sitting
so long in one attitude.
Elizabeth was
surprised, but
agreed to it
immediately.
Miss Bingley succeeded
no less than the real
object of her civility.
Mr. looked up.
He was as much a way
to the novelty
of attention
in that quarter
as Elizabeth herself
could.
Be, and unconsciously
closed his book.
He was directly.
Invited to join
their party,
but he declined it.
Observing that he could
imagine much too motives
for their choosing
to walk up
and down
the room together
with either
of which motives
his joining
them would interfere.
What could he mean?
She was dying to know
what could be
his meaning.
And asked Elizabeth
whether she could at all
understand him.
Not at all.
Was her answer.
But to depend upon it.
He means to be severe
on us,
and our surest way
of disappointing
him will be to ask
nothing about it.
Miss Bingley,
however was incapable
of disappointing Mr.
Darcy in anything
and persevered,
therefore in
requiring an explanation
of his two motives.
I have
not the
smallest objection
to explaining them.
Said he,
as soon as
she allowed him
to speak.
You either choose this
method of
passing the evening
because you are
in each
other's confidence
and have
secret affairs
to discuss,
or because you
are conscious
that your figures
appear
to the
greatest advantage
in walking.
If the first
I should be
completely in your way
and if the second,
I can admire
you much better as I sit
by the fire.
Shocking.
Cried Miss Bingley.
I never heard anything
so abominable.
How shall we punish him
for such a speech?
Nothing so easy
if you have.
But the inclination,
said Elizabeth.
We can all plague
and punish one another.
Tease him,
laugh at him.
Intimate as you are.
You must know how it is
to be done.
But upon my honor,
I do not.
I do assure you
that my intimacy
has not yet
taught me that
t.s calmness of manner
and presence of mine.
No, no fear.
He may defy us there.
It has to.
LAUGHTER
We will not
expose ourselves,
if you please,
by attempting to laugh
without a subject, Mr.
Darcy may hug himself.
Mr.
Darcy is not to be
laughed at.
Cried Elizabeth.
That is an uncommon
advantage and uncommon.
I hope it
will continue for
to be a great loss to me
to have
many such acquaintances.
I dearly love a laugh.
Miss Bingley.
Said he.
Has given me credit
for more
than can be the wisest
and best of men.
Nay, the wisest
and best of
their actions
may be rendered
ridiculous by a person
whose first object
in life is a joke.
Certainly,
replied Elizabeth.
There are such people.
But I hope I am
not one of them.
I hope I never ridicule
what is wise and good.
Follies and nonsense.
Whims
and inconsistencies
do divert me.
I own
and I laugh at them
whenever I can.
But these, I suppose,
are precisely
what you are without.
Perhaps
that is not
possible for anyone.
But it has
been the study
of my life
to avoid
those weaknesses
which often
expose a strong
understanding
to ridicule.
Such as vanity
and pride.
Yes, vanity
is a weakness indeed,
but pride
where there is
a real superiority
of mind.
Pride will be always
under good regulation.
Elizabeth turned away
to hide a smile.
Your examination of Mr.
Darcy is over,
I presume, said
Miss Bingley.
And pray.
What is the result?
I am perfectly
convinced by it that Mr.
Darcy has no defect.
He owns it himself.
Without disguise.
No.
Said Darcy.
I have made
no such pretension.
I have faults enough,
but they are not.
I hope of understanding
my temper.
I dare not vouch for.
It is, I believe,
too little yielding.
Certainly too little
for the
convenience of
the world.
I cannot
forget the
follies
and vices of others so
soon as I ought,
nor their offenses
against myself.
My feelings
are not puffed about
with every attempt
to move them.
My temper would
perhaps be
called resentful.
My good opinion, once
lost, is lost forever.
That is a
failing indeed.
Cried Elizabeth.
Implacable resentment
is a shade
in a character.
But you have chosen
your fault.
Well, I really cannot
laugh at it.
You are safe
from me.
There is,
I believe, in
every disposition.
The tendency
to some particular evil.
A natural defect
which not even best
education can overcome.
And your defect
is to hate everybody.
And yours.
He replied with a smile.
Is willfully
to misunderstand them.
Do not just have
a little music.
Kindness Bingley.
Tired of
the conversation
in which
she had no share.
Louisa.
You will not mind
my waking Mr.
Hurst.
Her sister had not
the smallest objection.
And the.
Pianoforte was opened.
And Darcy,
after a few moments
recollection was not
sorry for it.
He began to
the danger of paying
Elizabeth too
much attention.
Chapter 12.
In consequence of
an agreement
between the sisters,
Elizabeth wrote
to the next morning
to their mother to beg
that the carriage
might be sent for them
in the course
of the day.
But Mrs.
Bennett,
who had calculated
on her daughters
remaining at Netherfield
to the following Tuesday
which would
exactly finish Jane's
week,
could not bring herself
to receive them
with pleasure before
her answer, therefore
was not propitious,
at least not to.
Elizabeth's wishes, for
she was impatient
to get home.
Mrs.
Bennett sent them
word that they
could not possibly
have the carriage
before Tuesday,
and in her postscript,
it was added that if Mr.
Bingley and his sister
pressed them
to stay longer,
she could spare them
very well.
Against staying longer,
however, Elizabeth
was positively resolved.
Nor did she much expect
it would be asked
and fearful,
on the contrary,
as being considered
as intruding themselves
needlessly long.
She urged Jane
to borrow Mr.
Bigley's
carriage immediately
and at length.
It was settled
that their
original design
of leaving Netherfield
that morning
should be mentioned,
and the request.
Made the communication.
Excited
many professions
of concern.
And enough was said of
wishing them to stay
at least
till the following day,
to work on Jane
until the morrow.
Their going
was deferred.
Miss Bingley was
then sorry
that she had proposed
the delay.
For her jealousy
and dislike of
one sister much exceeded
her affection
for the other.
The master of the house
heard with real sorrow
that they were
to go so soon
and repeatedly tried
to persuade Miss Bennet
that it would
not be safer.
But she was
not enough recovered.
But Jane was firm
where she felt herself
to be, right?
To Mr.
Darcy,
it was a welcome
intelligence.
Elizabeth had been
at Netherfield
long enough.
She attracted him
more than he liked.
And Miss Bingley
was uncivil to her.
And more teasing than
usual to himself.
He wisely resolved
to be
particularly careful
that no sign
of admiration
should now escape him.
Nothing that
could elevate her
with the hope
of influencing
his felicity.
Sensible
that if such an idea
had been suggested,
his behavior
during the last day
must have
material weight
and confirming
or crushing.
It steady.
To his purpose.
He scarcely spoke
ten words to her
through the whole
of Saturday, and though
they were
at one time left by for
half an hour,
he adhered most.
Conscientiously to
his book and would not.
Even look at her.
On Sunday.
After morning service.
The separation
so agreeable to almost
all took place.
Miss Bingley civility
to Elizabeth increased
at last very rapidly,
as well as her affection
for Jane.
And when they parted
after assuring
latter of the pleasure,
it would always give her
to see her either
at Long Bourn
or Netherfield,
and embracing her
most tenderly.
She even shook
hands with the former.
Elizabeth took
leave of the
whole party in the
liveliest of spirits.
They were
not welcomed home
very cordially
by their mother.
Mrs.
Bennett
wondered at their coming
and thought
them very wrong
to give so much
and was sure
Jane would have
caught cold again.
But their father, though
very laconic
in his
expressions of pleasure,
was really glad
to see them.
He had felt
their importance
in the family circle.
The evening conversation
when they were
all assembled had lost
much of its animation
and almost all its sense
by the absence of Jane
and Elizabeth.
They found Mary,
as usual,
deep in the
study of Thoreau base
and human nature,
and had some extracts
to admire
and some
new observations
of threadbare morality
to listen to.
Catherine and Lydia
had information
for them
of a different sort.
Much had been.
Done and much
had been said
in the regiment
since the preceding
Wednesday.
Several of the officers
had dined lately
with their uncle.
A private had been.
Flogged.
And it had actually
been hinted
that Colonel Forrester
was going to be married.
Chapter 13.
I hope my dear.
Said Mr.
Bennett to his wife,
as they were
at breakfast
the next morning.
That you have ordered
a good dinner today,
because I have reason
to expect an addition
to our family party.
What do you mean,
my dear?
I know nobody
that is coming.
I am sure,
unless Charlotte Lucas
should happen
to call in.
And I hope my dinners
are good enough for her.
I do not believe
she often sees
such at home.
The person of
whom I speak is
a gentleman
and a stranger.
Mrs.
Bennett's eyes sparkled.
That gentleman
and a stranger.
It is Mr.
Bingley, I am sure.
Well, I am sure.
I shall be extremely
glad.
See, Mr.
Bingley.
But good Lord,
how unlucky.
There is not
a bit of fish
to be got today.
Lydia, my love.
Ring the bell.
I must speak to Hill.
This moment.
It is not Mr.
Bingley.
Said her husband.
It is a person
whom I never saw
in the whole
course of my life.
This roused
a general
astonished mint,
and he had the pleasure
of being
eagerly questioned
by his wife
and his five daughters
at once.
After amusing himself
some time
with their curiosity,
he thus explain.
About a month ago I
received this letter,
and about
a fortnight ago
I answered it for
I thought it
a case of some delicacy
and requiring
early attention.
It is from
my cousin, Mr.
Collins, who,
when I am dead, may
turn you all
out of this house
as soon as he pleases.
Oh, my dear.
Cried his.
Wife.
I cannot bear to hear
that mentioned.
Pray.
Do not talk of that
odious man.
I do think it is
the harshest thing
in the world
that your state
should be entailed away
from your own children.
And I am sure
if I had been you,
I should have
tried long ago
to do something
rather about it.
Jane and Elizabeth
tried to explain to her
the nature
of an and tale.
They had often attempted
to do it before, but
it was a subject
on which Mrs.
Bennett was beyond
the reach of reason.
And she.
Continued to rail
bitterly
against the cruelty
of settling in a state
away from a
family of five.
Daughters
in favor of a man whom.
Nobody cared
anything about.
It certainly is
a most
iniquitous affair.
Said Mr.
Bennett.
And nothing
can clear Mr.
Collins from the guilt
of inheriting
Long Bourn.
But if you will
listen to his letter,
you may perhaps
be a little softened
by his manner
of expressing himself.
Know that I am
sure I shall not.
And I think it is
very impertinent of him
to write to you at all
and very hypocritical.
I hate such
false friends.
Why could he not
keep on
quarreling with you
as his father
did before him?
Why?
He does seem to have had
some filial scruples
on that head.
As you will hear.
Hansford near West Kent,
the 15th of October.
Dear Sir,
the disagreement
subsisting
between yourself
and my
late honored father
always
gave me much uneasiness.
And since I have had
the misfortune
to lose him,
I have frequently
wished to heal
the breach.
But for some time,
I was back
by my own doubts,
fearing lest
it might
seem disrespectful
to his memory for me
to be on good terms
with anyone with whom
it had always him
to be at variance.
There, Mrs.
Bennett.
My mind, however, is
now made
up on the subject
for having
received ordination
at Easter.
I have been so fortunate
as to be distinguished
by the patronage
of the right.
Honorable Lady Katherine
de Borg,
widow of Sir
Louis de Borg,
whose bounty
and beneficence
has preferred me
to the valuable rectory
of this parish,
where it should be
my earnest endeavor
to demean myself
with grateful respect
towards Her Ladyship
and be ever ready
to perform
those rights
and ceremonies
which are instituted
by the Church
of England.
As a clergyman,
moreover,
I feel it my duty
to promote and establish
the blessing of peace
in all families
within the reach
of my influence.
And on these grounds,
I flatter myself
that my present
overtures of goodwill
are highly commendable
and that
the circumstance
of my being next
in the entail of long
born estate
will be kindly
overlooked on your side
and not lead you
to reject the offered
olive branch.
I cannot be otherwise
than concerned
of being the means
of injuring
your amiable daughters
and beg
leave to apologize
for it,
as well
as to assure you
of my readiness
to make them
every possible amends.
But of this
hereafter,
if you should have
no objection
to receive me
into your house,
I propose myself
the satisfaction
of waiting on you
and your family.
Monday, November
18th, by 4:00.
And she'll
probably trespass
on your hospitality
till the Saturday
said night following
which I can do without
any inconvenience.
As Lady
Catherine is far
from objecting
to my occasional absence
on a Sunday, provided
that some
other clergyman
is engaged
to do
the duty of the day.
I remain, dear sir,
with respectful
compliments
to your lady
and daughters,
your well-wisher
and friend
William
Collins
at 4:00.
Therefore,
we may expect
this peacemaking
gentleman.
Said Mr.
Bennett, as he folded up
the letter.
He seems to be
a most conscientious
and polite young man
upon my word,
and I doubt not
will prove
a valuable acquaintance,
especially if
Lady Catherine
should be so indulgent
as to let him
come to us again.
There is some sense in.
What he says
about the girls.
However,
and if he is disposed
to make them any amends,
I shall not
be the person
to discourage him.
Though
it is difficult,
said Jane,
to guess in what way
he can mean
to make us
the atonement.
He thinks I do.
The wish is certainly,
to his credit.
Elizabeth was
chiefly struck
by his
extraordinary deference
for Lady Catherine
and his kind intention
of christening, marrying
and burying
his parishioners
whenever it were
required.
He must be an oddity,
I think.
Said she.
I can not make him out.
There is something very
pompous in his style.
And what can he mean
by apologizing
for being next
in the entail?
We cannot suppose
he would help it
if he could.
Could he be a sensible
man, sir?
No, my dear,
I think not.
I have great hopes of
finding him.
Quite the reverse.
There is a mixture
of civility
and self-importance
in his letter,
which promises.
Well,
I'm impatient
to see him.
In point of
composition, said.
Mary.
The letter does not
seem defective.
The idea of the olive
branch,
perhaps, is
not wholly new.
Yet think it is
well expressed.
To Catherine and Lydia.
Neither the letter nor
its writer
were in any
degree interesting.
It was next
to impossible
that their cousin
should come in
a scarlet coat.
And it was now.
Some weeks
since they had received
pleasure
from the society
of a man
in any other color.
As for their mother, Mr.
Collins, his letter
had done away
much of her ill will,
and she was preparing
to see him
with a degree
of composure
which astonished
her husband
and daughters.
Mr.
Collins was punctual
to his time
and was received
with great politeness
by the whole family.
Mr.
Bennett
indeed said little,
but the ladies
were ready
enough to talk, and Mr.
Collins seemed
neither
in need of encouragement
nor inclined
to be silent himself.
He was a.
Tall, heavy
looking young
man of five and 20.
His air
was grave and stately,
and his manners
were very formal.
He had not been long
seated before.
He complimented Mrs.
Bennett
on having so fine.
A family of daughters
said he had heard much
of their.
Beauty,
but that in
this instance.
Fame had fallen short
of the truth
and added
that he did
not doubt her
seeing them all in
due time disposed of
in marriage.
This gallantry
was not much
to the taste
of some of his hearers.
But Mrs.
Bennett,
who quarreled
with no compliments,
answered most readily.
You are very kind,
I am sure,
and I wish
with all my heart
it may prove so.
For else
they will be destitute
enough.
Things are
settled so oddly.
You allude perhaps
to the
entail of this estate.
Her, sir.
I do indeed.
It is a grievous affair
to my poor girls.
You must confess.
Not that
I mean
to find fault with you
for such things.
I know where
all chance
in this world.
There is no knowing
how states will go.
And once they come
to be entailed.
I am very sensible,
madam, of the hardship
to my fair cousins,
and could say
much on the subject.
But that I am cautious
of appearing
forward and precipitate.
But I can assure
the young ladies
that I come prepared
to admire them.
At present
I will not say more, but
perhaps when we are
better acquainted.
He was interrupted
by a summons to dinner
and the girls
smiled on each other.
They were not the.
Only objects of Mr.
Collins's admiration.
The hall,
the dining room
and all its furniture
were examined
and praised,
and his commendation
of everything
would have touched Mrs.
Bennett's heart.
But for the mortifying.
Supposition of his
viewing it all
as his own
future property.
The dinner, too,
in its turn,
was highly admired.
And he begged
to know, too,
which of his fair
cousins, The Excellency.
Of its cooking was.
Own.
But he was sat
right there by Mrs.
Bennett, who assured him
with some disparity
that they were very well
able to.
Keep a good cook
and that her
daughters had.
Nothing to do
in the kitchen.
He begged pardon
for having
displeased her.
In a softened tone,
she declared herself
not at all offended.
But he continued to.
Apologize for
about a quarter
of an hour.
Chapter 14.
During dinner, Mr.
Bennett scarcely
spoke at all.
But when the servants
were withdrawn,
he thought it time
to have
some conversation
with his guest
and therefore started
a subject
in which he expected him
to shine.
By observing that,
he seemed very fortunate
in his patroness,
Lady Catherine,
to Berg's
attention to his wishes
and consideration
for his comfort appeared
very remarkable.
Mr.
Bennett could not have
chosen better.
Mr.
Collins was eloquent
in her praise.
The subject elevated him
to more
than usual
solemnity of manner,
and with the most
important aspect.
He protested that.
He had never
in his life
witnessed such behavior
in a person of rank,
such affability
and condescension,
as he had himself
experienced
from Lady Catherine.
She had been graciously
pleased to approve of
both of the discourses
which she had already
had the honor
of preaching before her.
She had also asked him
twice to dine at roses
and had sent for him
only the Saturday
before to make
up her pool of cordial
in the evening.
Lady Catherine
was reckoned
proud by many people
he knew,
but he had
never seen anything but
in her.
She had always
spoken to him
as she would
to any other gentleman.
She made not
the smallest
objection to.
His joining
in the society.
Of the neighborhood,
nor to his
leaving the parish
occasionally for a week
or two
to visit his relations.
She had
even condescended
to advise him to marry
as soon as he could.
Provided
he chose with discretion
and had once
paid him a visit
in his humble parsonage,
where she had
perfectly approved
all the alterations
he had been making and
had even vouchsafed
to suggest some herself
some shelves
in the closet upstairs.
That is all
very proper and civil,
I am sure, said Mrs.
Bennett, and I daresay
she is a very
agreeable woman.
It is a pity
that great
ladies in general
are not more like her.
Does she live near
you, sir?
The garden
in which stands my
humble abode,
is separated
only by Lane from Rose
Kings Park.
Her lady ships
residence.
I think you said
she was a widow, sir.
How?
She and her family.
She has one
only daughter,
the heir of Rose Ings,
and a very extensive
property.
Oh, said Mrs.
Bennett,
shaking her head.
Then she is better off
than many girls.
And what sort
young lady is she?
Is she handsome?
She is a most charming
young lady.
Indeed.
Lady Catherine herself
says that
in point of true
beauty, Mr.
Borg far
superior
to the handsomest
of her sex.
Because there is
that in her features,
which marks
the young woman
of distinguished birth.
She is unfortunately,
of a sickly constitution
which has prevented her
making that progress
in many accomplishments
which she could not
otherwise have
failed of.
As I am informed
by the lady
who superintended
her education and
who still
resides with them.
But she is perfectly
amiable and often
condescended
to drive
by my humble
abode
in her little phaeton
and ponies.
Has she been presented?
I do not
remember her name
among the ladies
at court.
Her indifferent
state of health
prevents her
being in town.
And by that means,
as I told Lady
Catherine myself,
one day has deprived
the British court
of its
brightest ornament.
Her Ladyship
pleased with the idea.
And you may imagine that
I am happy
on every occasion
to offer
those little
delicate compliments
which are
always acceptable
to ladies.
I have more than once
observed
to Lady Catherine
that her
charming daughter
seemed born
to be a duchess
and that the most
elevated rank,
instead of giving her
consequence
would be adorned by her.
These are
the kind of
little things
which please
her ladyship,
and it is the sort
of attention
which I conceive myself
peculiarly bound to pay.
You judge very properly.
Said Mr.
Bennett.
And it is happy for you
that you possess
the talent of flattering
with delicacy.
May I ask whether
these pleasing
attentions proceed
from the
impulse of the moment,
or are the result
of previous study?
They arise
chiefly from
what is passing
at the time.
And though I
sometimes amuse myself
with suggesting
and arranging
such little
elegant compliments
as may be
adapted to
ordinary occasions,
I always wish
to give them
as unstudied an error
as possible.
Mr.
Bennett's expectations
were fully answered.
His cousin was as absurd
as he had hoped.
And he listened.
To him
with the
keenest enjoyment,
maintaining,
at the same time
the most resolute
composure
of countenance, and
except in an
occasional glance
at Elizabeth requiring
no partner
in his pleasure.
By teatime.
However,
the dose
had been enough, and Mr.
Bennett
was glad to take
his guest
into the drawing
room again.
And when he was over,
glad to invite him
to read aloud
to the ladies.
Mr.
Collins readily
assented.
And a book was produced.
But on beholding.
It for everything,
announced it
to be
from the
circulating library.
He started back
and begging pardon,
protested that
he never read novels.
Kitty stared at him.
And Lydia exclaimed.
Other books
were produced.
And after
some deliberation,
he chose
for Dice's sermons.
Lydia gaped
as he opened the volume,
and before he had,
with very monotonous
solemnity, read
three pages.
She interrupted him.
With, Do you know
the law
that my Uncle Philips
talks of
turning away Richard?
And if he does
kind of forced
it will hire him.
My aunt told me
so herself on.
I shall walk to
merit in tomorrow
to hear more about it
and to ask when Mr.
Denny comes back
from town.
Lydia was bid by her
two eldest sisters
to hold her tongue.
But Mr.
Collins much offended,
laid aside his book
and said.
I have often
observed how
little young ladies
are interested
by books
of a serious stamp.
Though Written solely
for their benefit.
It amazes
me, I confess.
For certainly
there can be nothing
so advantageous
to them as instruction.
But I will no
longer important
in my young cousin.
Then turning to Mr.
Bennett,
he offered himself
as his antagonist
at backgammon.
Mr.
Bennett accepted
the challenge, observing
that he acted
very wisely
and leaving the girls
to their own
trifling amusements.
Mrs.
Bennett
and her daughters
apologized most severely
for Lydia's interruption
and promised
that it should
not occur again.
If he would
resume his book.
But Mr.
Collins,
after assuring them
that he bore
his young cousin
no ill will
and should never
resent her behavior
as any affront,
seated himself
at another table
with Mr.
Bennett and
prepared for backgammon.
Chapter 15.
Mr.
Collins was
not a sensible man,
and the deficiency
of nature had been
but little
assisted by education
or society.
The greatest part of
his life,
having been spent
under the guidance
of an illiterate
and miserly father.
And though belonged
to one
of the universities,
he had merely kept
the necessary terms
without forming at it
any useful acquaintance.
The subjection in which
his father
had brought him up
had given him originally
great humility
of manner.
But it was now a good
deal counteracted
by the self
conceit of a weak head
living in retirement
and the
consequential feelings
of early and unexpected
prosperity.
A fortunate chance
had recommended him
to Lady
Catherine de Burg
when the living
of Hansford
was vacant and.
The respect
which he felt for her
high rank
and his veneration
for her
as his patroness,
mingling
with a very good opinion
of himself,
of his authority
as a clergyman,
and his right
as, a rector.
Made.
Him altogether
a mixture of pride
and obsequiousness,
self-importance
and humility.
Having now a good house
and a very
sufficient income,
he intended to marry
and in seeking
a reconciliation
with the long
born family,
he had a wife in view
as he meant
to choose
one of the daughters
if he found them
as handsome and amiable
as they were represented
by Common Report.
This was his plan of a
means of atonement
for inheriting their
father's estate.
And he thought it an.
Excellent one, full
of eligibility
and suitable ness
and excessively generous
and disinterested
on his own part.
His plan did not vary.
On seeing them.
Misspell on
its lovely face,
confirmed his views,
and established
all his strictest
notions of what
was due to seniority.
And for the first
evening
she was his
settled choice.
The Next morning,
however, made
an alteration.
Four and a quarter of
an hour's tete
a tete with Mrs.
Bennett
before breakfast,
a conversation beginning
with his parsonage house
and leading naturally
the avowal of his hopes
that a mistress
might be found for
it had long.
Borne produced.
From her amid
very complaisant smiles
and general
encouragement.
A caution.
Against the very gaon
he had fixed on.
As to her
younger daughters.
She could not
take upon her to say
she could not
positively answer,
but she did not know
of any pre possession.
Her eldest daughter,
she must just mention
she felt it incumbent
on her to hint
what was likely to be
very soon engaged.
Mr.
Collins
had only to change
from Jane to Elizabeth,
and it was soon done.
Done while Mrs.
Bennett was
stirring the fire.
Elizabeth equally
next to Jane in birth
and beauty
succeeded her.
Of course, Mrs.
Bennett
treasured up the hint
and trusted
that she might soon
have two daughters
married and the man
whom she could
not bear to speak of
day before was now
high in her good graces.
Lydia's intention
of walking to Maritain
was not forgotten.
Every sister except Mary
agreed to go with her,
and Mr.
Collins
was to attend them
at the request of Mr.
Bennett,
who was most anxious
to get rid of him
and have his library
to himself.
For thither, Mr.
Collins had followed him
after breakfast,
and there
he would continue
nominally engaged
with one of the
largest folios
in the collection.
But really
talking to Mr.
Bennett
with little cessation.
Of his house.
And garden at Hansford.
Such doings
just composed Mr.
Bennett exceedingly.
In his library,
he had always been
sure of leisure
and tranquility,
and though prepared
as he told Elizabeth
to meet with folly
and conceit in
every other room
of the house.
He was used to be.
Free from them there.
His civility, therefore,
was most prompt
in inviting Mr.
Collins, join
his daughters
in their walk, and Mr.
Collins being, in fact,
much better fitted
for a walker
than a reader,
was extremely pleased
to close his large book
and go in pompous
nothings on his side.
And.
Civil assent
on that of his cousins.
Their time passed
till they
entered maritain.
The attention of.
The younger ones
was then no longer
to be gained by him.
Their eyes
were immediately
wandering up
in the street
in quest of
the officers,
and nothing
less than
a very smart bonnet.
Indeed,
or a really new muslin
in a shop window could.
Recall them.
But the attention
of every lady was soon
caught by young men
whom they
had never seen before.
Of most.
Gentlemen, like walking
with another officer
on the other
side of the.
Way.
The officer was
the very Mr.
Denny concerning
who had returned
from London.
Lydia came to inquire
and he bowed
as they passed.
All were struck
with the strangers air.
All wondered
who he could be.
And Kitty
and Lydia, determined.
If possible,
to find out, led
the way across
the street
under pretense
of wanting something
in an opposite shop
and fortunately had
just gained
the pavement.
When the two gentlemen
turning back had reached
the same spot.
Danny addressed them
directly
and entreated permission
to introduce
his friend, Mr.
Wickham,
who had returned
with him
the day before
from town.
And he was happy to.
Say, had accepted
a commission
in their corps.
This was exactly
as it should be.
For the young man.
Wanted only regimental
to make him
completely charming.
His appearance
was greatly
in his favor.
He had all the best
part of beauty,
a fine countenance,
a good figure,
and very
pleasing address.
The introduction was
followed up on his side
by a happy readiness,
a conversation.
And a.
Readiness
at the same time.
Perfectly correct
and unassuming.
And the whole party
were still standing
and talking together
very agreeably.
When the sound of horses
drew their notice
and Darcy and Bingley
were seen
riding down the street.
On distinguishing
the ladies of the group.
The two gentlemen came
directly towards them
and began
the usual civilities.
Bingley
was the principal
spokesman and Mr.
Bennett
the principal object.
He was then.
He said, on his way
to Long Bourne
on purpose, to inquire
after her.
Mr.
Darcy
corroborated it
with a bow,
and was beginning
to determine
not to fix his eyes
on Elizabeth
when they were
suddenly arrested
by the side
of the stranger
and Elizabeth happening
to see the countenance
of both
as they looked
at each other
was all astonishment
at the effect
of the meeting.
Both changed.
Color.
One looked white,
the other read Mr.
Wickham.
After a few moments
touched his hat.
A salutation which.
Mr.
Darcy just deigned
to return.
What could be
the meaning of it?
It was impossible
to imagine.
not too long to know.
In another minute, Mr.
Bingley.
But without seeming to.
Have noticed
what passed.
Took leave and rode on
with his friend.
Mr. Denny and.
Mr.
Wickham walked
with the young ladies
to the door of Mr.
Phillips house
and then made
their bows.
In spite of Miss
Lydia's
pressing entreaties
that they
should come in.
And even in spite
of Mrs.
Phillips
throwing up
the parlor window
and loudly seconding
the invitation.
Mrs.
Phillips was always
glad to see her nieces,
and the two eldest
from their
recent absence
were particularly
welcome,
and she was
eagerly expressing
her surprise
at their sudden
return home.
Which.
As their own carriage
had not fetched them.
She should have known
nothing about.
If she had not happened.
To see Mr.
Jones's shop
boy in the street
who had told her
that they were
not to send
any more drafts
to Netherfield
because
the Miss Bennetts
were come away.
When.
Her civility was claimed
toward Mr.
Collins by Jane's
introduction of him.
She received him
with her
very best politeness,
which he returned
with as much more,
apologizing for
his intrusion
without any
previous acquaintance
her which
he could not help.
Flattering
himself, however.
Might be justified.
By his relationship
to the young ladies
who introduced him
to her notice.
Mrs.
Phillips was quite
awed by such
an excess
of good breeding.
But her
contemplation of.
One stranger was soon
put to an end
by exclamations
and inquiries
about the other.
Of.
Whom, however,
she could only tell her
nieces
what they already knew
that Mr.
Denny
had brought him
from London,
and that he was to have
a lieutenant's
commission
in the blank share.
She had been
watching him.
The last hour, she said
as he walked up
and down the street
and had Mr.
Wickham appeared.
Kitty and Lydia
would certainly have
continued
the occupation,
but luckily
no one passed
windows now
except a few of
the officers.
Who, in.
Comparison
with the stranger,
would.
Become stupid.
Disagreeable fellows.
Some of them
were to dine
with the Phillips's
the next day,
and their aunt promised
to make her husband
call on Mr.
Wickham
and give him
an imitation.
Also,
if the family
from Long Bourn
would come in
the evening.
This was agreed to.
And Mrs..
Phillips protested
that they would have
a nice, comfortable,
noisy game
of lottery tickets
and a little bit of hot
supper afterwards.
The prospect of
such delights
was very cheering
and they parted
in mutual good spirits.
Mr.
Collins
repeated his apologies,
quitting the room
and was assured
with on
wearying civility
that they were
perfectly needless.
As they walked home,
Elizabeth related
to Jane,
which she had seen
passed between.
The two gentlemen.
But though Jane would
have defended either
or both had
they appeared
to be in the wrong.
She could
no more explain
such behavior
than her sister.
Mr.
Collins, his return
highly gratified Mrs.
Bennett.
By.
Admiring Mrs.
Phillips's manners
and politeness.
He protested
that except Lady
Catherine
and her daughter,
he had never seen
a more elegant woman.
For she had not only
received him
with the utmost
civility.
But even pointedly.
Included him
in her invitation
for the next evening,
although utterly unknown
to her
before something
he supposed.
Might be attributed
to his connection
with them.
But yet he had never met
with so much attention
in the whole
course of his life.
Chapter 16.
As no
objection was made
to the young
people's engagement
with their aunt
and all Mr.
Collins's
scruples of leaving Mr.
and Mrs.
Bennett
for a single
evening during
his visit were most
steadily resisted.
The coach conveyed
him and his five cousins
at a suitable hour
to Maritain,
and the girls
had the pleasure
of hearing
as they entered
the drawing room
that Mr.
Wickham had accepted
their uncle's invitation
and was then
in the house
when this information
was given
and they had all taken
their seats.
Mr.
Collins was at leisure
to look around
him and admire, and he.
Was so much struck.
With the size
and furniture
of the apartment
that he declared
he might almost have
supposed himself
in the small summer
breakfast parlor
at Rose.
Kings.
A comparison
that did not
at first convey
much gratification.
But when Mrs.
Phillips understood
from him.
What Rose Ings was
and who was.
Its proprietor.
When she had listened
to the description
of only one of Lady
Katherine's drawing.
Rooms and found.
That the
chimney piece alone had.
Cost ?800, she felt all.
The force of the.
Compliment and would.
Hardly have resented
a comparison
with the
housekeeper's room.
In describing to her
all the grandeur of Lady
Katharine
and her mansion
with occasional
digressions
in praise
of his own humble abode
and the improvements
it was receiving,
he was happily employed
until the gentleman
joined them
and he found and Mrs.
Phillips,
a very
attentive listener.
Whose opinion of his.
Consequence increased
with what she heard
and she was resolving
to retain it all
among her neighbors
as soon as.
She could.
To girls
who could not listen
to their cousin
and who had nothing
to do
but to wish
for an instrument
and examine
their own
indifferent
imitations of China
on the mantelpiece.
The interval
of waiting appeared
very long.
It was over at last.
However, the gentleman
did approach,
and when Mr.
Wickham walked
into the room,
Elizabeth felt
that she had neither
been seeing him before
nor thinking of him
since,
with the smallest degree
of unreasonable
admiration.
The officers
of the Blackshear
were in general
a very
creditable gentleman
like set,
and the best of them
were of the
present party.
But Mr.
Wickham was as far
beyond them
all in person.
Countenance ere and walk
as they were superior
to the broad
faced stuffy Philip's
breathing port wine,
who followed them
into the room.
Mr.
Wickham was the
happy man towards whom?
Almost every female
I was turned.
And Elizabeth
was the happy woman
by whom
he finally
seated himself.
And the agreeable manner
in which he immediately
fell into conversation.
Though it was only.
On its being a wet.
Night, made her.
Feel that
the commonest, dullest,
most threadbare topic
might be rendered
interesting by the skill
of the speaker.
With such rivals
for the notice
of the fair as Mr.
Wickham
and the officers, Mr.
Collins seemed to sink
into insignificance
to the young ladies.
He certainly
was nothing.
But he.
Had still at intervals
a kind listener and Mrs.
Phillips,
and was,
by her watchfulness.
Most.
Abundantly supplied
with coffee and muffin.
When the cards
tables were placed.
He had the opportunity
of obliging her in turn
by sitting down to West.
I know
little of the game
at present, said he,
but I shall be glad
to improve myself for
in my situation of life.
Mrs.
Phillips was very glad
for his compliance.
But could not wait.
For his reason.
Mr.
Wickham did
not play it west,
and with ready delight
was he received
at the other table
between Elizabeth
and Lydia.
At first
there seemed
danger of Lydia's
engrossing
hymn entirely,
for she was the most
determined talker,
but being likewise
extremely fond
of lottery tickets.
She soon grew much.
Interested in the game.
Too.
Eager and making bets
and exclaiming
after prizes
to have attention
for anyone
in particular,
allowing for the common
demands of the game.
Mr.
Wickham was therefore
at leisure
to talk to Elizabeth,
and she was very willing
to hear him,
Though what she chiefly
wished to hear,
she could not hope
to be. Told the.
History
of his acquaintance
with Mr.
Darcy.
She dared
not even mention
that gentleman.
Her curiosity,
however, was
unexpectedly relieved.
Mr.
Wickham began
the subject himself.
He inquired
how far Netherfield
was from Moreton,
and after receiving her
answer,
asked in a
hesitating manner
how long Mr.
Darcy had been
staying there.
About a month.
Said Elizabeth.
And then unwilling
to let the subject
drop at it.
He is a man.
Of very large property
in Derbyshire.
I understand.
Yes, replied Wickham.
His estate.
There is a noble one.
A clear 10,000
per annum.
You could not have met
with a person
more capable
of giving you
certain information
on that hedge
than myself.
For
I have been connected
his family
in a particular
manner from my infancy.
You may well
be surprised,
Miss Bennet,
at such an assertion,
after
seeing as you
probably might,
the very cold manner
of our
meeting yesterday.
Are you much acquainted
with Mr.
Darcy?
As much as I ever
wish to be.
Cried Elizabeth
very warmly.
I have spent four days
in the same house
with him
and think him
very disagreeable.
I have no right to give
my opinion,
said Wickham,
as to his
being agreeable
or otherwise.
I'm not qualified
to form one.
I have known him too
long and too
well to be a fair judge.
It is impossible
for me to be impartial,
but I believe
your opinion of him
would in
general astonish,
and perhaps you would
not express it
quite so strongly
anywhere else.
Here you are in your
own family.
Upon my word,
I say
no more
here than I might say in
any house
in the neighborhood.
Except.
Netherfield.
He is not at all
liked in Hertfordshire.
Everybody is disgusted
with his pride.
You will not find him
more favorably.
Spoken by anyone.
I cannot pretend
to be sorry.
Said Wickham,
after a short
interruption.
That he or that any man
should not be estimated
to be on their desserts.
But with him,
I believe
it does
not often happen.
The world is blinded
by his fortune
and consequence,
or frightened
by his high
and imposing manners
and sees him only
as he chooses
to be seen.
I should take him,
even on my slight
acquaintance, to be
an ill tempered man.
Wickham only
shook his head.
I wonder.
Said he, at the
next opportunity
of speaking.
Whether he is
likely to be in
this country
much longer.
I do not at all know.
But I heard nothing.
He was going away
when I was
at Netherfield.
I hope your plans
in favor of
the blank show
will not
be affected by his
being in the.
Oh, no.
It is not for me
to be driven away by Mr.
Darcy.
If he wishes to avoid
seeing me, he must go.
We not on
friendly terms.
And it always gives me
pain to meet him.
But I have no reason
for avoiding him.
But what I
might proclaim
to all the world.
A sense of very great
ill usage
and most painful regrets
at his being.
What he is
his father.
Miss Bennet,
the late Mr.
Darcy, was
one of the best
men ever breathed
and the truest friend
I ever had.
And I can never be
in company with this Mr.
Darcy,
without being grieved
to the soul
by a thousand
tender recollections.
His behavior
to myself has
been scandalous.
But I verily believe
I could forgive him
anything and everything
rather than
his disappointing
the hopes
and disgracing
the memory
of his father.
Elizabeth
found the interest
of the subject increase
and listened
with all her heart,
but the delicacy of it
prevented
further inquiry.
Mr.
Wickham began
to speak on more
general topics
Meriton,
the neighborhood,
the society
appearing highly pleased
with all that
he had yet seen,
and speaking
of the latter,
with gentle
but very
intelligible gallantry.
It was the prospect
of constant society
and good society.
He added.
Which was my
chief inducement
to enter the shire.
I know
to be
a most respectable,
agreeable call
and my friend
Danny tempted me further
by his
account of their
present quarters
and the very
great attentions
and excellent
acquaintance Meriton
had procured them.
Society I own
is necessary to me.
I've been a
disappointed man
and my spirits
will not bear solitude.
I must have employment
and society.
A military life
is not what
I was intended for,
but circumstances
have now made it
eligible.
The church
ought to have been
my profession.
I was brought up for
the church,
and I should
at this time
have been in possession
of a most
valuable living.
Had it pleased
the gentleman
we were speaking of
just now.
Indeed.
Yes.
The late Mr.
D'Arcy bequeathed me
the next presentation
of the best
living and his gift.
He was my godfather
and excessively
attached to me.
I cannot do justice
to his kindness.
He meant to provide
for me amply
and thought
he had done it.
But when the living
fell, it was elsewhere.
Good heavens!
Cried Elizabeth.
But how could that be?
How could his
will be disregarded?
Why not?
You seek legal redress.
There was just
such an informality
in the terms
of the bequest
as to give me
no hope from law.
A man of honor
could have doubted
the intention.
But Mr.
D'Arcy chose to doubt it
or to treat it
as a merely
conditional
recommendation
and to assert that
I had forfeited
all claim
it by extravagance
imprudence.
In short, anything or
nothing
certain, it
is that the living
became vacant
two years ago
exactly as I was
of an age to hold it,
and that it was given
to another man
and no less
certain is it
that I cannot
accuse myself
of having
really done
anything to
deserve to lose it?
I have a warm,
unguarded temper
and I may
perhaps have
sometimes spoken
my opinion of him
and to him too freely.
I can recall
nothing worse.
But the fact is
that we are
very different
sort of men
and that he hates me.
This is quite shocking.
He desires
to be
publicly disgraced.
Sometime
or other he will be.
But it shall not be
by me
till I can forget
his father.
I can never defy
or expose him.
Elizabeth
honored him
for such feelings
and thought him
handsomer than ever
as he expressed them.
But what she said
after a pause.
Cannot be his motive.
What can have
induced him to behave so
cruelly?
A thorough, determined
dislike of me.
A dislike which I cannot
but attribute in
some measure
to jealousy.
Had the late Mr.
D'Arcy liked me less.
His son might have borne
with me better,
but his father's
uncommon attachment
to me irritated him,
I believe,
very early in life.
He had not a temper
to bear
the sort of competition
in which we stood,
the sort of preference
which was often
given me.
I had not thought Mr.
D'Arcy so bad as this,
though
I have never liked him.
I had not thought so
very ill of him.
I had supposed him to.
Be despising his fellow
creatures in.
General,
but did not suspect him
of descending
to such malicious
revenge.
Such injustice.
Such inhumanity
as this.
After a few minutes
reflection, however,
she continued.
I do remember
his boasting.
One day at Netherfield.
Of the implacable
city,
of his resentments.
Of his having
an unforgiving temper.
His disposition
must be dreadful.
I will not trust myself
on the subject.
Replied Wickham.
I can hardly be
just to him.
Elizabeth was
again, deep in thought
and after a time
exclaimed.
To treat in
such a manner
the godson, the friend,
the favorite
of his father.
She could added.
A young man to like you,
whose very countenance
may vouch
for your being amiable.
But she contented
herself.
With and one too,
would probably
his companion
from childhood.
Connected together.
As I think
you said, in the.
Closest manner.
We were born
in the same parish,
within the same park.
The greatest
part of our youth
was passed together.
Inmates
of the same house
sharing the
same amusements.
Objects of the same
parental care.
My father
began life
in the profession
which your uncle, Mr.
Phillips,
appears to do so much
credit to.
But he gave up
everything to be of use
to the late Mr.
D'Arcy,
and devoted his time
to the care of the
Pemberley property.
He was
most highly
esteemed by Mr.
Darcy, a most intimate,
confidential friend.
Mr.
Darcy, often
acknowledged himself
to be under
the greatest obligations
to my father's
active superintendence.
And when?
Immediately
before my father's
death, Mr.
Darcy gave him
a voluntary promise
of providing for me.
I am convinced
that he felt it
to be
as much a debt
of gratitude to him
as of affection
to myself.
How strange!
Cried Elizabeth.
How abominable.
I wonder that the very.
Pride of this Mr..
Darcy has not made him
just to you.
If from
no better motive,
that he should not
have been too proud
to be dishonest
for dishonesty,
I must call it.
It is wonderful.
Replied Wickham.
For almost all
his actions
may be traced to pride.
And pride has
often been his
best friend.
It is connected
him nearer
with virtue
than any other feeling.
But we are none of us
consistent
and in his behavior.
To me,
there were
stronger impulses
even than pride.
Can such
abominable pride
as hares
have ever done him good?
Yes.
It has often
led him to be liberal
and generous
to give his money
freely, to display
hospitality,
to assist his tenants
and relieve the poor
family pride
and filial pride,
for he is very proud
of what his father was.
Have done this
not to appear
to disgrace his family.
To degenerate
from the
popular qualities
or lose the influence
of the Pemberley house
is a powerful motive.
He has also
brotherly pride, which,
with some
brotherly affection,
makes him very kind
and careful
guardian of his sister.
And you will hear him
generally cried up
as the most attentive
and best of brothers.
What sort of
a girl is Mr.
Darcy?
He shook his head.
I wish I could call her
amiable.
It gives me pain
to speak ill of a Darcy.
But she is too much like
her brother.
Very, very proud.
As a child,
she was affectionate
and pleasing
and extremely
fond of me.
And I have devoted hours
and hours
to her amusement.
But she is
nothing to me now.
She is a handsome
girl, about 15 or 16.
And I understand.
Highly accomplished.
Since her
father's death,
her home
has been London,
where a lady lives with
and superintend
her education.
After many pauses
and many trials
of other subjects.
Elizabeth could not
help, reverting
once more to the first
and saying.
I am astonished
at his intimacy with Mr.
Bingley.
How can Mr.
Bingley, who seems good
humor itself
and is,
I really believe,
truly amiable
being with such a man.
How can they suit
each other?
Do you know Mr.
Bingley?
Not at all.
He is a sweet
tempered,
amiable, charming man.
He cannot know what Mr.
Darcy is.
Probably not.
But Mr.
Darcy can please
where he chooses.
He does not
want abilities.
He can be
a convertible companion
if he thinks it
worth his while.
Among those
who are at all
his equals.
In consequence,
he is a very
different man
from what
he is
to the less prosperous.
His pride
never deserts him,
but with the rich,
he is liberal minded,
just sincere,
rational, honorable
and perhaps agreeable,
allowing something
for fortune and figure.
The West Party.
Soon afterwards,
breaking up,
the players gathered
round the other table,
and Mr.
Collins took his station
between his cousin
Elizabeth and Mrs..
The usual inquiries
as to his success
was made by the latter.
It had not been
very great.
He had lost every point.
But when Mrs.
Phillips began
to express her
concern, thereupon
he assured her with much
earnest gravity,
that it was not
of the least importance
that he considered
the money
as a mere trifle,
and begged
that she would
not make herself.
I know very well, madam.
Said he.
That when persons
sit down
to a card table,
they must take
their chance
of these things
and happily
I am not in
such circumstances
as to make
five shillings
any object.
There are
undoubtedly many
who could not
say the same.
But thanks to Lady
Catherine de Borg,
I am removed far
beyond the necessity
of regarding
little matters.
Mr.
Wickham's
attention was caught
and after observing Mr.
Collins
for a few moments.
He asked Elizabeth.
In a low voice
whether her relation
was very intimately
acquainted
with the family of De.
Berg,
Lady Catherine de Berg.
She replied.
Has very lately
given him a living.
I hardly know how Mr.
Collins was first
introduced to
her notice.
But he certainly has
not known how long.
You know,
of course,
that lady
Catherine de Borg
and Lady
and Darcy were sisters.
Consequently,
that she is aunt
to the present.
Mr. Darcy?
No, indeed,
I did not.
I knew
nothing at all of Lady
Katherine's connections.
I never heard
of her existence
till the day
before yesterday.
Her daughter, Mr.
Borg,
will have
a very large fortune.
And it is believed
that she and her cousin
will unite the
two estates.
This information
made Elizabeth smile
as she thought of poor
Miss Bingley.
Vain, indeed
must be all
her attentions,
vain and useless.
Her affection
for his sister
and her
praise of himself
if he were already self
destined for another.
Mr.
Collins said.
She speaks highly,
both of Lady Catherine
and her daughter,
but in some particulars
that he is
related of her Ladyship.
I suspect his gratitude
misleads him and.
That in spite of her
being his.
Patroness,
she is an arrogant,
conceited woman.
I believe her to be
both in a great degree,
replied Wickham.
I have not seen her
for many years,
but I very well remember
that I never liked her
and that her manners
were dictatorial
and insolent.
She has the reputation
of being remarkably
sensible and clever,
but I rather believe
she derives
part of her abilities
from her rank
and fortune,
apart
from her
authoritative manner
and the rest from the
pride of her nephew
who chooses
everyone connected
with him
should have
an understanding of
the first class.
Elizabeth allowed
that he had given
a very
rational account of it.
And they continued
talking.
Together
with mutual satisfaction
till supper,
put an end to cards
and gave the rest
of the ladies
their share of Mr.
Wickham's attentions.
There could be.
No conversation in the.
Noise of Mrs.
Phillips supper party,
but his manners
recommended him
to everybody.
Whatever he said
was well said,
and whatever he did
done gracefully.
Elizabeth went away
with, her head
full of him.
She could think
of nothing but of Mr.
Wickham.
And of.
What he had told her
all the way home.
But there was not time
for her
even to mention his name
as they went
for neither Lydia.
Mr.
Collins were
once silent.
Lydia talked
incessantly of lottery
tickets of the fish
she had lost
and the fish
she had won.
And Mr.
Collins, in describing
the civility of Mr.
and Mrs. Phillips.
Protesting that he did.
Not in the least
regard his.
Losses at whist.
Enumerating all
the dishes at supper.
And repeatedly fearing
that he crowded
his cousins.
Had more to say
than he could
well manage
before the carriage
stopped at
Longhorn House.
Chapter 17.
Elizabeth Related
to Jane the next day
what had passed
between Mr.
Wickham and herself.
Jane listened
with astonishment
and concern.
She knew not
how to believe that Mr.
Darcy could be
so unworthy of Mr.
Bailey's regard.
And yet
it was not in her nature
to question the veracity
of a young man
of such
amiable appearance
as Wickham.
The possibility
of his having endured
such unkindness
was enough to interest
all her tender feelings,
and nothing remained
therefore to be done,
but to think
well of them both,
to defend the conduct
of each and throw
into the account
of accident or mistake,
whatever could
not be otherwise
explained.
They have both said
she been deceived.
I daresay in some way
or other
of which we can form.
No idea.
Interested people have
perhaps misrepresented
each to the other.
It is, in short,
impossible
for us to conjecture
the causes
or circumstances
which may have
alienated them
without actual blame
on either side.
Very true indeed.
And now, my dear
Jane,
what have you got to on
behalf of the interested
people
who have
probably been concerned
in the business?
Do you clear them too?
Or we shall be obliged
to think of somebody
love as
as you choose.
But you will not
laugh me
out of my opinion.
My dearest Lizzie.
But do consider in what
a disgraceful light
it pleases. Mr.
Darcy
to be treating
his father's favorite
in such a manner.
One whom his father.
Had promised
to provide for.
It is impossible.
No man of
common humanity,
no man who had any value
for his character
could be capable of it.
Can his most
intimate friends
be so excessively
deceived in?
Oh, no.
I can much more easily
believe Mr.
Bingley is
being imposed on
then that Mr.
Wickham
should invent
such a history
of himself
as he gave me
last night.
Names,
facts, everything.
Mentioned without.
Ceremony.
If it be not so, let Mr.
Darcy contradict it.
Besides,
there was truth
in looks.
It is difficult.
Indeed,
it is distressing.
One does not know
what to think.
I beg your pardon?
One knows what to think.
But Jane could think
with certainty
on only one.
Point.
That Mr.
Bingley.
If he had been imposed
on, would have.
Much to suffer
when the affair
became public.
The two young ladies.
Were summoned
from the shrubbery,
where this
conversation passed
by the arrival
of the very persons
of whom they had been.
Speaking. Mr.
Bingley and his sisters
came to give
their personal
invitation
for the long expected
ball at Netherfield,
which was fixed
for the
following Tuesday.
The two ladies
were delighted
to see their dear
friend again,
called it an age
since they had.
Met
and repeatedly asked.
What she had
been doing with herself
since their.
Separation.
To the rest of
the family.
They paid
little attention,
avoiding Mrs.
Bennett
as much as possible,
saying
not much to Elizabeth
and nothing
at all to the others.
They were soon
gone again, rising
from their seats
with an activity
which took their brother
by surprise
and hurrying off
as if eager to escape
from Mrs.
Bennett's civilities.
The prospect of
the Netherfield Ball
was extremely agreeable
to every female
of the family.
Mrs.
Bennett chose
to consider it
as given in compliment
to her eldest daughter
and was
particularly flattered
by receiving
the invitation from Mr.
Bingley himself.
Instead of a
ceremonious card,
Jane pictured
to herself
a happy evening
in the society
of her two friends.
And the.
Attentions of
her brother.
And Elizabeth thought
pleasure of dancing
a great deal with Mr..
Wickham and of seeing.
A confirmation
of everything in Mr.
Darcy's look
and behavior.
The happiness
anticipated by Katherine
and Lydia depended
less on any single event
or on any
particular person.
Four.
Though
they each
like Elizabeth.
Meant.
To dance
half the evening
with Mr. Wickham.
He was by no means
only partner
who could satisfy them,
and a ball was,
at any rate, a ball.
And even Mary
could assure her family
that she
had no disinclination
for it.
While I can have
my mornings to myself,
said she,
it is enough.
I think it is
no sacrifice
to join occasionally
in evening engagements.
Society
claims on us all,
and I profess myself
one of those who
consider intervals
of recreation
and amusement
as desirable
for everybody.
Elizabeth Spirits
were so high on
this occasion.
That though
she did not often.
Speak
unnecessarily to Mr.
Collins.
She could not help.
Asking him
whether he intended
to accept Mr.
Bigley's.
Invitation
and if he did.
Whether he would think
it proper to join
in the.
Evening's amusement.
And she was rather
surprised to find
that he entertained
no scruple whatsoever
on that head
and was very far
from dreading a rebuke,
either
from the archbishop
or Lady
Catherine de Berg
by venturing to dance.
I am by no means of
opinion, I assure you.
Said he.
That a ball of this
kind given
by a young man
of character
to respectable people
can have any evil
tendency.
And I am so far
from objecting
to dancing myself
that I shall hope
to be honored
with the hands
of all my fair cousins
in the course
of the evening.
And I take
this opportunity
of soliciting
yours, Miss Elizabeth,
for the two
first dances, especially
a preference
which I trust my cousin
Jane.
When a tribute
to the right cause
and not to
any disrespect for her.
Elizabeth felt herself
completely taken in.
She had fully proposed
being engaged by Mr.
Wickham
for those very dances
and to have Mr.
Collins instead.
Her liveliness
had never been
worse timed.
There was no help
for it.
However, Mr.
Wickham's happiness
and her own
were perforce
delayed a little longer,
and Mr.
Collins
proposal accepted
with as good
a grace as she could.
She was not.
The better pleased
with his gallantry
from the idea.
Suggested of
something more.
It now first struck her.
That.
She was selected
from among her sisters
as worthy
of being mistress
of Hansford Parsonage
and of assisting to form
a quadrille table
at Rose
Ings in the absence
of more eligible
visitors.
The idea soon.
Reached a conviction.
As.
She observed
as increasing
civilities herself
and her
his frequent attempt
at a compliment
on her wit and vivacity.
And though
more astonished
than gratified herself
by the
effect of her charms,
it was not long
before her
mother gave her
to understand that
the probability
of their marriage
was extremely agreeable
to her.
Elizabeth, however,
did not choose
to take the hint.
Being well aware
that a serious dispute
must be the consequence
of any reply.
Mr.
Collins might
never make the offer.
And still he did.
It was useless.
To quarrel about him
if there had not
another field ball
to prepare for
and talk of the younger
Miss Bennetts
would have been
in a very pitiable state
at this time. Four.
From the.
Day of the invitation.
To the day of the ball,
there was such
a succession
rain as prevented
their walking to merit.
And once
no aunt, no officers.
No news could.
Be sought after.
The very shoe roses
for Netherfield were by.
Even Elizabeth
might have found
some trial
of her patience
and weather,
which totally suspended
the improvement
of her acquaintance
with Mr. Wickham.
Has nothing.
Less than a
dance On Tuesday.
Could have made such
a Friday, Saturday,
Sunday and Monday
endurable to Kitty
and Lydia.
Chapter 18
Till Elizabeth entered
the drawing room
at Netherfield
and looked in vain
for Mr. Wickham.
Among the cluster
of red coats
there assembled.
A doubt of his.
Being present,
had never to her
the certainty of
meeting him
and not being shocked
by any of
those recollections
that might
not unreasonably
have alarmed her.
She had dressed with
more than usual care
and, prepared
in the highest spirits
for the conquest
of all that remained
on, subdued
of his heart,
trusting that it was not
more than might be won
in the course
of the evening.
But in an instant rose
the dreadful suspicion
of his.
Being purposely
omitted for Mr.
Darcy's pleasure
in the binky's
invitation
to the officers.
And though this was.
Not exactly the case,
the absolute
fact of his absence
was pronounced
by his friend Danny,
to whom
Lydia eagerly applied,
and who told them
that Wickham
had been obliged
to go to town
on business
the day before
and was not
yet returned,
adding with a
significant smile.
I do not imagine
his business
would have
called him away just now
if he had not wish
to avoid a
certain gentleman here.
This part of
his intelligence,
although unheard
by Lydia,
was caught by Elizabeth,
and as it assured her
that Darcy was not less
answerable
for Wickham's absence
than if her
first surmise
had been, just.
Every.
Feeling of displeasure
against the former
was so sharpened
by immediate
disappointment
that she could
hardly reply,
with tolerable civility
to the polite inquiries
which he
directly afterwards
approached to make
attendance.
Forbearance.
Patience with Darcy.
Was.
Injury to Wickham.
She was.
Resolved against any.
Sort of conversation
with him and turned.
Away with a degree
of ill humor,
which she could not
wholly surmount.
Even in speaking to Mr.
Bingley,
whose blind partiality
provoked her.
But Elizabeth
was not formed
for ill humor,
and though
every prospect
of her own
was destroyed
for the evening.
It could not long.
Dwell on her spirits.
And having.
Told all her griefs
to Charlotte.
Lucas, whom she had not.
Seen for a week,
she was soon able
to make
a voluntary transition
to the oddities
of her cousin
and to point him out
to her
particular notice.
The first two dances,
however,
brought a
return of distress.
They were dances of
mortification, Mr.
Collins,
awkward and solemn,
apologizing
instead of attending
and often moving wrong
without being
aware of it,
gave her all the shame
and misery
which a
disagreeable partner
for a couple of dances
can give.
The moment of.
Her release from
him was Ecstasy.
She danced next with an.
Officer
and had the refreshment
of talking of Wickham.
And.
Of hearing
that he was
universally liked.
When those dances
were over,
she returned
to Charlotte Lucas
and was in conversation
with her
when she found herself
suddenly addressed
by Mr.
Darcy,
who took her
so much by surprise
and his
application for her
that without knowing.
What she did, she.
Accepted him.
He walked away again
immediately
and she was left
to fret over her own
want of
presence of mind.
Charlotte
Tried to console her.
I daresay will find him
very agreeable.
Heaven forbid.
That would be
the greatest misfortune
of all.
To find a man agreeable
one is
determined to hate.
Do not wish me
such an evil.
When the dancing.
Recommenced,
however, and Darcy
approached to claim
her hand.
Charlotte could
not help.
Cautioning her
in a whisper
not to be a simpleton
and allow her fancy
for Wickham
to make her appear
unpleasant in the eyes
of a man of ten times
his consequence.
Elizabeth made answer
and took her
place in the set.
Amazed at the dignity
to which.
She was arrived
and being allowed
to stand opposite to Mr.
Darcy and reading it,
her neighbors
looks their amazement
and beholding it.
They stood for some time
without speaking a word,
and she began to imagine
that their silence
was to last
in the two dances.
And at first
she was resolved
not to break it
till suddenly fancying
that it would be
the greater punishment
to her partner
to oblige him to talk.
She made
some slight observation
on the dance.
He replied
and was again.
Silent
after a pause
of some minutes.
She addressed him
a second time with.
It is your turn
to say something now.
Mr. Darcy.
I talked
about the dance,
and you ought to make
some sort of remark
on the size of the room
or the number
of couples.
He smiled
and assured her
that whatever
she wished him to say
should be.
Said very well.
That reply will.
Do for the present.
Perhaps by and by
I may observe.
That private balls.
Are much pleasanter
than public ones.
But now we may
be silent.
Do you talk
by rule then,
while you are dancing?
Sometimes
one must speak
a little, you know.
It would look odd
to be entirely silent
for half an hour
together.
And yet,
for the advantages
of some conversation
ought to be so arranged.
As they might have
the trouble of.
Saying
as little as possible.
Are you consulting
own feelings
in the present case,
or do you imagine
that you are
gratifying mine?
Both.
Replied
Elizabeth archly.
For I have always seen
a great similarity
the town of our minds.
We are each of
an unsocial, taciturn
disposition,
unwilling to speak
unless.
We expect
to say something
upon the Mays.
The whole room,
and be handed
to posterity.
With all the eclat
of a proverb.
This is no very striking
resemblance
of your own character.
I am sure.
Said he.
How near it may be
to mine.
I cannot to say.
You think
it's a faithful
portrait? Undoubtedly.
I must
not decide on my
own performance.
He made no answer.
And they were again
silent,
until they had gone
down the dance.
When he asked her
if she and her sisters
did not very often walk
to Maritain,
she answered in
the affirmative
and unable
to resist the.
Temptation, added
When you met us there
the other day, we had
just been forming
a new acquaintance.
The effect
was immediate.
A deeper shade
of hauteur
over Sparta's features.
But he said not a word.
And Elizabeth,
though blaming herself
for her own weakness,
could not go on.
At length, Dorothy spoke
and in a
constrained manner,
said.
Mr.
Wickham is blessed
with such happy manners
as may ensure
his making friends.
Whether he may be
equally capable
of retaining them
is less certain.
He has been so
unlucky as to lose
your friendship.
Replied Elizabeth,
with emphasis.
And in a manner
which he is
likely to suffer
from all his life.
Darcy made no answer
and seemed desirous
of changing the subject.
At that moment,
Sir William
Lucas appeared
close to them, meaning
to pass through the set
to the other
side of the room.
But on proceeding, Mr..
Darcy, he stopped
with a bow of superior
courtesy
to compliment him
on his dancing
and his partner.
I have been most
highly gratified.
Indeed, my dear sir.
Such very superior
dancing is not often
seen.
It is evident
that you belong
to the first circles.
Allow me to say,
however, that
your fair partner
does not disgrace you
and that I must hope
to have this pleasure
often repeated,
especially when a
certain desirable event.
My dear Miss Eliza.
Glancing,
her sister and Bingley.
Shall take place.
What?
Congratulations
will then flow in.
I appeal to Mr.
Darcy.
But let me not
interrupt you, sir.
You will not thank me
for detaining you
from the
bewitching converse
of that young lady
whose bright
eyes are also
upbraiding me.
The latter
part of this address
was scarcely
heard by Darcy.
But Sir
William's allusion
to his friend
seemed to strike him
forcibly,
and his eyes
were directed
with a
very serious expression
towards Bingley and Jane
who were dancing
together.
Recovering himself.
However, shortly
he turned to his partner
and said.
Sir William's
interruption
has made me forget
what we were talking.
I do not think we were
speaking at all.
Sir William
could not
have interrupted
two people in the wrong
who had less to say
for themselves.
We have tried
two or three
subjects
already without.
Success
and what
we are to talk of next.
I cannot imagine.
What think you of books?
Said he, smiling.
Perks.
Ho no,
I am sure
we never read
the same or not
with the same feelings.
I am sorry.
You think so?
But if that be the case,
there can at least be
no want of subject.
We compare our different
opinions.
No, I cannot talk of
books in a ballroom.
My head is always full
of something else.
The present
always occupies.
You in such scenes.
Does it?
Said he,
with a look of doubt.
Yes.
Always, she replied,
without knowing
what she said, for her
thoughts had
wandered
far from the subject
as soon afterwards
appeared by her
suddenly exclaiming.
I remember hearing you
once say, Mr.
Darcy, that you hardly
ever forgave
that your resentment
once created
was on a peaceable.
You are very cautious,
I suppose, as to its
being created.
I am.
Said he,
with a firm voice,
and never allow yourself
to be blinded
by prejudice.
I hope not.
It is
particularly incumbent
on those
who never change
their opinion
to be secure of judging
properly at first.
May I
ask to what
these questions tend.
Merely
to the illustration
of your character?
Said she endeavoring,
to shake off
her gravity.
I am trying.
To make it out.
And what is
your success?
She shook her head.
I do not get on at all.
I such different
accounts of you
as to puzzle
me exceedingly.
I can readily believe.
Answered he gravely.
That reports may vary
greatly with respect
to me,
and I could
wish Miss Bennet
that you were not
to sketch
my character
at the present moment,
as there is reason
to fear
that the performance
would reflect
no credit on either.
But if I do not to take
your likeness now,
I may never have
another opportunity.
I would by no means
suspend
any pleasure of yours.
He called the replied.
She said no more.
And they went down
the other dance
and parted in silence.
And on each.
Side dissatisfied,
though
not to an equal degree.
For in Dorothy's breast
there was a tolerable
powerful
feeling towards her.
Which soon procured her.
Pardon and directed all
his anger
against another.
They had
not long separated.
When Miss Bingley came
towards her
and with an expression
of civil disdain,
accosted her.
So, Miss Eliza,
I hear
you are quite delighted
with George Wickham.
Your sister has been
talking to me about him
and asking me a
thousand questions.
And I find that
the young man
quite forgot
to tell you,
among his
other communication,
that he was
the son of Old Wickham.
The late Mr.
Darcy Stewart.
Let me recommend you,
however, as a friend,
not to
give implicit confidence
to all his assertions
for as to Mr.
Darcy's using him ill,
it is perfectly false
for on the contrary,
he has always
been remarkably
kind to him.
Though
George Wickham
is treated Mr.
Darcy
in a most
infamous manner,
I do not know
the particulars,
but I know
very well that Mr.
Darcy is not
at least to blame,
that he cannot bear
to hear
George
Wickham mentioned.
And that though
my brother thought
that he could not
well avoid including him
in his invitation
to the officers,
he was excessively
glad to that
he had taken himself
out of the way.
His coming into
the country at all
is the
most insolent thing.
Indeed.
And I wonder
how he could
presume to do it.
I pity Miss Eliza
for this discovery
of your favorites guilt.
But really,
considering his descent,
one could not
expect much better.
His guilt and his
descent appear
by your account,
to be the same.
Said Elizabeth angrily.
For I have heard
you accuse him
of nothing
worse than being
the son of Mr.
Darcy Stewart.
And of that,
I can assure you,
he informed me himself.
I beg your pardon?
Replied Miss Bingley,
turning away
with a sneer.
Excuse my interference.
It was kindly meant
insolent girl.
Said Elizabeth
to herself.
You are much.
Mistaken if you expect.
To influence me
by such a paltry attack
as this.
I see nothing in it
but your own
willful ignorance
and the malice of Mr.
Darcy.
She then sought out
her eldest sister,
who has undertaken
to make inquiries
on the same
subject of Bingley.
Jane met her
with a smile of such
sweet complacency,
a glow of such
happy expression.
As sufficiently.
Marked how
well she was satisfied
with the occurrences
of the evening.
Elizabeth instantly
read her feelings,
and at that
moment solicitude
for Wickham resentment
against his enemies
and everything else.
Gave way
before the hope
of Jane's.
Being in the fairest way
for happiness.
I want to know,
said she.
With a countenance
no less smiling
than her sisters.
What do you have learned
about Mr.
Wickham?
But perhaps
you've been too
pleasantly engaged
to think of
any third person,
in which case you may be
sure of my pardon.
No, replied Jane.
I have not
forgotten him.
But have nothing
unsatisfactory
to tell you.
Mr.
Bingley just don't know.
The whole of
his history, and he.
Is quite
ignorant of
the circumstances
which have principally.
Offended Mr.
Darcy.
But he will
vouch for the good,
the probity
and honor of his friend,
and is perfectly
convinced. That Mr.
Wickham has deserved
much less attention
from Mr.
Darcy
than he has received.
And I am sorry to.
Say by account,
as well as his sisters.
Mr.
Wickham is by no means
a respectable young man.
I am afraid
he has been
very imprudent
and has deserved
to lose Mr.
Darcy's regard.
Mr.
Bingley
just don't know Mr.
Wickham himself.
No, he never saw him
till the other morning
at Meriton.
This account,
then, is
what he has received
from Mr.
Darcy.
I am satisfied.
But what does he say
of the living?
He does not
exactly recollect
the circumstances,
though
he has heard them. Mr.
Darcy more than once,
but believes
that it was left to him
conditionally only.
I have not
a doubt of Mr.
Bingley sincerity.
Said Elizabeth warmly.
But he must excuse my
not being convinced
by assurances.
Only Mr.
Bingley,
his defense
of his friend,
was a very able one,
I daresay,
but since he
is unacquainted
with several
parts of the story
and has learned the rest
from that
friend himself,
I shall venture to
still think
of both gentlemen
as I did before.
She then.
Changed the discourse
to one more
gratifying each
and on which
there could be
no difference of.
Sentiment.
Elizabeth listened
with delight
to the happy,
though modest hopes
which Jane entertained
of Mr.
Bingley regard,
and said
all in her power
to heighten
her confidence in it.
On their being joined
by Mr.
Bingley himself.
Elizabeth withdrew
to Miss Lucas.
To whose.
Inquiry
after the pleasantness
of her last partner
she had scarcely replied
before Mr.
Collins came up to them
and told her
with great exaltation.
That he had
just been
so fortunate as.
To make a most important
discovery.
I have found out,
said he,
by a singular accident,
that there is now
in the room
a near relation
to my patroness.
I happened to overhear
the gentleman himself
mentioning to
the young lady
who does the honors
of this house
the names of
his cousin, Mr.
Borg, and of her mother,
Lady Katharine.
How Wonderfully,
these sort of things
occur.
Who would have thought
of my meeting
with perhaps
a nephew of Lady
Katharine de Borg
in this assembly?
I am most thankful
the discovery is made
in time for me
to pay my respects
to him,
which I am now
going to do and trust.
He will excuse my
not having done it
before.
My total
ignorance of
the connection
must plead my apology.
You are not going
to introduce yourself
to Mr. Darcy.
Indeed I am.
I shall entreat
his pardon
for not having
done it earlier.
I believe him to be Lady
Catherine's nephew.
It will be in my power
to assure him
that her Ladyship
was quite
well yesterday.
The night.
Elizabeth tried hard to.
Dissuade him
from such a scheme.
Assuring him that Mr.
Darcy would consider
his addressing him
without introduction
as an
impertinent freedom,
rather than a compliment
to his aunt that it was
not in the least
necessary.
There should be
any notice
on either side.
And that if it.
Were, it must belong
to Mr.
Darcy,
the superior
in consequence to.
Begin the acquaintance.
Mr.
Collins listened to her
with the
determined error
of following
his own inclination.
And when she ceased
speaking, replied
thus.
My dear Miss Elizabeth,
I have the
highest opinion
in the world
of your
excellent judgment
in all matters
within the scope
of your understanding.
But permit me to say
that there must be
a wide difference.
The established forms
of ceremony
amongst the laity
and those
which regulate
the clergy.
Forgive me
leave to observe that
I consider
the clerical office
as equal in point.
Dignity with the highest
rank in the kingdom,
provided that a
proper
humility of behavior
is at the same time
maintained.
You must
therefore allow me
to follow the dictates
of my conscience
on this occasion,
which lead me to perform
what I look on
as a point of duty.
Pardon me for neglecting
to profit
by your advice,
which on every
other subject shall be
my constant guide.
Though
in the case
before us,
I consider myself
more fitted by education
and habitual study
to decide
what is right
than a young lady
like yourself.
And with a low bough.
He left her
to attack Mr.
Darcy,
whose reception
of his advances.
She eagerly watched.
And whose.
Astonishment at being so
addressed
was very evident.
Her cousin prefaced
his speech
with a solemn vow,
and though
she could not hear
a word of it, she felt
as if hearing it all
and saw in.
The motion of his lips
the words apology
Hansford
and Lady
Catherine de Berg.
It vexed her to
see him expose
to such a man.
Mr.
Darcy was eyeing him
with unrestrained
wonder,
and when at last Mr.
Collins allowed him
time to speak, replied
with an air of
distant civility.
Mr.
Collins,
however, was
not discouraged
from speaking again,
and Mr.
Darcy's contempt seemed
abundantly increasing
with the length
of his second speech.
And at the end of it
he only made him a.
Slight bow
and moved another way.
Mr.
Collins
then returned
to Elizabeth.
I have no reason,
I assure you, said he,
to be dissatisfied
with my reception.
Mr.
Darcy seemed much
pleased with
the attention.
He answered me
with the utmost civility
and even paid me
the compliment
of saying that
he was so well
convinced of Lady
Katherine's discernment
as to be certain
she could never bestow
a favor unworthy.
It was really a
very handsome thought
upon the whole.
I am much with him.
As Elizabeth had
no longer
any interest
of her own to pursue.
She turned her attention
almost entirely
on her sister and Mr.
Bingley
and the train
of agreeable reflections
which her
observations gave
birth to, made her
perhaps almost as happy
as Jane.
She saw her in ideas,
settled in
that very house
in all the Felicity
a marriage of
true affection
could bestow.
And she felt capable.
Under such circumstances
of endeavoring even
to like
being these two sisters.
Her mother's
thought she saw
were bent the same way,
and she determined
not to venture
near her, lest
she might hear too much.
When they sat down
to supper.
Therefore,
she considered it
a most unlucky Innes,
which placed them
within one of each other
and deeply
what she vexed to find
that her mother
was talking
to that one person.
Lady Lucas.
Freely, openly
and of nothing
but her expectation
that Jane would soon
be married to Mr.
Bingley.
It was an.
Animating subject,
and Mrs.
Bennett seemed
incapable of.
Fatigue while.
Enumerating
the advantages
of the match.
His being such.
A charming young man
and so rich and living.
But three miles
from them
were the first points
of self granulation.
And then it was
such a comfort.
Think
how fond the two sisters
were of Jane,
and to be certain
that they must
desire the connection
as much as she could do.
It was, moreover,
such a promising thing
for her
younger daughters,
as Jane's marrying
so greatly must
throw them
in the way of other
rich men.
And lastly,
it was so pleasant
at her time of life
to be able
to consign her
single daughters
to the care
of their sister,
that she might
not be obliged
to go into company
more than she liked.
It was.
Necessary
to make
this circumstance
a matter of pleasure,
because.
On such occasions
it is the etiquette.
But no one was
less likely than Mrs.
Bennett to find comfort
and staying home at any
period of her life.
She concluded
with many good wishes
that Lady Lucas
might soon
be equally fortunate.
Though evidently
triumphantly believing
there was
no chance of it
in vain.
Did Elizabeth endeavor
to check the rapidity
of her mother's words
or persuade her
to describe her?
Felicity,
in a less audible
whisper for to her
inexpressible vexation?
She could perceive
that the chief of
it was overheard by Mr.
Darcy,
who sat
opposite to them.
Her mother only
scolded her
for being nonsensical.
What is Mr.
Darcy to me?
Pray that
I should be
afraid of him.
I am sure we owe him
no such
particular civility
as to be obliged
to say nothing.
He not like to hear.
For heaven's sake,
madam, speak lower.
What advantage can.
It be
for you to offend Mr.
Darcy?
You will never
recommend yourself
to his friend
by so doing.
Nothing that
she could say,
however,
had any influence.
Her mother would talk of
her views
in the same
intelligible tone.
Elizabeth blushed
and blushed again
with shame and vexation.
She could not help.
Frequently
glancing her eye at Mr.
Darcy,
though every glance
convinced her
of what she dreaded,
for though
he was not always
looking at her mother.
She Was convinced
that his attention
was invariably fixed
on her.
The expression of his.
Face changed gradually,
from indignant contempt.
To a composed and.
Steady gravity.
At length, however,
Bennet
had no more to say,
and Lady Lucas,
who had been long
yawning
at the repetition
of delights
which she saw
no likelihood
of sharing, was left
to the comforts
of cold ham and chicken.
Elizabeth now
began to revive.
But not long
was the interval
of tranquility for
when supper was over.
Singing was talked.
Of.
And she had
the mortification
of seeing, after
very little entreaty,
preparing to oblige
the company.
By.
Many significant looks
and silent entreaties.
Did she endeavor
to prevent
such a
proof of complacence
but in vain?
Mary would
not understand then
such an opportunity
of exhibiting
was delightful to her,
and she began her song.
Elizabeth's eyes
were fixed on, her
with most
painful sensations,
and she watched
her progress
through the
several stanzas
with an impatience,
which was very
ill rewarded
at their close for Mary.
On receiving
amongst the
thanks of the.
Table
the hint of a hope.
That she might
be prevailed on
to favor them again.
After the pause.
Of half a minute
began another.
Mary's powers
were by no. Means.
Fitted for a display.
Her voice was weak
and her manner affected.
Elizabeth was
in agonies.
She looked at.
Jane to see how she.
Bore it.
But Jane was
very composed,
oddly,
talking to Bingley.
She looked at his two.
Sisters and saw them
making signs of derision
at each other
and at Darcy,
who continued, however
imperturbable,
the grave.
She looked at her father
to entreaties,
interference. Lest.
Mary should be
singing all night.
He took the hint.
And when Mary had
finished, her
second song said
aloud.
That will do
extremely well, child.
You have delighted us
long enough.
Let the other
young ladies
have time to exhibit.
Mary, though
pretending not to hear,
was disconcerted.
And Elizabeth.
Sorry for her.
And sorry
for her father's speech.
Was afraid
her anxiety had done
no good.
Others of the party
were now applied to.
If I.
Said Mr.
Collins.
Were so fortunate
as to be able to sing,
I should have
great pleasure.
I am sure
in obliging the company
with an heir,
for I consider
as a very
innocent diversion
and perfectly compatible
with the
profession of
a clergyman.
I do not mean,
however, to assert
that we can be justified
in devoting
too much
our time to music,
for there are
certainly other things
to be attended to.
The rector of a parish
has much to do.
In the first place
he must make such
agreement for tithes
as may be beneficial
to himself
and not offensive
to his patron.
He must write
his own sermons,
and the time
that remains
will not be too much
for his parish duties
and the care
and improvement
of his dwelling,
which he cannot
be excused
from making
as comfortable
as possible.
And I do not think it
of light importance
that he should have
and conciliatory manners
towards everybody,
especially towards
those to
whom he owes
his preferment.
I cannot acquit
him of that duty,
nor could I think
well of the man
who should omit
an occasion
of testifying
his respect
towards
anybody connected
with the family.
And with a bow to Mr.
Darcy.
He concluded his speech.
Which had.
Been spoken
so loud as to be heard
by half the room.
Many stared.
Many smiled.
But no one looked.
More amused than Mr.
himself.
While his wife
seriously.
Commended Mr.
Collins
for having spoken
so sensibly and observed
and a half
whisper to Lady Lucas
that he was a
remarkably clever good
kind of young man.
To Elizabeth,
it appeared that had
her family
made an agreement
to expose themselves
as much as
they could
during the evening.
It would have
been impossible.
For them
to play their parts
with more spirit
or finer success
and happy.
Did she think it
for Bingley
and her sister
that some of
the exhibition
had escaped his notice
and that his feelings
were not of a sort,
to be much distressed
by the folly
which he must
have witnessed, that
his two sisters and Mr.
Darcy, however,
should have such
an opportunity
of ridiculing her.
Relations was bad.
Enough
and she could not.
Determine
whether the
silent contempt
of the gentleman
or the insulin
smiles of the ladies
were more intolerable.
The rest of the
evening
brought her little.
She was.
Teased by Mr.
Collins.
Who continued.
Most perceptively
by her side.
And though he could
not prevail on her
to dance with him again,
put it out of her power
to dance with others
in vain.
Did she?
And treat him
to stand up
with somebody else
and offer
to introduce him
to any young
lady in the room?
He assured her
that as to dancing,
he was
perfectly indifferent
to it,
that his chief object
was by
delicate attentions
to recommend
himself to her,
and that he should
therefore make a point
of remaining
close to her
the whole evening.
There was no arguing
such a project.
She owed her
greatest relief
to her friend,
Miss Lucas.
Who often joined them
and good.
Naturedly engaged Mr.
Collins conversation
to herself.
She was at.
Least free from
the offense of Mr.
Darcy's further notice,
though often standing
within a very short
distance of her
quite disengaged.
He never came
near enough to speak.
She felt it
to be
the probable consequence
of her allusions to Mr.
Wickham.
And rejoiced in it.
The long born party
with the last
of all the company
to depart,
and by a maneuver, Mrs.
Bennett
had to wait
for their carriage
a quarter of an hour
after everybody
else was gone,
which gave them time
to see how heartily
they were whisked away
by some of the family.
Mrs.
Hurst and her sister
scarcely
opened their mouths
except to
complain of fatigue
and were
evidently impatient
to have the house
to themselves.
They repulsed
every attempt of Mrs.
Bennett's conversation,
and by doing so, threw
a languor
over the whole party,
which was very
little relieved
by the long speeches
of Mr.
Collins,
who was
complimenting Mr.
Bingley and his sisters
on the elegance
of their entertainment.
And.
The hospitality
and politeness
which had marked
their behavior
to their guests.
Darcy said
nothing at all.
Mr.
Bennett, in
equal silence,
was enjoying the scene.
Mr.
Bingley
and Jane
were standing together,
a little detached
from the rest,
and talked
only to each other.
Elizabeth preserved
a steady,
a silence,
as either Mrs.
Hirst or Miss Bingley.
And.
Even Lydia
was too much fatigued
to utter more
than the
occasional exclamation.
Of Lord,
how tired I am.
Accompanied by a violent
yawn,
when at length
they arose to
take leave.
Mrs.
Bennett was most
pressingly civil
in her hope
of seeing the
whole family
soon at Long Bourn,
and addressed herself,
especially to Mr.
Bingley. To.
Assure him how happy
he would make them
by eating
a family dinner
with them at any time
without the ceremony
of a formal invitation.
Bingley was all
grateful pleasure,
and he readily engaged
for taking
the earliest opportunity
of waiting on her
after his return
from London.
Whether he was obliged
to go
the next day for a short
time, Mrs.
Bennett was
perfectly satisfied
and quitted
the house,
under the
delightful persuasion
that allowing
for the necessary
preparation
of settlements,
new carriages
and wedding clothes.
She should undoubtedly.
See her daughter
settled at Netherfield
in the course of three
or four months
of having
another daughter
married to Mr..
Collins.
She thought
with equal certainty
and with considerable,
though
not equal pleasure.
Elizabeth was
the least dear to her
of all her children.
And though
the match and the man
were quite good
enough for her,
the worth of each
was eclipsed by Mr.
Bingley and Netherfield.
Chapter 19.
The next day opened.
A new.
Scene and long born Mr.
Collins
made his declaration
in form
having resolved to do it
without loss of time,
as his leave of absence
extended only
to the
following Saturday
and having no feelings
of diffidence
to make it
distressing himself
even at the moment,
he set about it
in a very orderly manner
with all the observances
which he supposed
a regular part
of the business.
On finding Mrs.
Bennett, Elizabeth
and one of the younger
girls together.
Soon after breakfast,
he addressed the mother
in these words.
May I hope, madame,
for your interest
with your fair
daughter, Elizabeth
when I solicit
for the honor
of a private audience
with her in the course
of this morning.
Before Elizabeth
had time
for anything
but a blush of
surprise Mrs.
Bennett
answered instantly.
Oh, dear.
Yes, certainly.
I am sure
Lizzie would be
very happy.
I am sure she can have
no objection.
Come, Kitty.
I want you.
Upstairs.
And gathering her work
together.
She was hastening away
when Elizabeth
called out.
Dear madam, do not go.
I Beg you will not go.
Mr.
Collins must excuse me.
He can have
nothing to say to me
that anybody need
not hear.
I am going away myself.
No, no, Lizzie.
I desire you to stay
where you are.
And upon
Elizabeth,
seeming really
with vexed
and embarrassed
looks about to escape.
She added, Lizzie,
I insist
upon your staying
and hearing Mr.
Collins.
Elizabeth would
not oppose
such an injunction
and a moment's
consideration,
making her
also sensible.
It would be wisest
to get it over as soon
and as
quietly as possible.
She sat down again
and tried to conceal
by incessant employment
the feelings
which were divided
between distress
and diversion.
Mrs.
Bennett
and Kitty walked.
Off, and as soon.
As they were gone, Mr.
Collins began.
Believe me,
my dear Miss Elizabeth,
that your modesty
so far from doing
you any disservice
rather adds to your
other perfections.
You would have been less
amiable in my eyes
had there
not been this
little unwillingness.
But allow me
to assure you
that I have
your respected mother's
permission for
this address.
You can hardly doubt the
purport of my discourse.
However, your
natural delicacy
may lead
you to dissemble.
My attentions have been
to Mark, to be mistaken.
Almost
As soon as I entered
the house,
I singled you out
as the companion
of my future life.
But before I am run away
with by my feelings
on this subject,
perhaps it will
be advisable
for me
to state my reasons
for marrying
and.
Moreover,
for coming
into Hertfordshire
with the design
of selecting a wife,
as I certainly did.
The idea of Mr.
Collins,
with all his
solemn composure
being run away with
by his feelings,
made Elizabeth so near
laughing
that she could not use
the short pause
he allowed in
any attempt
to stop him further.
And he continued.
My reasons
for marrying are first
that I think it
a right thing
for every clergyman.
In easy circumstances
like myself
to set the
example of matrimony
in his parish.
Secondly,
that I am convinced
it will add very greatly
to my happiness.
And thirdly,
which perhaps
I ought
to have
mentioned earlier,
that it is
the particular advice
and recommendation
of the very noble lady,
whom I have the honor
of calling Patroness
twice
as she condescended
give me her opinion
unasked to
on this subject.
And it was.
But the very
Saturday night
before I left Hansford
between our pools
at Quadrille, while Mrs.
Jenkinson
was arranging Mr.
Borg's footstool
that she said.
Mr.
Collins,
you must marry
a clergyman,
like you must marry,
choose properly, choose
a gentlewoman
for my sake
and for your own.
Let her be an active,
useful.
Sort of person, not.
Brought up high,
but able to make a small
income go a good way.
This my advice.
Find such a
woman as soon as you can
bring her to Hansford
and I will visit her.
Allow me, by the way,
to observe my cousin
that I do not reckon
the notice
and kindness
of Lady
Catherine de Borg
as among
the least
of the advantages
in my power to offer.
You will find her
manners beyond anything
I can.
And your wit
and vivacity, I think
must be
acceptable to her,
especially when tempered
with the silence
and respect
which her rank will
inevitably excite.
Thus much
for my general intention
in the favor
of matrimony,
it remains to be told
why my views
were directed
to long borne
instead of my
own neighborhood,
where I assure you
there are many amiable
young women.
But the fact is
that being as I am
to inherit this estate
after the death
of your own it father,
who, however, may
live many years,
I could not
satisfy myself
without resolving
to choose a wife
from among his daughters
that the loss to them
might be
as little as possible
when the
melancholy event
takes place,
which, however,
as I have already said,
may not be for
several years.
This has been my motive,
my fair cousin
and I flatter myself.
It will not
sink me in your.
And now
nothing remains for me
but to assure you
in the most
animated language
of the violence,
of my affection
to fortune,
I am perfectly
indifferent
and shall make no demand
of that nature
on your father,
since I am well aware
that it could not
be complied with,
and that ?1,000
in the four percents
which will not be yours
till after
your mother's
decease, is all that
you may
ever be entitled to
on that head.
Therefore,
I shall
be uniformly silent
and you may
assure yourself
that no
ungenerous reproach
shall ever pass my lips
when we are married.
It was.
Absolutely necessary
to interrupt him.
Now.
You are too hasty.
She cried.
You forget that
I have made no answer.
Let me do it
without further
loss of time.
Except my
thanks for
the compliment
you were paying me.
I am very sensible
of the honor
of your proposals,
but it is impossible
for me to do
otherwise than
to decline them.
I am not
now to learn.
Replied Collins,
with a
formal wave of the hand.
That it is usual
with young ladies
to reject
the addresses of the man
whom they secretly mean
to accept
when he first applies
for their favor,
and that sometimes
the refusal is repeated
a second
or even a third time.
I am therefore
by no means discouraged
by what you
have just said
and shall hope
to lead you to the altar
ere long.
Upon my words.
Cried Elizabeth.
Your hope is rather
an extraordinary one
after my declaration.
I do assure you that
I am not
one of those
young ladies.
If such young ladies
there are
who are so daring
as to risk
their happiness
on the chance
of being asked
a second time,
I am perfectly serious
in my refusal.
You could not make me
happy.
And I am convinced
that I am
the last woman
in the world
who could make you so
nay were your friend.
Lady Catherine, to know.
Me.
I am persuaded
she would find me
in every respect,
ill qualified
for the situation.
Where it's
certain
that Lady Catherine
would think.
Said Mr.
Collins, very gravely.
But I cannot imagine
that Her Ladyship
would at all
disapprove of you.
And you may be
certain that
when I have the honor
of seeing her again,
I shall speak
in the highest terms
of your modesty economy
and other
amiable qualifications.
Indeed, Mr.
Collins,
All praise of me
will be unnecessary.
You must give me leave
to judge for myself
and pay me
the compliment.
Believing what I say.
I wish you very happy
and very rich.
And by refusing
your hands
do all in my power
to prevent
your being otherwise,
and making.
Me the offer
you must have satisfied
delicacy
of your feelings
with regard to.
My family
and may take possession
of nothing born.
To state with ever.
It falls
without any
self reproach.
This matter
may be considered
therefore as finally
settled.
And rising as she thus.
Spoke.
She would have quitted
the room had Mr..
Collins not
thus addressed her.
When I do
myself the honor
of speaking to you
next on the subject,
I shall hope
to receive
a more favorable answer
than you have
now given me.
Though
I am far from accusing
you of the cruelty at
because I know it
to be
the established custom
of your sex
to reject a man
on the
first application.
And perhaps
you have even now
said as much
to encourage
my suit
as would be consistent
with the true delicacy
of the female character.
Really, Mr.
Collins?
Cried Elizabeth
with some warmth.
You puzzle
me exceedingly.
If what I pay,
the two said
can appear to you
in the form
of encouragement.
I know not
how to express.
My refusal in such.
A way as to convince
you of its being one.
You must give me
leave to flatter myself.
My dear cousin,
that your refusal,
my addresses
are merely words,
Of course.
My reasons
for believing
it are briefly these.
It does not appear to me
that my hand
is unworthy.
Your acceptance,
or that
the establishment
I can offer
would be any other
than highly desirable.
My situation in life,
my connections
with the family
of the book,
and my relationship,
your own
are circumstances
highly in my favor,
and you should take it
into further
consideration that
in spite
of your
manifold attractions,
it is by
no means certain
that another
of marriage may ever
be made you.
Your portion
is unhappily so small
that it will
in all likelihood undo
the effects
of your loveliness and
amiable qualifications.
As I must
therefore conclude
that you are not serious
in your rejection of me.
I shall choose
to attribute it
to your wish
of increasing
my love by suspense,
according to the
usual practice
of elegant females.
I do assure you
that I have
no pretensions.
Whatsoever
to that kind of.
Elegance which consists
in tormenting
a respectable man.
I would rather be paid
the compliment
of being believed
sincere.
I thank you
again and again
for the honor
you have done me
in your proposals.
But To accept them
is absolutely
impossible.
My feelings
in every respect
forbid it.
Can I speak plainer?
Do not consider.
Me now
as an elegant
female intending.
To plague you,
but as a rational
creature, speaking the
truth from her heart.
Your uniformly charming.
Cried hair
with an air of awkward
gallantry.
And I am persuaded
that when sanctioned
by the express
authority
of both your excellent
parents,
my proposals
will not fail
of being acceptable.
To such.
Poor severance
and willful
self-deception.
Elizabeth would
make no reply.
And immediately.
And in silence,
withdrew.
Determined.
If he persisted
in considering
her repeated refusals
as flattering
encouragement
to apply to her father,
whose negative mind
might be uttered
in such a manner
as to be decisive
and whose behavior
at least.
Could not be mistaken.
For the affectation
and Cocodrie
of an elegant female.
Chapter 20.
Mr.
Collins was
not left long
to the
silent contemplation
of his successful love
for Mrs.
Bennett having dawdled
about in the vestibule.
Watch
for the end of
the conference.
No sooner saw Elizabeth
open the door
and with quick
step, pass
her toward
the staircase.
Then she entered
the breakfast room.
And.
Congratulated both him
and herself
in warm terms
on the happy prospect
of their
near connection.
Mr.
Collins received
and returned
these felicitations
with equal pleasure.
And then.
Proceeded to relate
the particulars
of their interview
with the result
of which he trusted.
He had every reason
to be satisfied
since the refusal which
his cousin
had steadfastly
given him
would naturally flow
from her bashful
and the genuine delicacy
of her character.
This information,
however, startled Mrs.
Bennett.
She would have been glad
to be equally satisfied
that her daughter
had meant to
him by protesting
against his proposals.
But she dared
not believe.
It and could not help
saying so,
but to depend upon it.
Mr.
Collins, she
that Lizzie shall
be brought to reason.
I will speak
to her about it
directly.
She is a very
headstrong, foolish girl
and does
not know
her own interest.
But I make her know it.
Pardon me for
interrupting you, madam.
Cried Mr.
Collins.
But if she is
really headstrong
and foolish, I know
not whether
she would
altogether be
a very desirable wife
to a man in my situation
who naturally looks
for happiness
in the marriage state.
If therefore,
she actually persists in
rejecting my suit,
perhaps were better
not to force her
into accepting me,
because if liable
to such defects
of temper,
she could not contribute
much to my felicity.
Sir, you quite
misunderstand me.
Said Mrs.
Bennett, alarmed.
Lizzie is
only headstrong
in such matters
as these.
In everything else,
she is as good natured
a girl ever lived.
I will go directly
to Mr.
Bennett,
and we shall very soon
settle it with her.
I am sure she would.
Not give him time
to reply, but hurrying
instantly to her husband
called out
as she entered
the library.
Oh, Mr.
Bennett,
you are
wanted immediately.
We are all in an uproar.
You must come
and make Lizzie Mr.
Collins, for she
she will not have him.
And if you do not make
haste,
he will change his mind
and not have her.
Mr.
Bennett raised his eyes
from his book
as she entered and fixed
them on her
face with a calm
which was not in the
least altered
by her communication.
I have not
the pleasure
of understanding.
You, said he.
When she had
finished her speech.
Of What are you talking.
Of? Mr.
Collins and Lizzie?
Lizzie declares
that she will
not have Mr. Collins.
And Mr.
Collins begins to say
that he would
not have Lizzie.
And what am I to do
on the occasion?
It seems a
hopeless business.
Speak to Lizzie about it
yourself.
Tell her that you insist
upon her marrying him.
Let her be called down.
She shall hear
my opinion.
Mrs.
Bennett rang
the bell
and Miss Elizabeth
was summoned
to the library.
Come here, child.
Cried her father
as she appeared.
I have sent you on
an affair of importance.
I understand that Mr.
Collins has made
you an offer
of marriage.
Is it true?
Elizabeth
replied that it was
Very well.
And this offer
of marriage.
You have refused.
I have, sir.
Very well.
We now come
to the point.
Your mother
insists upon
your accepting it.
Is it not, sir?
Mrs. Bennett?
Yes.
Or I will
never see her again.
An unhappy alternative
is before
you, Elizabeth.
From This day
you must be a stranger
to one of your parents.
Your mother
will never see you again
if you do not marry Mr.
Collins.
And I will never see
you again.
If you do.
Elizabeth could not
but smile
at such a conclusion
of such a beginning.
But Mrs..
Bennett,
who had
persuaded herself
that her
husband regarded
the affair
as she wished.
Was excessively
disappointed.
What do you mean?
Mr.
Bennett, in talking
this way.
You promised me
to insist upon her
marrying him.
My dear.
Replied her husband.
I two small favors
to request.
First,
that you will allow me
the free use
of my understanding
on the present occasion,
and secondly of my room.
I shall be
glad to have the
library to myself
as soon as may be.
Not yet.
However,
in spite
of her disappointment
in her husband.
Did Mrs.
Bennett
give up the point?
She talks to Elizabeth
again and again,
coaxed
and threatened her
by turns.
She endeavored to secure
Jane in her interest.
But Jane,
with all possible
mildness,
declined interfering.
And Elizabeth,
sometimes with
real earnestness
and sometimes
with playful gaiety,
replied to her attacks,
though her manner
varied, however, her
determination never did.
Mr.
Collins, meanwhile, was
meditating in solitude
on what had passed.
He thought too
well of himself
to comprehend.
On what motives
his cousin
could refuse him.
And though
his pride was hurt.
He suffered in
no other way.
His regard for her
was quite imaginary,
and the possibility
of her
deserving her
mother's reproach
prevented his feeling.
Any regret.
While the family
were in this confusion,
Charlotte Lucas came
to spend the day
with them.
She was met
in the vestibule
by Lydia,
who flying to her,
cried in a half whisper.
I glad you will come,
for there is such
fun here.
What do you think
has happened
this morning?
Mr.
Collins
has made an offer
to Lizzie
and she will not
have him.
Charlotte hardly
had time to answer
before they were joined
by Kitty,
who came to
tell the same news.
And no sooner had
they entered
the breakfast room
where Mrs.
Bennett was alone.
Then she likewise
began on the subject,
calling on Miss Lucas
for her compassion
and entreating her
to persuade
her friend
Lizzie to comply
with the wishes of all
her family.
Prayed.
Do my damnedest,
Lucas, she.
Added in a melancholy.
Tone.
But nobody is on
my side.
Nobody takes part
with me.
I am cruelly used.
Nobody feels for my poor
nerves.
Charlotte's reply
was spared
by the entrance of Jane
and Elizabeth I.
There she comes.
Continue, Mrs.
Bennett.
Looking as unconcerned
it may be, and caring
no more for us than
if we were
at York, provided
she can have her own way.
But I tell
you, Miss Lizzie,
if you take it
into your head to go on
refusing
every offer of marriage
in this way,
you will never
get a husband at all.
And I am sure
I do not know
who is to maintain
you and
your father is dead.
I Shall not be able to
keep you.
And so I warn you,
I have done with you
from this very day.
I told you
in the library
you know that
I should never
speak to you again.
And you will find me
as good as my word.
I have no pleasure
in talking
to other
dutiful children.
Not that I have
much pleasure.
Indeed, in
talking to anybody.
People who suffer
as I do
from nervous complaints
and have no great
inclination talking.
Nobody can tell
which I suffer, but
it is always so.
Those
who did not complain
and ever pitied.
Her daughters
listened in silence
to this effusion.
Sensible.
Any attempts
to reason with her
or soothe
her would only increase
the irritation.
She talked on.
There for
without interruption
from any of them
till they were joined
by Mr.
Collins,
who entered the room
with an more stately
than usual,
and on perceiving whom
she sent to the girls.
Now, I do insist
upon it that you,
all of you,
hold your tongues
and let me and Mr.
Collins
have a little
conversation together.
Elizabeth passed
quietly out of the room,
Jane and
Kitty following.
But Lydia stood
her ground,
determined to hear
all she.
Could and.
Charlotte detained
first
by the civility of Mr.
Collins.
Whose.
Inquiries after herself
and all her
family were very minute,
and then,
by a little curiosity,
satisfied
with walking
to the window
and pretending
not to hear.
In a doleful voice, Mrs.
Bennett began
the projected
conversation.
Oh, Mr.
Collins.
My dear Madam.
Replied.
He let us be forever
silent on this point.
Far be it from me.
He presently continued
in a voice
that marked
his displeasure.
To resent the behavior
of your daughter.
Resignation
to inevitable
evils is the
duty of us all
the peculiar
duty of a young
man who has been
so fortunate
as I have been
in early preferment,
and I trust
I am resigned.
Perhaps not the less
so from feeling
a doubt of my positive
happiness.
Had my fair
cousin honored me
with her hand.
For
I have often observed
that resignation
is never so perfect
as when the blessing
denied begins
to lose somewhat
of its value.
In our estimation.
You will not,
I hope, consider me
as showing
any disrespect
to your family,
my dear Madam,
by thus withdrawing
my pretensions
to your daughter's favor
without having
paid yourself and Mr.
Bennett
to the compliment
of requesting you
to interpose
your authority
in my behalf.
My conduct,
may I fear,
be objectionable
in having accepted
my decision
from your
daughter's lips
instead of your own.
But we are all
liable to error.
I have certainly meant
well through the
whole affair.
My object has
been to secure
an amiable
companion myself
with due consideration
for the advantage
of all your family.
And if my manner
has been
at all reprehensible,
I hear,
beg leave to apologize.
Chapter 21.
The discussion of Mr.
Collins's offer was now
nearly at an end,
and Elizabeth had only
to suffer
from the uncomfortable
feeling unnecessarily
attending it
and occasionally
from some peevish
allusions of her mother.
As for the gentleman
himself,
his feelings were
chiefly expressed
not embarrassment
or dejection, or
by trying to avoid her,
but by stiffness
of manner
and resentful silence.
He scarcely ever spoke
to her and assiduous
attentions
which she had been
so sensible of himself,
were transferred
for the rest of the day
to Miss Lucas,
whose civility
and listening to him
was a seasonable relief
to all, and especially
to her friend.
The morrow produced
no abatement of Mrs.
Bennett's ill humor
or ill health.
Mr.
Collins was also
in the
same state of
angry pride.
Elizabeth had hoped
that his resentment
might shorten his visit,
but his plan
did not appear
in the least
affected by it.
He was always to
gone on Saturday
and to Saturday.
He meant to stay.
After breakfast,
the girls walked
to Maritain to inquire
if Mr.
Wickham were returned
and to lament
over his absence
from the
Netherfield Ball.
He joined them on
their entering the town
and attended them
to their aunt's,
where his regret
and vexation
and the concern of
everybody was well
talked over
to Elizabeth.
However, he
voluntarily acknowledged
that the
necessity of his absence
had been self-imposed.
I found that he.
As the time Junior,
that I.
I'd better not meet Mr.
Darcy, that to.
Be in the.
Same room, the same.
Party with him
so many hours together.
Might be more
I could bear.
And that scenes
might arise unpleasant
to more than myself.
She highly
approved his forbearance
and they had leisure for
a full discussion of it
and for all
the commendation
which they
civilly bestowed
on each other as Wickham
and another officer
walked back with them
to Long Borne.
And during the walk
he particularly
attended to her
his accompanying them
with the
double advantage.
She felt
all the compliment
it offered to herself,
and it was
most acceptable
as an occasion
of introducing him
to her father
and mother.
Soon after their return,
a letter was delivered
to Mr. Bennett.
It came
from Netherfield.
The envelope contained
a sheet of elegant
little hot
pressed paper.
Well, with a lady's
fair flowing hand.
And Elizabeth saw her
sister's
countenance change
as she read it
and saw her dwelling
intently
on some particular
passages.
Jane recollected
herself soon.
And putting
the letter away,
tried to join
with her
usual cheerfulness
and the
general conversation.
But Elizabeth felt
an anxiety
on the subject
which drew off
her attention,
even from Wickham.
And no sooner had
he and his companion
taken leave
than a glance from Jane
invited her
to follow her upstairs.
When they had
gained their own.
Room.
Jane,
taking out the letter,
said,
This is from
Caroline Bingley.
What it contains
has surprised me
a good deal.
The whole party have.
Left Netherfield
by this time
and are on their way to.
Town
and without
any intention
of coming back again.
You shall hear
what she says.
She then read the
first sentence aloud.
Which comprised.
The information
of their having
just resolved
to follow their brother
to town directly
and of their
meaning to dine in
Grosvenor Street,
where Mr.
Hurst had a house.
The next was
in these words.
I do not pretend
to regret anything.
I shall
leave in Hertfordshire
except your society,
my dearest friend.
But we will hope
at some future period
to enjoy many returns
of that
delightful intercourse
we have known.
And in the.
Meanwhile,
I may lessen
the pain of separation.
By a very frequent
and most unreserved
correspondence.
I depend on you
for that.
To these high flown
expressions.
Elizabeth listened
with all
the insensibility
of distrust, and though
the suddenness
of their removal
surprised her.
She saw.
Nothing in
it really to lament.
It was not to be.
Suppose that
their absence
from Netherfield
would prevent Mr.
Bingley being there,
had asked
for the loss
of their society.
She was persuaded
that Jane must cease
to regard it
in the enjoyment of his.
It is unlucky, said.
She, after
a short pause.
That you should not
be able
to see your friends
before they leave
the country,
but maybe not hope.
That the period
of future.
Happiness to which Mr.
Bingley looks forward
may arrive
than she is aware.
And that the delightful.
Intercourse
you have known
as friends
will be renewed
with yet
greater satisfaction
as sisters.
Mr.
Bingley will
not be detained
in London them.
Caroline
decidedly says
that none of the.
Party will return
into Hertfordshire
this winter.
I will read it to you.
When my brother
left us yesterday.
He imagined that
the business
which took him to London
might be
concluded in three
or four days.
But as we are certain,
it cannot be so.
And at.
The same time
convinced that. When.
Charles gets.
To town,
he will be in
no hurry
to leave it again.
We have determined
on following him thither
that he may not.
Be obliged
to spend
his vacant hours.
In a comfort.
This hotel.
Many of my acquaintances
are already there
for the winter.
I wish that I could
hear that you,
my dearest friend,
had any intention
of making
one of the crowd.
But of that I despair.
I sincerely hope
your Christmas
in Hertfordshire
may abound in the cities
which that season
generally brings,
and that your bows
will be so numerous
as to prevent
your fitting.
The loss of the.
Three.
Whom we shall.
Deprive you.
It is
evident by this
added Jane,
that he comes back
no more this winter.
It is only evident
Miss Bingley.
Does not mean
that he should.
Why would you think so?
It must be
his own doing.
He is his own master.
But you do not know all.
I will read you
the passage,
which particularly
hurts me.
I will have no reserves
from you.
Mr.
Darcy is impatient
to see his sister
and to confess
the truth.
We are scarcely less
eager to meet her again.
I really do not think
Georgiana Darcy
has her equal
for beauty, elegance
and accomplished sense.
And the affection she.
Inspires in Louisa
and myself.
Is heightened
into something
still more interesting
from the hope
we dare entertain of her
being here after Alice.
I do not
know whether I
ever before
mentioned to you
my feelings
on this subject, but
I will not
leave the country
without confiding them,
and I trust
you will not.
Esteem them.
Unreason all.
My brother admires
her greatly already.
He will have frequent
opportunity
now of seeing her
on the most
intimate footing.
Her relations
all wish the connection
as much as his
and a sister's
partiality
is not misleading me,
I think.
When I call Charles
most capable of engaging
any woman's heart
with all
these circumstances
to favor an attachment
and nothing
to prevent it.
Am I wrong?
My dearest Jane,
in indulging the hope of
an event
which
to secure
the happiness
of so many.
What do you think
of this sentence,
my dear?
Lizzie said to Jane
as she finished it.
Is it not clear enough?
Does it not expressly.
Declare that
Caroline
neither expects,
wishes me
to be her sister.
But she is
perfectly convinced
of her
brother's indifference,
and that if she suspects
the nature
of my feelings for him,
she means most kindly
to put me on my God.
Can there be
any other opinion
on the subject?
He has that can
for mine
is totally different.
Will you hear it
most willingly?
You have it
in a few words.
Miss Bingley.
Sees that
her brother is in
love with you and.
Wants him to marry
Miss Darcy.
She follows him to town
in hope
of keeping him there
and tries
to persuade you
that he does not
care about you.
Jane shook her head.
Indeed, Jane.
You ought to believe me.
No one who has ever seen
you together
can doubt his affection.
Miss being the
I am sure cannot.
She is not
such a simpleton.
Could she have seen
half as.
Much love in Mr.
Darcy for herself?
She would have
ordered her
wedding clothes.
But the case is this.
We are not rich enough
or grand
enough for them.
And she is
the more anxious to.
Get Miss.
Darcy for her brother.
From the notion
that when there has been
one into marriage,
she may have less.
Trouble in
achieving a second.
In which there is
certainly
some ingenuity.
And I dare
say it would succeed
if Mr.
Burke were
out of the way.
But my dearest Jane,
you cannot
seriously imagine.
That because Miss
Bailey tells
you her brother
greatly admires Ms..
Darcy.
He is in the
smallest degree, less
sensible of
your marriage
than when he took
leave you on Tuesday,
or that it would be
in her power
to persuade him that
instead of
being in love with you,
he is very much in
love with a friend.
If we thought alike.
Of Miss, replied Jane,
your representation
of all
this might make
me quite easy.
But I know
the foundation
is unjust.
Caroline is incapable
of willfully
deceiving anyone.
And all that
I can hope in this case.
Is that she is deceiving
herself.
That is.
Right.
You could not
have started
a more happy idea
since you will not
comfort in mine.
Believe had
to be deceived
by all means.
You have now done
your duty by.
Her and.
Must fret no longer.
But my dear sister,
can I be happy?
Even supposing the best.
In accepting a man
whose sisters
and friends
are all wishing him
to marry elsewhere?
You must decide
for yourself.
Said Elizabeth.
And if.
Upon mature
deliberation, you.
Find that
the misery of disabling
his two sisters is more
than equivalent
to the happiness
of being.
His wife, I advise you,
by all means,
to refuse him.
How can you talk?
So?
Said Jane,
faintly, smiling.
You must know
that, though
I should be
exceedingly grieved
at their disapprobation.
I could not hesitate.
I did not think
you would.
And that.
Being the case.
I cannot consider
your situation
with much compassion.
But if he returns
more this winter,
my choice will
never be required.
A thousand things
may arise in six months.
The idea
of his returning
no more
Elizabeth, treated
with the utmost
contempt,
it appeared to her
merely
the suggestion
of Caroline's
interested wishes.
And she could
not for a moment.
Suppose that
those wishes, however
openly or
artfully spoken,
could influence
a young man so totally
independent of everyone
she represented
to her sister
as forcibly as possible
what she felt
on the subject,
and had soon
the pleasure of seeing
its happy effect.
James temper
was not responding,
and she was
gradually led to hope.
Though the diffidence
of affection
sometimes overcame
the hope that Bingley
would return
to Netherfield
and answer
wish of her heart.
They agreed that Mrs.
Bennett should only hear
of the departure
of the family
without being alarmed
on the score
of the
gentleman's conduct.
But even
this partial
communication
gave her
a great deal of concern.
And she.
Bewildered
as exceedingly unlucky
that the lady
should happen
to go away,
just as they
were all getting
so intimate together.
After lamenting it,
however, at some length,
she had the consolation
that Mr.
Bingley would
soon be down again
and soon
dining at Long Bourn.
And the
conclusion of all was
the comfortable
declaration
that though
he had been invited
only to a family dinner,
she would take care to
have two full courses.
Chapter 22.
The Bennetts were
engaged to dine
with the Lucas's
and again
during the chief of
the day was Miss Lucas,
so kind
as to listen to Mr.
Collins.
Elizabeth took
an opportunity
of thanking her.
It keeps him in good
humor, said she.
And I am.
More obliged to you
than I can express.
Charlotte assured,
her friend
of her satisfaction
in being useful
and that it amply
repaid her
for the little
sacrifice of her time.
This was very amiable.
But Charlotte's kindness
extended farther
than Elizabeth had.
Any conception of.
Its object.
Was nothing else
than to secure her
from any return of Mr.
Collins addresses
by engaging them
towards herself.
Such was Miss Lucas's
scheme, and appearances
were so favorable
that when they
parted at night,
she would have felt
almost secure of success
if he had not been
to leave Hertfordshire
so very soon.
But here she did
injustice to the fire
and independence
of his character, for it
led him to escape
out of Long Bourne house
the next morning
with Admiral
Slyness and.
Hastened.
To Lucas Lodge
to throw himself
at her feet.
He was anxious to avoid
the notice
of his cousins
from a conviction
that if they
saw him depart,
they could not fail
to conjecture
his design and.
He was not.
Willing to have
the attempt
known till its success
might be known.
Likewise,
for the feeling
almost secure
and with reason
for Charlotte
had been
tolerably encouraging.
He was
comparatively diffident
since the adventure
of Wednesday.
His reception, however,
was of the most
flattering kind.
Miss Lucas.
Perceived him
from an upper window
as he walked
towards the house.
And instantly.
Set out to meet him
accidentally
in the lane.
But little had
she dared to hope
that so much love
and eloquence
awaited her there
in as short
a time as Mr.
Collins long
speeches would allow.
Everything was settled
between them
to the
satisfaction of both.
And as they entered
the house,
he earnestly
entreated her
to name the day
that was to make him
the happiest men.
And though
such a solicitation
must be way
for the present,
the lady felt
no inclination to trifle
with his happiness.
The stupidity
with which
he was favored by nature
must guard his courtship
from any charm
that could make a woman
wish for
its continuance.
And Miss Lucas,
who accepted him.
Solely from the pure
and disinterested desire
of an establishment,
cared not how soon
that establishment
were gained.
Sir William and Lady
Lucas were speedily
applied to
for their consent.
And it.
Was bestowed
with the most
joyful alacrity.
Mr.
Present circumstances
made it a most eligible
match
for their daughter,
to whom
they could
give little fortune,
and his prospects
of future wealth
were exceedingly fair.
Lady Lucas began
directly to calculate
with more interest
than the matter
had ever excited before.
How many years
longer Mr.
Bennett was
likely to live.
And Sir William gave it
as his decided opinion
that whenever Mr.
Collins should be
in possession
of the long
bored estate,
it would
be highly expedient
that both
he and his wife
should make
their appearance
at St James's.
The family, in short,
were properly overjoyed
on the occasion.
The younger girls
formed hopes
of coming out a year
or two sooner
than they might
otherwise have done,
and the boys
were relieved
from their apprehension.
Charlotte's dying
and old maid.
Charlotte herself
was tolerably composed.
She had gained her point
and had time to consider
of it.
Her reflections
were, in general,
satisfactory Mr.
Collins, to be
sure, was neither
sensible nor agreeable.
His society was irksome.
And his attachment.
To her
must be imaginary.
But still he would.
Be her husband
without thinking highly
either of men
or matrimony.
Marriage
had always been
her object.
It was
the only provision
for well-educated
young women
of small fortune.
And however,
of giving happiness
must be their pleasant
est preservative
from want.
This preservative
she had now obtained
and at the age of 27,
without having
ever handsome,
she felt all
the good luck of it.
The least agreeable
circumstance in
the business
was the surprise.
It must occasion
to Elizabeth Bennet,
whose friendship
she valued beyond that
of any other person.
Elizabeth would wonder
and probably
would blame her.
And though
her resolution
was not to be shaken,
her feelings
must be hurt
by such
a disapprobation.
She resolved to give her
the information herself
and therefore
charged Mr.
Collins when he returned
to Longboard to dinner
to drop
no hint of
what had passed
before any of
the family.
A promise of
secrecy was, of course,
very dutifully given.
But it could not be kept
without.
Difficulty
for the curiosity,
excited by his long
absence, burst forth
in such
very direct questions
on his return
as required
some ingenuity to evade.
And he was at
the same time exercising
great self-denial,
for he was longing
to publish
his prosperous love
as he was to begin
his journey
too early on the morrow
to see any of
the family.
The ceremony of Leave
taking was performed
when the ladies moved
for the night, and Mrs.
Bennett,
with great politeness
and cordiality, said
how happy they should be
to see him
at long born again
whenever his engagements
might allow him
to visit them.
My dear,
he replied.
This invitation
is particularly
gratifying
because it is what
I have been
hoping to receive,
and you may be
very certain
that I shall avail
myself of it
as soon as possible.
They were
all astonished, and Mr.
Bennett, who could
by no means wish
for so speedy to return,
immediately said.
But is there
not danger of Lady
Katherine's
disapprobation here?
My good sir,
you had better neglect
your relations than run
the risk
of offending
your patroness.
My dear sir.
Replied Mr..
I am particularly
obliged to you for this
friendly caution,
and you may
depend upon my
not taking such material
a step
without Her
Ladyship concurrence.
You cannot be
too much on your guard.
Risk anything
rather than
her displeasure.
And if you find
it likely to be raised
by your coming
to us again,
which I should think
exceedingly probable.
Stay quietly at home
and be satisfied that
we shall take
no offense.
Believe me,
my dear sir, my
gratitude is
warmly excited
by such affectionate
attention and depend
upon it.
You will speedily
receive from me
a letter of
thanks for this, as well
as for every other
mark of your regard
during my stay
in Hertfordshire.
As for my fair cousins,
though,
my absence
may not be long enough
to render it necessary.
I shall now
take the liberty
of wishing them
health and happiness,
not accepting
my cousin Elizabeth.
With proper civilities,
the ladies
then withdrew,
all of them
equally surprised
that he meditated
a quick return.
Mrs.
Bennett wished to.
Understand by it
that he thought
of Peggy's addresses
to one of her
younger girls had
marry,
might have
been prevailed
on to accept him.
She rated his abilities
much higher
than any of the others.
There was a solidity
in his reflections
which often struck her.
And though by no means
as clever as herself,
she thought that
if encouraged
to read and improve
by such
an example as hers,
he might become a very
agreeable companion.
But on the
following morning,
every hope of this kind
was done away.
Miss Lucas called
soon after
and in a
private conference
with Elizabeth,
related the event
of the day before
the possibility of Mr.
Collins
fancying himself in love
with her friend
had once occurred
to Elizabeth
within the last
day or two, but
that Charlotte
could encourage him
seemed almost
as far from possibility
as she could
encourage him herself.
And her astonishment.
Was consequently.
So as to overcome
at the first
the bounds of
decorum, and.
She could not.
Help crying out.
Engaged to Mr.
Collins, My
dear Charlotte.
Impossible.
The steady countenance
which Miss Lucas
had commanded
in telling her story.
Gave way to a momentary.
Confusion here
on receiving
so direct a reproach,
though as it was
no more than expected,
she soon
regained her composure
and calmly replied,
Why should you
be surprised,
my dear Eliza?
Do you think
it incredible.
That Mr.
Collins should be able
to procure.
Any woman's
good opinion?
Because he was not.
So happy
as to succeed with you.
But Elizabeth had
now recollected herself
had making a
strong effort for
it was able to assure
with tolerable firmness
that the prospect
of their relationship
was highly
grateful to her
and that she wished her
all imaginable
happiness.
I see what
you were feeling,
replied Charlotte.
You must be surprised.
Very much surprised.
So lately, as Mr..
Collins was wishing
to marry you.
But when you have had
time to think it over,
I hope you'll
be satisfied
with what I have done.
I am not romantic,
you know.
I never was.
I ask only a
comfortable home.
And considering Mr.
Collins character,
connection
and situation in life.
I am convinced.
That my chance
of happiness
with him is as.
Fair as
most people can boast
on entering.
The marriage state.
Elizabeth
quietly answered.
Undoubtedly.
And after
an awkward pause,
they returned
to the rest
of the family.
Charlotte
did not stay
much longer,
and Elizabeth was
then left to reflect
on what she had heard.
It was a long time
before she became
at all
reconciled to the idea
of so unsuitable
a match.
The strangeness of Mr.
Collins
making two offers
of marriage
within three days
was nothing
in comparison
of his
being now accepted.
She had always.
Felt that
Charlotte's opinion.
Of matrimony was not.
Exactly like her own.
But she had not
supposed it.
To be possible
that when called
into action,
she have sacrificed
every better
feeling to
worldly advantage.
Charlotte,
the wife of Mr.
Collins, was
the most
humiliating picture
and the paying
of a friend.
Disgracing
and sunk in her.
Esteem was added.
The distressing
conviction
that it was impossible
for that friend
to be tolerably
happy and the law
she had chosen.
Chapter 23.
Elizabeth was
sitting with her
mother and sisters,
reflecting on
what she had
heard and doubting
whether she
was authorized
to mention it.
When Sir William
Lucas himself appeared
sent by his daughter
to announce
her engagement
to the family.
With.
Many compliments to them
and much
self-flagellation
and the prospect
of a connection
between the houses,
he unfolded the matter
to an audience
not merely wondering,
but incredulous.
For Mrs.
Bennett,
with more perseverance
than politeness,
protested
he must be
entirely mistaken.
And Lydia, always
unguarded
and often uncivil,
boisterously exclaimed.
Good Lord.
So, William,
how can you tell
such a story?
Do not you know that Mr.
Collins wants to
marry Lizzie?
Nothing less
than the
complacence of
a courtier
could have born
without anger.
Such treatment.
But Sir William's
good breeding
carried him
through at all.
And though he begged
leave to be positive
as to the truth
of his information,
he listened to all
their impertinence
with the most forbearing
courtesy.
Elizabeth
feeling it
incumbent on her
to relieve him
from so unpleasant
a situation.
Now.
Put herself forward
to confirm his account
by mentioning her prior
knowledge of it
from Charlotte herself.
And.
Endeavored to put a stop
to the exclamations
of her mother
and sisters
by the earnestness
of her Congratulations
to Sir William, in which
she was readily
joined by Jane
and by making a variety
of remarks
on the happiness
that might be expected
from the Match.
The excellent character
of Mr.
Collins
and the convenient
distance of HUNTSBERRY
from London.
Mrs.
Bennett was in fact,
too much over
power to say
a great deal
while Sir
William remained.
But no sooner.
Had he left them
than her feelings
found a rapid vent.
In the first place,
she persisted
in disbelieving
the whole of the matter.
Secondly,
she was very sure
that Mr.
Collins
had been taken in.
Thirdly,
she trusted that
they would never be
happy together.
And fourthly,
that the match
might be broken off to.
Inferences,
however, were
plainly deduced
from the whole one
that Elizabeth
was the real cause
of the mischief
and the other
that she herself
had been barbarous,
only misused
by them all.
And on these two.
Points,
she principally dwelt
during the rest
of the day.
Nothing could console
and nothing could
appease her.
Nor did that day
wear out her resentment.
A week elapsed
before
she could see Elizabeth
without her.
A month passed away
before she could speak
to Sir William
or Lady Lucas
without being rude.
And many months
were gone before
she could at all
forgive their daughter.
Mr.
Bennett, emotions
were much more tranquil
on the occasion,
and such as he
did experience,
he pronounced to be
of a most agreeable sort
for it.
Gratified him,
he said,
to discover that
Charlotte Lucas, whom
he had been used
to think
tolerably sensible, was.
As foolish
as his wife and.
More foolish
than his daughter.
Jane confessed herself
a little surprised
at the match.
But she said
of her astonishment
than of her
earnest desire
for their happiness.
Nor can Elizabeth
persuade her
to consider it
as improbable.
Kitty and Lydia
were far from envying
Miss Lucas.
For Mr.
Collins,
only a clergyman.
And it affected them in
no other way
than as a piece of
news to spread
at Meriton.
Lady Lucas could
not be insensible.
Of triumph
on being able
to retort on Mrs.
Bennett
the comfort of
having a daughter
while married,
and she called it
long born
rather oftener
than usual.
To say
how happy she was.
Though Mrs.
Bennett's.
Sour looks
and ill natured remarks
have been enough
to drive happiness away
between Elizabeth
and Charlotte,
there was restraint
which kept them
mutually silent
on the subject.
And Elizabeth felt
persuaded that no real
confidence
could ever subsist
between them again.
Her disappointment
in Charlotte
made her turn
with fonder
regard to her sister,
of whose rectitude
and delicacy
she was sure
opinion could
never be shaken
and for whose happiness
she carried
daily more anxious
as Bingley
had now been gone a week
and nothing
more was heard
of his return.
Jane had Caroline
an early
answer to her letter
and was counting
the days
till she might
reasonably hope
to hear again.
The promised letter of
Thanks for.
Mr.
Collins
arrived on Tuesday,
addressed to
their father and written
with all the
solemnity of gratitude
which a 12 months
abode in the family
might have prompted.
After discharging
his conscience
on that head,
he proceeded
to inform them with many
rapturous expressions
of his happiness
and having obtained
the affection
of their amiable
neighbor, Ms..
Lucas,
and then explained that
it was merely
with a view
of enjoying her society,
that he had been
so ready to close
with their kind wish
of seeing him again
at long born.
Whether he hoped.
To be able
to return
on Monday fortnight.
For Lady Catherine,
he added,
so heartily approved
his marriage
that she wished it
to take place
as soon as possible.
Which.
He trusted
would be
an unanswerable argument
with his amiable
Charlotte,
to name an early day
for making him
the happiest of men.
Mr.
Collins returned
to Hertfordshire,
was no longer
a matter of pleasure
to Mrs. Bennett.
On the contrary,
she was as much disposed
to complain of it
as her husband.
It was.
Very strange
that he should come
too long born
instead of the Lucas.
Lodge.
It was also
very inconvenient
and exceedingly
troublesome.
She hated having
visitors in the house
while her health
was so indifferent.
Had lovers
were of all people
the most disagreeable.
Such were the gentle
murmurs of Mrs.
Bennett,
and they gave way
only to the greater
distress of Mr.
Bingley
his continued absence.
Neither Jane
nor Elizabeth
were comfortable
on this subject.
Day after day
passed away
without bringing
any other
tidings of him.
Then the report,
which shortly
prevailed
and merited
of his coming
no more to Netherfield
the whole winter.
A report
which highly
incensed Mrs.
Bennett.
And which.
She never failed
to contradict
as the most scandalous.
Falsehood.
Even Elizabeth
began to fear not
that Bingley
was indifferent,
but that his sisters
would be successful
in keeping him away.
Unwilling as she was
to admit, an idea
so destructive
of Jane's happiness
and so dishonorable
to the
stability of her lover,
she could not
prevent its
frequently occurring.
The united efforts
of his two
unfeeling sisters
and of his overpowering
friend, assisted
by the attractions
of Miss Dorothy
and the
amusements of London.
Might be too much.
She feared
for the strength
of his attachment.
As for Jane, her
under the suspense was,
of course,
more painful
than Elizabeth's.
But whatever she felt
she was
desirous of concealing.
And between Elizabeth
and herself, therefore,
the subject was
never alluded to.
But as no.
Such delicacy
restrained her mother
and our seldom past
in which she did
not talk of Bingley
expressed her impatience
for his arrival
or even required
to confess that
if he did not come back,
she would
think herself very ill.
Used.
It needed all
Jane's steady mildness
to bear
these attacks with
tolerable tranquility.
Mr.
Collins returned
most punctually
on Monday fortnight,
but his reception
at Long
Bond was not quite
so gracious as it had
been on his
first introduction.
He was too happy
to need much attention,
and luckily
for the others,
the business
of lovemaking
relieved them
from a great
deal of his company.
The chief of.
Every day
was spent by him
at Lucas Lodge.
And he sometimes.
Returned to Long Borne
only in time
to make an apology
for his absence
before the family
went to bed.
Mrs.
Bennett was really
in a most
pitiable state.
The very mention
of anything
concerning the match
threw her into an
agony of ill humor,
and wherever she went,
she was sure
of hearing it.
Talked of.
The sight of Miss Lucas
was odious.
To her as her successor.
That house.
She regarded her
with jealous abhorrence
whenever Charlotte
came to see them.
She concluded her
to be anticipating
the hour of possession,
and whenever
she spoke
in a loud voice to Mr.
Collins.
Was convinced.
That they were talking
of the long born estate
and resolving
to turn herself
and her daughters
out of the house
as soon as Mr.
Bennett were dead.
She complained bitterly
of all this
to her husband.
Indeed, Mr.
Bennett said she.
It is very hard
to think that
Charlotte Lucas.
Should ever
be mistress of.
This house
and that I
should be forced
to make way for her
and live to see her
take a place in it.
My dear,
do not give way to such
gloomy thoughts.
That is hope
for better things.
Let us
flatter ourselves that
may be the survivor.
This was
not very
consoling to Mrs.
Bennett, and therefore,
instead of making
any answer, she went on
as before.
I cannot bear to think
that they should
have all this estate.
If it was not
for the entail,
I should not mind it.
What should not you
mind?
I should not mind
anything at all.
Let us be thankful
that you are preserved
from a
state of
such insensibility.
I can never be
thankful, Mr. Bennett.
For anything
about the entail.
How anyone should have
the conscience
to entail away
in a state
from one's
own daughters.
I can not understand.
And all
for the sake of Mr.
Collins do.
Why should he have it
more than anybody else?
I leave it to yourself
to determine.
Said Mr.
Bennett.
Chapter 24.
Miss Bingley
letter arrived
and put an end to doubt.
The very first sentence
conveyed the assurance
of their
being all
settled in London
for the winter
and concluded
with her
brother's regret
at not having had time
to pay
his respects
to his friends
in Hertfordshire
before he left
the country.
Hope was over,
entirely over,
and when Jane
could attend
to the rest
of the letter,
she found little
except the professed
affection of the writer
that could give her
any comfort.
Miss Darcy's
praise occupied
the chief of it.
Her many attractions
were again dwelt on,
and Caroline boasted
joyfully of their
increasing intimacy
and venture to predict
the accomplishment
of the wishes
which had been unfolded
in her former letter.
She wrote also
with great pleasure
of her brother's
being an intimate of Mr.
Darcy's house
and mentioned
with raptures
some plans of the latter
with regard to
new furniture.
Elizabeth to whom Jane
very soon communicated.
The chief of all this
heard it in silent
indignation.
Her heart was divided
between, concern
for her sister
and resentment
against all others
to Caroline's
assertion of
her brothers
being partial
to Miss Darcy.
She paid no credit that.
He was
really fond of Jane.
She doubted
no more than she had
ever done,
and much as she had
always been
disposed to like him.
She could not.
Think without anger,
hardly without on that
easiness of temper,
that want of
proper resolution,
which now made him
the slave
of his designing friends
and led him to sacrifice
of his own
happiness to the caprice
of their inclination,
had his own happiness.
However,
being the only sacrifice
he might have been
allowed to sport
with it in
whatever manner
he thought best.
But Sisters
was involved in it
as she thought.
He must be
sensible himself.
It was a subject,
in short,
on which reflection
would be long indulged
and must be unavailing.
She could think of
nothing else.
And yet
whether Bailey's regard
had really died away
or were suppressed
by his
friend's interference.
Whether he
had been aware
of Jane's attachment
or, whether
it had escaped
his observation.
Whatever were the case,
though, her
opinion of him
must be
materially affected
by the difference.
Her sister's situation
remained the same.
Her Peace equally.
Wounded.
A day or two
passed before
Jane had courage
to speak of her feelings
to Elizabeth.
But at last on, Mrs.
Bennett's
leaving them together
after a
longer irritation
than usual
about Netherfield
and its master,
she could not
help saying.
Oh, that, my dear
mother,
had no
command of herself.
She have no idea
of the pain
she gives me by her
continual reflections
on him.
But I will not
draw pine.
It cannot last long.
He will be forgot.
And we be as
we were before.
Elizabeth
looked at her sister
with incredulous
solicitude,
but said nothing.
You doubt me?
Cried Jane, slightly.
Indeed,
you have no reason.
He may live in my memory
as the most.
Amiable man
of my acquaintance.
But that is all.
I have nothing either
to hope or fear
and nothing
to reproach him with.
Thank God
I have not that pain.
A little time.
Therefore, I shall.
Certainly try
to get to the better
with a stronger voice,
she soon added.
I have this
comfort immediately
that it has
not been more
than an error of fancy
on my side,
and that has done
no harm to anyone
but myself.
My dear Jane!
Exclaimed Elizabeth.
You are too good.
Your sweetness
and disinterest
are really angelic.
I do not know what
to say to you.
I feel as.
If I had.
Never done you justice
or loved you
as you deserve.
Miss Bennet
eagerly disclaimed
all extraordinary merit
and threw back
the praise on her
sister's warm affection.
Nay, said Elizabeth.
This is not fair.
You wish to.
Think all
the world respectable.
And are hurt by
speak ill of anybody.
I only want to
think you perfect
and you
set yourself against it.
Do not be afraid
of my running.
Into any excess of.
My encroaching
on your privilege
of universal goodwill.
You need not.
There are few people
whom I really love
and still few of whom
I think.
The more
I see of the world,
the more am I.
Dissatisfied with it.
And every day confirms
my belief
of the inconsistency
of all human characters
and of the
little dependance
that can be placed
on the appearance
of merit or sense.
I have met
with two instances
lately.
One I will not mention.
The other is
Charlotte's marriage.
It is unaccountable.
In every view, it is
unaccountable.
My dear Lizzie,
do not give way to such.
Feelings as.
These.
They will ruin your.
You do
not make
allowance enough
for difference
of situation and temper.
Consider Mr.
Collins respectability
and Charlotte's steady,
prudent character.
Remember that
she is one of a.
Large family
that asked to fortune.
It is a most
eligible match.
And to be ready to
believe everybody's sake
that she may
feel something, regard
and esteem
for our cousin.
To oblige you.
I would try to believe
almost anything,
but no one else could
be benefited by.
Such a belief.
Is this for her?
I persuaded
that Charlotte
had any real
regard for him.
I should only
think worse
of her understanding
than I now
do of her heart.
My dear Jane, Mr.
Collins is a conceited,
narrow minded,
silly man.
You know he is
as well as I do.
And you must feel as.
Well as I do that the.
Woman who married him
cannot have a proper
way of thinking.
He shall not defend
her, though.
It is Charlotte Lucas.
You shall not,
for the
sake of one individual,
change
the meaning of
principle and integrity,
nor endeavor
to persuade yourself me
that selfishness,
prudence
and insensibility
of danger.
Security for happiness.
I must
think your language
too strong.
And speaking of both,
replied Jane.
And I hope you will
be convinced of it
by seeing them
happy together.
But enough of this.
You alluded to
something else.
You mentioned
two instances.
I cannot
misunderstand you,
but I.
And treat
you, dear Lizzie,
not to pain me
by thinking
that person to blame
and saying your opinion
of him is sunk.
We must not be so ready
to fancy ourselves
intentionally injured.
We must not expect.
A lively young man
to be always so.
Guarded and circumspect.
It is very often
nothing but our own.
Vanity that deceives.
Women
fancy admiration means
more than it does.
And men
take care
that they should.
If it is decidedly done,
they cannot
be justified.
But I have no idea.
Of there
being so much design
in the world as some.
Persons imagine.
I am far from.
Attributing
any part of Mr.
Bigley's conduct
to design,
said Elizabeth.
But without scheming
to do wrong
or to
make others unhappy,
there may be error
and there may be misery.
Thoughtlessness.
I want to pay attention
to other
people's feelings and.
Want a resolution?
Will do the business.
And do
you impute it to
either of those?
Yes, to the last.
But if I go on,
I shall displease
you by saying what
I think of persons
you esteem.
Stop me whilst
you can.
You persist that
in supposing his sisters
influence him?
Yes.
In conjunction
with his friend.
I cannot believe it.
Why should they try
to influence him?
They can only wish
his happiness.
And if he is
attached to me,
no other woman
can secure.
Your first
position is false.
They may wish
many things
besides his happiness.
They may wish
his increase of.
Wealth and consequence.
They may wish him
to marry a girl
who has the.
Importance of money,
great connections
and pride.
Beyond doubt,
they do
wish him to choose,
Miss Darcy,
replied Jane.
But this may be
from better feelings
than you are supposing.
They have known
her much longer
than they have known me.
Now wonder
if they love her better
about whatever may
be their own wishes.
It is very unlikely
that they should
have opposed
their brothers.
What sister
would think herself
at liberty to do it
unless there
was something
very objectionable.
If they believed him
attached to me,
they would not
try to part us.
If he worsened,
they could not succeed.
I suppose in
such an affection.
You make
everybody acting
unnaturally and wrong
and me most unhappy
do not distress me
by the idea.
I am not ashamed of.
Having been mistaken.
Or at least it is light.
It is nothing
in comparison
of what I should be
thinking ill of him
or his sisters.
Let me take it
in the best in the light
in which it may
be understood.
Elizabeth could not
oppose such a wish.
And from this time, Mr..
Begley's name
was scarcely
ever mentioned
between them.
Mrs.
Bennett
still continued
to wonder, and we pine
at his returning
no more.
And though a day
seldom passed
in which Elizabeth
did not account for it.
Clearly
there was little chance
her ever considering it
with less perplexity.
Her daughter endeavored
to convince her of what
she did
not believe herself
that his attentions
to Jane
had been merely
the effect of a common
and transient liking.
Which ceased.
When he saw her no more.
But though
the probability
of the statement
was admitted
at the time,
she had the same story
to repeat every day.
Mrs.
Bennett's best comfort
was that Mr.
Bingley
must be down again
in the summer.
Mr.
Bennett treated
the matter differently.
So Lizzie.
Said he, one day.
Your sister is crossed
in love.
I find.
I congratulate her
next to being married.
A girl
likes to be crossed in
love a little now
and then.
It is something
to think of
and gives her
a sort of distinction
among her companions.
When is your turn
to come?
You will hardly bear
to be
long outdone by Jane.
Now Is
your time
here?
Are officers
enough at Meriden
to disappoint
all the young ladies
in the country?
Let Wickham be your man.
He's a pleasant fellow
and would
jilt creditably.
Thank you, sir.
But a less.
Agreeable man
would satisfy me.
We must not all expect
Jane's good fortune.
True, said Mr.
Bennett.
But it is a comfort
to think that whatever
of that kind
may befall you.
You have an affectionate
mother
who will always
make the most of it.
Mr.
Wickham,
Society was
of material service
in dispelling the gloom,
which the late
perverse occurrences
had thrown on
many of the long
born family.
They saw him often
and to.
His other
recommendations was now
added that of General
unreserved.
The whole of.
What Elizabeth
had already heard
his claims on Mr.
D'Arcy and all that
he had suffered from him
was now
openly acknowledged
and publicly canvased
and everybody
was pleased
to know
how much they had
always disliked Mr.
D'Arcy before they had
known anything
of the matter.
Miss Spanish was the
only creature
who could suppose there
might be any extenuating
circumstances
in the case, unknown
to the Society
of Hertfordshire.
Her mild and steady
candor always pleaded
for allowances and urged
the possibility
of mistakes.
But by everybody
else, Mr.
Darcy was condemned
as the worst of men.
Chapter 25.
After a week
spent in professions
of love
and schemes
of Felicity, Mr.
Collins was called
from his amiable
Charlotte
by the arrival Saturday.
The pain of separation,
however, might
be alleviated
on his side
by preparations
for the reception
of his bride,
as he had reason
to hope that shortly
after his return
into Hertfordshire
the day would be fixed.
That was to make him
the happiest of men.
He took leave
of his relations
at long, borne
with as much solemnity
as before,
wished his fair
cousin's health
and happiness,
and promised
their father
another letter
of thanks.
On the following
Monday, Mrs.
Bennett had the pleasure
of receiving her brother
and his wife,
who came, as usual,
to spend the Christmas
at Long Bourn.
Mr.
Gardner was a sensible
gentleman like man,
greatly superior
to his sister,
as well by nature
as education.
The Netherfield ladies
would have
had difficulty
in believing
that a man
who lived by trade
and within view
of his own warehouses
could have been
so well-bred
and agreeable.
Mrs.
Gardner
was several years
younger than Mrs.
Bennett, and Mrs.
Phillips was an amiable,
intelligent,
elegant woman
and a great favorite
with all her
long born nieces.
Between the.
Two eldest and herself
especially,
there subsisted
a particular regard.
They had frequently been
staying with her
in town.
The first part of Mrs.
Gardner's
business on her arrival
was to distribute
her presents
and describe
the newest fashions.
When this was done,
she had a less
active part to play.
It became her
turn to listen.
Mrs.
Bennett
had many grievances
to relate
and much to complain of.
They had all been
very ill used
since she last
saw her sister.
Two of her girls
had been upon
the point of marriage,
and after all,
there was nothing in it.
No, I do not blame Jane,
she continued,
for Jane
would have got to Mr.
Bingley if she could.
But, Lizzie.
Oh, sister,
it is hard
to think
she might have been Mr.
Collins wife
by this time had it
not been for her own
perverse niece.
He made her an offer
in this very room,
and she refused.
The consequence of it
is, is that Lady
Lucas will
have a daughter
married before I have,
and that the long
born estate is
just as much
entailed as ever.
The Lucas is very artful
people indeed, sister.
They are all for
what they can get.
I am sorry to say it
to them, but.
So it is.
It makes me very nervous
and poorly
to be thwarted.
So my own family
and to have neighbors
who think of themselves
before anybody else.
However, your coming
just at this time
is the
greatest of comforts,
and I am very glad
to hear
what you tell us
of Sleeves.
Mrs.
Gardiner,
to whom
the chief of this news
had been given
before
in the course of Jane
and Elizabeth's
correspondence with her
made her sister a slight
and in compassion
to her.
Nieces,
turned the conversation
when.
Alone with Elizabeth.
Afterwards,
she spoke more
on the subject.
It seems likely
to have been
a desirable match
for Jane, said she.
I am sorry it went off,
but these things happen
so often.
A young man
such as you
describe, Mr.
Bingley.
So easily.
Falls in love
with a pretty girl
for a few. Weeks.
And when accident
separates them,
so easily forgets
that these
sort of inconsistencies
are very frequent,
an excellent
consolation in its way,
said Elizabeth.
But it will
not do for us.
We do not
suffer by accident.
It does not often happen
that the interference
of friends
persuade a young man
of independent fortune
to think no
more of a girl
he was violently in love
with only a
few days before.
But that expression
of violently in love
is so hackneyed,
so doubtful,
so indefinite
that it gives me
very little idea.
It is as often
applied to feelings
which arise
from a half
hour's acquaintance
as to a real
strong attachment.
How violent was Mr.
Begley's love?
I never saw a more
promising incarnation.
He was growing
quite inattentive.
To other people.
And wholly
engrossed by her.
Every time they met,
it was more decided
and remarkable.
At his own ball,
he offended
two or three
young ladies
by not
asking them to dance.
And I spoke to him.
Twice myself
without receiving an.
Answer.
Could there be finer
symptoms?
Is not
general incivility
the very essence of love?
Oh Yes.
Of that kind of love,
which I suppose him
to have felt for Jane.
I am sorry for her.
Because with
her disposition,
she may not get over it
immediately.
It had better have
happened to you, Lizzie.
You would have
laughed yourself
out of it sooner.
But do you think
she would be prevailed
upon to go back with us?
Change of scene
might be of service.
And perhaps a
little relief from home
may be as useful
as anything.
Elizabeth was
exceedingly pleased
with this proposal
and felt
persuaded of her
sister's
rowdy acquiescence.
I hope, added Mrs.
Gardiner,
that's no consideration.
With regard
to this young man.
Influence her.
We live in so different
to part of town.
All our connections
are so different.
And as you well know,
we go out so.
Little
that it is
very improbable
that they should
meet at all
unless he really comes
to see her.
And that
quite impossible.
But he is now
in the custody
of his friend.
And Mr.
Darcy would no
more suffer him
to call on Jane
in such a part
of London.
My dear aunt,
how you think of it?
Mr. Darcy may.
Perhaps.
Have heard of
such a place
as Grace Church Street,
but he would
hardly think
a month's ablution
enough to cleanse him
from its impurities.
What he wants to
enter it
then depend upon it.
Mr.
Bingley never
stood without him.
So much the better.
I hope
they will not
meet at all.
But does not Jane
correspond with
his sister?
She will not be able
to help calling.
She will drop
the acquaintance
entirely.
But in spite.
Of the certainty
in which Elizabeth
affected
to place this point,
as well
as the still
more interesting,
one of Bingley is
being withheld
from seeing.
Jane.
She felt a solicitude.
On the subject,
which convinced her
on examination.
That she did not.
Consider
entirely hopeless.
It was possible,
and sometimes
she thought it probable
that his affection might
be reanimated
and the influence
of his friends
successfully
by the more
natural influence
of Jane's attractions.
Miss Bennet
accepted her
aunt's invitation
with pleasure,
and the Bengalis
were no otherwise
in her thoughts.
At the same time
then, as she hoped
by Caroline's not living
in the same house
with her brother,
she might occasionally
spend a morning with her
without any danger
of seeing him.
The gardener
stayed a at Long Bourne,
and what with
the Phillips's,
the Lucas's
and the officers.
There was not a day
without its engagement.
Mrs.
Bennet had so
carefully provided
for the entertainment
of her brother sister
that they did not want
sit down
to a family dinner
when the engagement
was for home.
Some of the officers
always made part of it,
of which officers Mr.
Wickham was
sure to be one.
And on
these occasions, Mrs.
Gardner,
rendered suspicious
by Elizabeth's warm
commendation, narrowly
observed them both
without supposing them
from what she saw, to be
very seriously in love.
Their preference
of each other
was plain enough
to make her
a little uneasy.
And she resolved to.
Speak to Elizabeth
on the subject
before
she left Hertfordshire
and represent to her,
the imprudence
of encouraging
such an attachment
to Mrs.
Gardner.
Wickham had one means
of affording pleasure
unconnected
with his general powers.
About ten
or a dozen years ago,
before her marriage,
she had spent
a considerable time
in that
very part of Derbyshire
to which she belonged.
They had therefore
many acquaintances
in common.
And though Wickham.
Had been little there
since the death
of Darcy's father,
it was yet in his power
to give her fresher
intelligence
of her former friends
than she had
been in the way
of procuring.
Mrs.
Gardner had
seen Pemberley
and known the late Mr.
Darcy by character
perfectly well.
Here, consequently
was an
inexhaustible subject
of discourse and
comparing her
recollection
of Pemberley
with the
minute description
which Wickham
could give.
And in bestowing her
tribute of praise
on the character
of its late possessor,
she was delighting both
him and herself
on being made acquainted
with the present Mr.
Darcy's
treatment of him.
She tried to remember
some of that
gentleman's
reputed disposition
when quite a lot
which might
agree with it
and was confident
last that
she recollected,
having heard Mr.
Fitzwilliam Darcy
formerly spoken of as a
very proud,
ill natured boy.
Chapter 20.
Six.
Mrs.
Gardiner's caution
to Elizabeth
was punctually
and kindly given
on the first
favorable opportunity
of speaking to alone
after honestly
telling her
what she thought.
She thus went on,
You are too sensible
a girl, Lizzie,
to fall in love merely
because you are
warned against it.
And therefore
I am not afraid of
speaking openly.
Seriously, I would have
you be on your guard.
Do not involve.
Yourself or endeavored
to involve him
in an affection.
Which the wonder fortune
would make
so very imprudent.
I have nothing to say
against him.
He is the most
interesting young man.
And if he had
the fortune,
he ought to have.
I should think
you could not do better.
But as it is,
you must not
let your fancy run away
with you.
You have sense,
and we all expect you
to use it.
Your father would depend
on your resolution.
Good conduct.
I am sure
he must not disappoint
your father.
My dear aunt,
this is being serious.
Indeed.
Yes.
And I hope to engage.
To be serious.
Likewise.
Well, then
you need not be under
any alarm.
I will take care of
myself and Mr.
Wickham too.
He shall not be in
love with me
if I can prevent it.
Elizabeth.
You are not serious now.
I beg your pardon?
I will try again.
At present,
I am not in love
with Mr. Wickham.
No, I certainly am not.
But he is beyond
all comparison,
the most agreeable man
I ever saw.
And if he becomes
really attached to me,
I believe it will be.
Better that he should.
Not.
I see the imprudence
of it.
How?
That abominable Mr.
Darcy.
My father's
opinion of me
does me the greatest.
Honor,
and I be miserable
forfeited.
My father,
however, is
partial to Mr.
Wickham.
In short, my dear aunt,
I should be very sorry
to be.
The means
of making any of you.
Unhappy.
But since.
We see every day
that where there is
affection, young
people are seldom
withheld by.
Immediate wonder fortune
from entering
into engagements
with each other.
How can I promise.
To be wiser
than so
many of my
fellow creatures
if I am.
Tempted?
Well,
how am I even to know
that it would be wisdom
to resist?
All that I can promise
you, therefore, is
not to be in a hurry.
I will not be in a hurry
to believe myself.
His first object.
When I am in company
with him,
I will not be wishing.
In short,
I will do my best.
Perhaps it
would be as well
if you discourages
coming here
so very often.
At least
you should not remind
your mother
of inviting him
as I did the.
Other day,
said Elizabeth,
a conscious smile.
Very true.
It will be wise in me
to refrain from that.
But do not imagine that
he is always here
so often.
It is on your account
that he has been
so frequently this week.
You know.
My mother's ideas
as to the necessity.
Of constant company
for her friends.
But really,
and upon my honor,
I will try to do what
I think
to be the wisest.
And now I hope
you are satisfied.
Her aunt assured her
that she was.
And Elizabeth,
having thanked her
for the kindness
of her, hence
they parted
a wonderful instance
of advice
being given
on such a point
without being resented.
Mr.
Collins
returned in
to Hertfordshire
soon after it had been
committed
by the gardeners
and Jane.
But he took up his
abode with the.
Lucca says his arrival
was no great
inconvenience to Mrs.
Bennett.
His marriage was now
fast approaching,
and she was at length
so far, resigned
as to think
it inevitable.
And even repeatedly to.
Say in
an ill natured tone
that she.
Wished
they might be happy.
Thursday
was to be the
wedding day.
And on Wednesday,
Miss Lucas paid
farewell visit.
And when she rose
to take leave,
Elizabeth, ashamed
of her mother's
ungracious
and reluctant
good wishes,
sincerely affected
herself,
accompanied her
out of the room
as they went downstairs
together,
Charlotte said.
I shall depend.
On hearing from you
very often.
Eliza.
That you.
Certainly shall.
And I
have another
favor to ask you.
Will you come
and see me?
We shall often meet,
I hope,
in Hertfordshire.
I am not likely to.
Leave
Kent for some time.
Promise Me
therefore, to come
to Hansford.
Elizabeth could.
Not refuse.
Though
she foresaw
little pleasure
in the visit.
My father and Maria
are coming to me
in March,
added Charlotte.
And I hope
you have consented
to be of the party.
Indeed, Eliza,
you will be as welcome
as either of them.
The wedding took place.
The bride and bridegroom
set off
for Kent
from the church door.
And everybody had
as much to say
or to hear
on the subject,
as usual.
Elizabeth soon
heard from her friend
and their correspondence
was as regular
and frequent
as it had ever been.
That it should be
equally unreserved
was impossible.
Elizabeth could never
address her
without feeling
that all
the comfort of
intimacy was over,
and they were determined
not to slacken.
As a correspondent.
It was for the sake of
what had been rather
than what was.
Charlotte's first
letters were received
with a good
deal of eagerness.
There could not
but be curiosity
to know.
How she would
speak of her new home,
how she.
Would like
Lady Katharine,
and how happy
she would dare
pronounce herself to.
Be.
Though
When the letters
were read,
Elizabeth felt
that Charlotte
expressed herself
on every point exactly
as she might
have foreseen.
She wrote cheerfully,
seemed surrounded
with comforts
and, mentioned nothing,
which she
could not praise.
The house, furniture
and neighborhood
and roads
were all to her taste.
And Lady Katherine's
behavior
was most friendly
and obliging.
It Was Mr.
Collins picture
of Hansford and Roses
rationally softened
and Elizabeth perceived
that she must
wait for her own
visit there to
know the rest.
Jane had already written
few lines to her
sister to announce
their safe
arrival in London.
And when she
wrote again.
Elizabeth hoped
it would be in her power
to say
something of
the Baileys.
Her impatience
for the
second letter
was as well rewarded
as impatience
generally is.
Jane had been
a week in town
without either
seeing or hearing
from Caroline.
She accounted for
it, however,
by supposing that
her last to her friend
from long born had,
by some accident,
been lost.
My aunt,
she continued,
is going to morrow
and to that part
of the town,
and I shall take
the opportunity
of calling.
In Grosvenor Street.
She wrote again
when the visit was paid,
and she had seen
Miss Bingley.
I did not think
Caroline and spirits.
Were her words.
But she was very glad
to see me
and reproached me
for giving her
no notice of my
coming to London.
I was right there
for my last
letter had
never reached her.
I inquired after that
brother course.
He was. Well.
But so much engaged.
With Mr.
Darcy
that they scarcely.
Ever saw him.
I found that Mr.
C was
expected to dinner.
I wish I could see her.
My visit was not long
as Caroline and Mrs..
Her still going out.
I daresay
I shall see them soon.
Here.
Elizabeth shook her
head over this letter.
It her that accident
only could discover
to Mr.
Bingley, her
sisters being in town.
Four weeks passed away.
And Jane.
Saw nothing of him.
She endeavored
to persuade
that she did
not regret it.
But she could no longer
be blind to Miss Bingley
and attention.
After waiting at home
every morning
for a fortnight
and inventing
every evening
a fresh excuse for her,
the visitor,
did it last appear?
But the shortness
of her stay, and yet
more the alteration
of her manner
would allow Jane
to deceive herself
no longer.
The letter,
which she wrote
on this occasion
to her sister,
will prove
what she felt.
My dearest Lizzie will,
I am sure, be incapable
of triumphing
in her better judgment
at my expense.
When I.
Confess myself
to have been
entirely deceived
in this
being these regard.
For me.
But my dear sister,
though
the event has proved
you right.
Do not think.
Be obstinate.
If I still.
Assert that.
Considering what
her behavior was,
my confidence
was as natural
as your suspicion.
I do not at all
comprehend her reason
for wishing
to be intimate with.
Me.
But if the same
circumstances
were to happen again,
I am sure I should
be deceived again.
Caroline did not return.
My visit till.
Yesterday.
And not a note.
Not a line did I receive
in the meantime.
When she did come,
it was very evident.
That she had no
pleasure in it.
She made a slight.
Formal apology
for not calling before.
Said not
a word of wishing
to see me again
and was in every respect
so altered a creature
that when she went away
I was perfectly resolved
to continue
the acquaintance
no longer.
I pity, though
I cannot help
blaming her.
She was very wrong
in singling me out
as she did.
I can safely say
that every advanced.
Intimacy began
on her side.
But I pity her
because she must feel
that she is
being acting wrong.
And because I am
very sure
that anxiety for her.
Brother is.
The cause of it.
I need not.
Explain myself further.
And though
we know this anxiety
to be quite needless.
Yet if she feels it,
it will easily account
for her behavior to me
and so deservedly
dear as he is to his.
Whatever anxiety
she must feel on
his behalf
is natural and amiable.
I cannot.
But one day,
however, it her
having any such
fears now,
because if he did
or cared about me,
we must have met
long ago.
He knows of my
being in town.
I am certain
from something
she said herself.
And yet it would seem
by her manner of talking
as if she wanted
to persuade herself.
That he is
really partial to Miss.
Darcy.
I cannot understand it
if I were not afraid
of judging harshly.
I should be almost
tempted to say
there is a
strong appearance
of duplicity
in all this, but I.
Will endeavor
to banish every.
Painful thought
and think only of what
will make me happy.
Your affection
and the
invariable kindness
of my dear
aunt and uncle.
Let me hear from you
very soon.
Mr. Bingley.
Said something of his
never returning
to Netherfield.
Again,
of giving up the house,
but not with
any certainty.
We had better
not mention it.
I am extremely.
Glad that you have
such pleasant accounts
from our friends at.
Hansford.
Pray.
Go to see them with Sir
William and Maria.
I am sure
he will be
very comfortable there.
Yours, etc..
This letter gave
Elizabeth some pain,
but her spirits returned
as she considered
the chain would
be no longer
duped by the sister
at least.
All expectation
from the brother
was now absolutely over.
She would not even wish
for a.
Renewal
of his attentions.
His character
sunk on every review
of it,
and as a punishment
for him,
as well as a possible
advantage to Jane.
She seriously hoped that
he might really soon
marry Mr.
D'Arcy sister.
As by Wickham's account,
she would make him
abundantly regret
what he had thrown away.
Mrs.
Gardiner about this time
reminded Elizabeth
of her promise
concerning
that gentleman
and required
information.
And Elizabeth
had such to send
as my father
gave contentment
to her aunt
and to herself.
His apparent partiality
had subsided.
His attentions
were over.
He was the admirer
of someone.
Elizabeth was
watchful enough
to see it all.
But she could see it
and write. Of it
without material pain.
Her heart had been
but slightly touched
and her vanity
was satisfied
with believing
that she would have been
his only choice
had fortune
permitted it.
The sudden
acquisition of ?10,000
was the most
remarkable charm
of the young lady
to whom he was now
rendering himself
agreeable.
But, Elizabeth,
less clear
sighted, perhaps
in this case
than in Charlotte's.
Did not.
Quarrel with him
for his wish of.
Independence?
Nothing.
On the contrary,
be more natural.
And while able
to suppose
that it cost him
a few struggles
to relinquish her,
she was ready
to allow it a wise
and desirable measure
for both
and could
very sincerely wish him.
All this was
acknowledged to Mrs.
Gardiner,
and after
relating the
circumstances
she thus went on.
I am now.
Convinced, my dear aunt.
That I have never
been much in love.
How I really.
Experience that pure
and elevating passion.
I should at present
detest his very name
and wish him all
manner of evil.
But my feelings
are not only
cordial towards him,
they are even impartial
towards this king.
I cannot.
Find out that I.
Hate her at all
or the time in the least
unwilling to think,
or a very good
sort of girl.
There can be no
love in all this.
My watchfulness
has been effectual.
And though I.
Certainly should be
a more
interesting object
to all my acquaintances,
would I distractedly in
love with him?
I cannot say that
I regret.
To my comparative.
Insignificance.
Importance may sometimes
be purchased too dearly.
Kitty and Lydia
take his defection
much more to heart than.
I do.
They are young
in the ways of the world
and yet opened
the mortifying
conviction that handsome
young men must.
Have something to live
on, as well as the plain
Chapter 27.
With no
greater events
than these
in the long born family
and otherwise
diversified
by little beyond
the walks to Maritain.
Sometimes dirty
and sometimes cold
to January
and February pass away.
March was to
take Elizabeth
to Hansford.
She had not
first thought
very seriously
of going thither,
but Charlotte,
she soon found,
was depending
on the plan
and she
gradually learned
to consider it herself
with greater pleasure
as well as greater
certainty.
Absence had increased
her desire
of seeing
Charlotte again
and weakened her disgust
of Mr.
Collins.
There was novelty
in the scheme.
And with such a mother
and such
companionable sisters.
Home could not be.
Faultless.
A little change
was not unwelcome
for its own sake.
The journey
would, moreover
give her a peep at Jane,
and in
as the time junior.
She would have been.
Very sorry
for any delay.
Everything, however,
went.
On smoothly
and was finally.
Settled,
according to Charlotte's
first. Sketch.
She was to.
Accompany Sir
William and his
second daughter.
The improvement
of spending
a night in London
was added in time,
and the plan became
as perfect
as plan could be.
The only pain
was in leaving
her father,
who would
certainly miss her,
and who,
when it came
to the point
so little
liked her going that
he told her to
write to him and almost
to answer her letter.
The farewell
between herself and Mr.
Wickham was
perfectly friendly
on his side.
Even more his presence
pursued
could not make
him forget
that Elizabeth
had been the first
to excite
and to
deserve his attention,
the first to listen
and to pity,
the first to be admired,
and in his manner
of bidding her adieu,
wishing her
every enjoyment
reminding her of what
she was to expect
in Lady
Catherine de Berg
and trusting
their opinion of her,
their opinion
of everybody
would always coincide.
There was a.
Solicitude, an interest.
Which she.
Felt must
ever attach her to him
with the most
sincere regard,
and she parted from him,
convinced that
whether married
or single,
he must always be her
model of the amiable
and pleasing
her fellow travelers.
The next day were
not of a kind
to make her thinking
less agreeable.
Sir William Lucas
and his daughter Maria,
a good humored
but as empty headed as
himself,
had nothing to say
that could be
worth hearing
and were listened to
with about
as much delight
as the rattle
of the shares.
Elizabeth
loved absurdities,
but she had known Sir
Williams too long.
He could tell her
nothing new
of the wonders
of his presentation
and knighthood,
and his abilities
were worn out
like his information.
It was a journey
of only 24 miles,
and they began it
so early
as to be in Grace
Church Street.
By noon
as they drove to Mr.
Gardner's door.
Jane was at
a drawing room
window watching.
Their arrival,
When they entered
the passage,
she was there
to welcome them.
And Elizabeth, looking
earnestly in her face,
was pleased to see it
healthful and lovely
as ever.
On the stairs were troop
of little boys and girls
whose eagerness
for their cousin's
appearance
would not allow them
to wait
in the drawing room,
and whose shyness,
as they had
not seen her for
12 month, prevented
their coming lower.
All was joy
and kindness.
The day passed most
pleasantly away
the morning and bustle
and shopping
and the evening
at one of the theaters.
Elizabeth then
contrived to
sit by her aunt.
Their first object
was her sister,
and she was more grieved
than astonished to hear
and reply
to her minute inquiries
that though Jane
always struggled
to support her spirits,
there were periods
of dejection.
It was reasonable,
however, to hope
that they would
not continue long.
Mrs.
Gardiner gave her
the particulars
also of Miss Bailey's
Visit in Grace
Church Street
and repeated
conversations
occurring at
different times
between Jane
and herself,
which proved that
the former
had from her heart
given up.
The acquaintance, Mrs.
Gardiner
then rallied her
niece on Wickham's
desertion
and complimented her on
bearing it so well.
But my dear Elizabeth,
she added,
What of a girl is Ms..
King?
I should be sorry
to think our friend
mercenary.
Pray, my dear aunt,
what is the difference.
In matrimonial affairs
between.
The mercenary
and the prudent motive?
Where does discretion.
End and avarice begin?
Last Christmas,
you were afraid of
his marrying me.
Because it would
be imprudent.
And now?
Because he is trying.
To get a girl
with only 10,000.
Pounds.
He want to find out that
he is mercenary.
If he will only tell me
what sort of girl
Miss King is.
I shall know
what to think.
She is a very good
sort of girl, I believe.
I know no harm of her.
But he paid her
not the
smallest attention.
Till her grandfather's.
Death made her mistress
this fortune.
No.
What should he
if it were not allowable
for him
to gain my affections
because I had no money?
What occasions
would there
be for him
making love to girl
whom he did
not care about and
who was equally pole?
But there
seems in a delicacy
in directing
his attentions
towards her
so soon
after this event,
and that in
distress
has not time
for all
those elegant decorum
which other
people may observe.
If she does not
object to it,
why should we?
Her not
objecting does not him.
It only shows her being.
Deficient
in something herself.
Sense or feeling.
Well, cried.
Elizabeth.
Have it as you choose.
He shall be mercenary
and she shall
be foolish.
No, Lizzie,
that is what I do
not choose.
I should be sorry,
you know, to think
ill of a young man
who has lived
so long in.
Oh, if that is all.
I have a very poor
opinion of young men
who live in Derbyshire
and their
intimate friends
who live
in Hertfordshire
are not much better.
I Am sick of them all.
Thank heaven.
I am going to morrow
where I shall find a man
who is not one
agreeable quality
who has neither manner
nor sent
to recommend him.
Stupid Men
are the only ones
worth knowing after all.
Take care, Lizzie.
That speech save a
strongly of
disappointment.
Before they were
separated by
the conclusion
of the play.
She had the unexpected
happiness
of an invitation
to accompany her uncle
and aunt in a
tour of pleasure,
which they proposed
taking in the summer.
We have noted a term
and how far it
shall carry.
Us, said Mrs.
Gardner.
But perhaps
to the lakes.
No scheme
could have been
more agreeable
to Elizabeth and her
acceptance
of the invitation.
Most ready and grateful.
Oh, my dear, dear aunt.
She rapturously cried.
What delight
was Felicity?
You give me fresh
life and vigor
adieu due
to disappointment
and spleen.
What are young men to
rocks and mountains.
Oh, what's ours
of transport
We shall spend.
And when we do return,
it shall not
be like other.
Travelers without being.
Able to give
one accurate
idea of anything.
We will know
where we have gone.
We will recollect
what we have seen.
Lakes, mountains,
rivers shall not
be jumbled.
Together in.
Our imaginations,
nor when we.
Attempt to describe
any particular scene
when we begin
quarreling
about its relative.
Situation.
Let our effusions
be less insupportable.
Than those of the
generality of travelers.
Chapter 20.
Eight.
Every
object in the next
journey was new
and interesting
to Elizabeth,
and her spirits were
in a state of enjoyment,
for she had seen her
sister looking so well
as to banish
all fear for her health
and the prospect of her
northern tour
was a constant
source of delight.
When they left
the high road
for the lane
to Hansford, every
I was in
search of the parsonage
and every turning
expected
to bring it in view.
The railings
of rose Ings
Park was
their boundary
on one side.
Elizabeth smiled
at the recollection
of all that
she had heard
of its inhabitants.
At length,
the parsonage
was discernible,
the garden
sloping to the road.
The house
standing in it,
the green pails
and the laurel hedge.
Everything declared
they were arriving.
Mr.
Collins and Charlotte
appeared at the door
and the carriage stopped
at the small gate,
which led by a short
gravel
walk to the house.
Amidst the nods
and smiles
of the whole party.
In a moment
they were
out of the shares,
rejoicing
at the
sight of each other.
Mrs.
Collins
welcomed her friend
for the liveliest
pleasure, and Elizabeth
was more
and more satisfied
with coming
when she found herself
so affectionately
received.
She saw instantly
that her
cousin's manners
were not altered
by his marriage.
His formal civility
was just what it had.
Been, and he detained.
Her some
at the gate to hear
and satisfy
his inquiries.
After all, her family,
they were then
with no other delay
than his pointing out
the neatness
of the entrance
taken into the house.
And as soon
they were in the parlor,
he welcomed them
a second time
with ostentatious
formality
to his humble abode
and punctually repeated
all his wife's
offers of refreshment.
Elizabeth was prepared
to see him in his glory,
and she could not help
in fancying
that in displaying
the good proportion
of the room,
its aspect
and its furniture.
He addressed himself,
particularly to her
as if wishing
to make her feel
what she had lost
and refusing him.
But though
everything seemed
neat and comfortable,
she was not able to
gratify him
by any sign of
and rather
looked with wonder
at her friend
that she could have
so cheerful an heir
with such a companion.
When Mr.
Collins said
anything of which
his wife
might reasonably
be ashamed,
which certainly.
Was not on seldom.
She involuntarily
turned her eye
on Charlotte
once or twice
she could discern
a faint blush.
But in general,
Charlotte wisely
did not hear
after sitting
long enough to admire
every article
of furniture
in the room,
from the sideboard
to the fender.
To give an account
of their journey
and of all that
had happened in London.
Mr.
invited them
to take a stroll
in the garden.
Which.
Was large
and well laid out,
and to the cultivation
of which
he attended himself.
To work in this garden
was one of his
most respectable,
and Elizabeth
admired
the command
of countenance
with which Charlotte
talked
of the healthfulness
of the exercise,
and she encouraged it
as much as possible.
Here, leading the way
through every walk
and crosswalk
and scarcely
allowing them
an integral
to utter the praise
as he asked for.
Every view
was pointed out
with a mind newness,
which left beauty
entirely behind.
He could number
the fields
in every direction
and could tell
how many trees
there were
in the most
distant clump.
But of all the views
which his garden
or which
the country or kingdom
could boast.
None were to be.
Compared
with the prospect
of rose eggs afforded
by an opening
in the trees
that bordered
the park near
the opposite
the front of his.
House.
It was a.
Handsome,
modern building,
well situated on
rising ground.
From his garden, Mr.
Collins would have led
them round his
to Meadows.
But the lady's
not having shoes
to encounter
the remains of a white
frost turned back.
And while Sir William
accompanied him,
Charlotte
took her sister
and friend
over the house.
Extremely well pleased.
Probably to have
the opportunity
of showing it
without her
husband's help.
It was rather small,
but well-built
and convenient,
and everything
was fitted up
and arranged
with a neatness
and consistency, of
which Elizabeth
gave Charlotte
all the credit.
When Mr.
Collins could
be forgotten,
there was really an air
of great comfort
throughout
and by Charlotte's
evident enjoyment of.
Elizabeth supposed
he must be
often forgotten.
She had already learned
that Lady Catherine
was still in
the country.
It was spoken of again
while they
were at dinner.
When Mr.
Collins
joining in observed.
Yes, Miss Elizabeth,
you will have the honor
of seeing Lady Catherine
de Boer on the ensuing
Sunday at church,
and I need not say
you will be
delighted with her.
She is all
affability and
condescension,
and I doubt not.
But you will
be honored
with some portion
of her notice
when service is over.
I scarcely
any hesitation in saying
that she will include
you and my sister Maria
in every invitation
with which she honors
us during
your stay here.
Her behavior.
To my dear
Charlotte, is charming.
We dine at Rose's
twice every week
and are never allowed
to walk home.
Her lady ships
carriage is regularly
ordered for us.
I should say one of her
ladies ships carriages.
So she has
several.
Lady Catherine is
a very respectable,
sensible woman indeed,
added Charlotte.
And a most
attentive neighbor.
Very true, my dear.
That is exactly
what I say.
She is the sort of woman
whom one
cannot regard with
too much difference.
The evening was spent.
Chiefly in talking over
Hertfordshire News
and telling again
what had already
been written
and when it closed.
Elizabeth,
in the solitude
of her chamber,
had to meditate
upon Charlotte's
degree of contentment
to understand
her address
and guiding
and composure
in bearing
with her husband,
and to acknowledge
that it was all done
very well.
She had also
to anticipate
how her visit
would pass.
The quiet tenor
of their
usual employments.
The vexatious
interruptions of Mr.
Collins
and the gay ities
of their intercourse
with rose ings.
A lively.
Imagination soon.
Settled at all
about the middle
of the next day.
She was in her room,
getting ready
for a walk.
A sudden.
Noise below
seemed to speak
the whole house.
In confusion.
And after
listening a moment,
she heard somebody
running up the stairs
in a violent hurry
and calling loudly her.
She opened the door
and met Mariah
in the landing place.
Who.
Breathless
with agitation,
cried out.
Oh, my dear Eliza,
pretty make haste
and come into the dining
room,
for there is
such a sight to be seen.
I will not tell.
You what it is.
Make haste and come down
this moment.
Elizabeth asked
questions in vain.
Mariah would tell her
nothing, and down
they ran into
the dining room,
which fronted the lane
In quest of this wonder.
It was two ladies
stopping in
a low phaeton
at the garden gate.
And is this all?
Cried Elizabeth.
I expected at least that
the pigs
would got into
the garden.
And here is nothing
but Lady Catherine
and her daughter.
Oh, my dear.
Said Mariah.
Quite shocked
at the mistake.
It is not Lady
Catherine.
The old lady is Mrs.
Jenkinson,
who lives with them.
The other is Mr.
Burke.
Only look at her.
She is
quite a little creature.
Who would have thought
that she could be
so thin and small?
She is abominably rude
to keep Charlotte
out of doors
and all this wind.
Why does won't
she come in?
Oh, Charlotte says
she hardly ever does.
It is the greatest
of favors when Mr.
Burg comes in.
I like her appearance.
Said Elizabeth, Struck
with other ideas.
She looks sickly
and cross.
Yes, she will do for him
very well.
She will make him
a very proper wife.
Mr.
Collins and Charlotte
were both standing
at the gate conversation
with the ladies
and Sir William
to Elizabeth's
high diversion.
Was stationed.
In the doorway
in earnest contemplation
of the greatness
before him.
And.
Constantly, whenever Mr.
Burg looked that way.
At length,
there was nothing
more to be said.
The ladies drove on
and the others
returned into the house.
Mr.
Collins no sooner
saw the two girls
than he began
to congratulate them
on their good fortune,
which Charlotte
explained by
letting them know
that the whole party
was asked to
dine at roses
the next day.
Chapter 29
Mr.
Collins is triumph in
consequence of
this invitation
was complete.
The power of displaying
the grandeur
of his patroness
to his
wandering visitors,
and of letting them
see her civility
towards himself
and his wife was exactly
what he had wished for.
And that
an opportunity of doing
it should be given so.
Soon was such
an instance.
Of Lady
Katherine's
condescension as he knew
not how to admire.
Enough.
I confess.
That he.
That I should
not have been
at all surprised by Her
Ladyship
asking us on Sunday
to drink tea
and spend the evening
at Rose Ings.
I rather expected
from my knowledge of,
her affability
that it would happen.
But who could
have foreseen
such an attention
as this?
Who could have
imagined that
we should receive
an invitation to dine?
There
and invitation moreover,
including
the whole party?
So immediately
after your arrival.
I am the less surprised
at what has happened.
Replied Sir William.
From that knowledge
of what
the manners
of the great really are,
which my situation
in life
has allowed me
to acquire
about the Court.
Such instances
of elegant breeding
are not uncommon.
Scarcely
anything was talked of.
The whole day
or next morning.
But their visit to Rose
Kings, Mr.
Collins
was carefully
instructing them
in what they were to.
Expect
that the sight of.
Such rooms,
so many servants
and so splendid a dinner
might not wholly
overpower them.
When the ladies
were separating
for the toilette,
he said to, Elizabeth.
Do not make
yourself uneasy, my dear
cousin, about
your apparel,
lady Catherine is
far from requiring
that elegance
of dress in us,
which becomes
herself and daughter.
I would advise
you merely
to put on
whatever of
your clothes is superior
to the rest.
There is no occasion
for anything more.
Lady Catherine
will not think
the worse of you
for being
simply dressed.
She likes to have
the distinction
of rank preserved.
While they were
dressing,
he came two
or three times
to their different doors
to recommend their
being quick as lady.
Catherine very much
objected to be kept
waiting for her dinner.
Such formidable
accounts of her Ladyship
and her
manner of living.
Quite frightened
Maria Lucas,
who had been little
used to company
and she looked forward
to her introduction
at Rose, sings
with as
much apprehension
as her father had done
to his presentation.
At St James's.
As the weather was fine.
They had a pleasant
walk of
about half a mile
across the park.
Every park
has its beauty
and its prospects
and Elizabeth,
so much to be
pleased with.
Though she.
Could not be in
such raptures as Mr.
Collins expected
the scene to inspire.
And.
Was but
slightly affected
by his enumeration
of the windows
in front of the house
and relation
of what
the glazing
altogether had
originally costs
or Louis to Bourg.
When they ascended
the steps to the hall.
Maria's
alarm was every
moment increasing,
and even Sir William
did not look
perfectly calm.
Elizabeth's courage
did not fail her.
She had heard
nothing of Lady
Catherine
that spoke her awful
from any
extraordinary talents,
miraculous virtue,
and the mere stateliness
of money or rank
she thought she
could witness
without trepidation.
From the entrance
hall, of which Mr.
Collins pointed out
a rapturous air,
the fine proportion
and the
finished ornaments.
They followed
the servants
through an antechamber
to the room
where Lady Catherine,
her daughter, and Mrs.
Jenkinson, were sitting.
Her ladyship,
with great
condescension, arose
to receive them,
and as Mrs.
Collins had settled it
with her husband,
that the office
of Introduction
should be hers.
It was performed
in a proper manner,
without any
of those apologies
and thanks,
which he would have
thought necessary.
In spite of having
been at St James's, Sir
William was so
completely awed
by the grandeur
surrounding.
Him that he had,
but just carriage
enough.
To make a very low bow
and to take his seat
without saying a word.
At.
His daughter, frightened
almost out
of her senses.
Sat.
On the edge of chair,
not knowing
which way to look.
Elizabeth found herself
quite equal to the scene
and could observe
the three ladies
before her
composed oddly.
Lady Catherine,
a tall, large woman
with strongly marked.
Features
which might once.
Have been handsome.
Her heir was
not consolidating,
nor was her manner
of receiving them
Such to make
her visitors
forget their inferior
rank.
She was not rendered
formidable by silence.
But whatever she said
was spoken in
so authoritative
a tone as marked herself
and brought Mr.
Wickham immediately
to Elizabeth's mind.
And from the observation
of the day altogether.
She believed
Lady Katharine
to be exactly.
What he represented.
When, after
examining the mother
in whose countenance
and deportment
she soon found
some resemblance of Mr.
Darcy.
She turned her
eyes on the daughter
she could have joined
in rise
astonishment at her
being so thin.
And so small.
There was
neither in figure
nor face any likeness
between the ladies.
Mr.
Bourg was pale
and sickly.
Her features, though
not plain,
were insignificant,
and she spoke
very little,
except in a low voice
to Mrs..
Jenkinson, in whose.
Appearance
there was
nothing remarkable,
and who was
entirely engaged
in listening
to what she said
and placing a screen
in the proper direction
before her eyes.
After sitting
a few minutes,
they were all sent
to one of the windows
to admire the view.
Mr.
Collins
attending them
to point out
its beauties, and Lady
Catherine kindly
informing them
that it was much
better worth
looking at
in the summer.
The dinner was
exceedingly handsome
and there were
all the servants
and all the
articles of plate,
which Mr.
Collins had promised,
and as he had
likewise foretold.
He took his.
Seat at the bottom
of the table.
Her lady ships desire,
and looked as if he felt
that life could furnish
nothing greater.
He carved and ate
and praised
with delighted alacrity,
and every dish
was commended,
first by him
and then by Sir William,
who was now
enough for cover to echo
whatever his son in law
said, in a manner
which Elizabeth
wondered Lady
Catherine could bear.
But Lady
Catherine
seemed gratified
by their
excessive admiration
and gave
most gracious smiles,
especially when any dish
on the table
proved a novelty
to them.
The did not supply
much conversation.
Elizabeth was ready
to speak
whenever there
was an opening.
But she was seated.
Between Charlotte
and Mr.
Burke,
the former of
whom was engaged
in, listening
to Lady Catherine,
and the latter said
not a word to her
all dinnertime.
Mrs.
Jenkinson
was chiefly employed
in watching
how little Mr.
Burke ate, pressing her
to try other dish
and fearing
she was indisposed.
Maria thought,
speaking out of the.
Question and the.
Gentleman did nothing
but eat and admire.
When the
ladies
to the drawing room,
there was little
to be done.
But to hear Lady
Catherine talk.
Which she did.
Without any intermission
until coffee came in,
delivering her opinion
on every subject
and so decisive a manner
as proved
that she was not used
to have
her judgment
introverted.
She inquired
into Charlotte's
domestic concerns
familiarly and minutely
gave her a great deal
of advice
as to the
management of them all,
told her how everything
ought to be regulated
in so small a family
as hers,
and instructed her
as to the care
of her cows
and her poultry.
Elizabeth found
that nothing was beneath
this great
lady's attention,
which could furniture
with an occasion
of dictating to others.
In.
The intervals
of her discourse of Mrs.
Collins.
She addressed a variety
of questions
to Maria and Elizabeth.
But especially.
To the latter
of whose connection
she knew the least.
And who she. Observed.
Mrs.
Collins was a
very genteel,
pretty kind of girl.
She asked her
at different times
how many sisters
she had,
whether They were older
or younger than herself,
whether any of them
were likely
to be married,
whether they
were handsome,
whether they had
been educated,
what carriage
her father kept,
and what had been
her mother's
maiden name.
Elizabeth felt
all the impertinence
of her questions,
but answered them
very composed, oddly.
Lady Catherine
then observed.
Your father's estate
is entailed on Mr.
Collins, I think,
for your sake.
Turning to Charlotte.
I am glad of it.
But otherwise
I see no occasion
for entailing estates
from the female line.
It was not thought
necessary in Sir Louis
De Berg's family.
Do you play and sing,
Miss Bennett?
A little, No.
Then sometime or other,
we shall be
happy to hear you.
Our instrument
is a capital one.
Well, probably superior
to you.
Shall try it someday.
Do your sisters
play and sing?
One of them
does.
Why did not
you all done?
You walked
to have learned
the Miss
Webb's old play.
And their father
has not so good
an income as yours.
Do you draw?
No, not at all.
Oh, what?
None of you.
Not one.
That is
very strange.
But I suppose
you had opportunity.
Your mother should
have taken you
to town every spring
for the
benefit of Masters.
My mother would have
had no objection.
But my father hates
London.
Has your governess
left you?
We never had
any governess.
No governess.
How was that possible?
Five daughters
brought up at home
without a governess.
I never heard
of such a thing.
Your mother must
have been quite a slave
to education.
Elizabeth
could hardly
help, smiling
as she assured her that
that had not
been the case.
Then who taught you?
Who attended to you
without a governess,
you must have
been neglected.
Compared
with some families,
I believe we were.
But such of us
as wish to learn.
Never wanted the.
Means.
We were always
encouraged to read
and had all the masters
that were necessary.
Those who chose
to be idle
certainly might.
Oh, I no doubt.
But that is what a
governess prevent.
And if I had known
your mother,
I should have
advised her
most strenuously
to engage one.
I always say that
nothing is to be done
in education
without steady
and regular instruction,
and nobody but
a governess can give it.
It is wonderful
how many families
I have been
the means
of supplying
in that way.
I am always
glad to get
a young person
well placed out
for nieces of Mrs.
Jenkinson are most
delightfully situated
through my.
And it was.
But the other day
that I recommended
another young person
who was
merely accidentally
mentioned to me,
and the family are quite
delighted with her.
Mrs.
Collins,
did I tell you
of Lady
Metcalf's
calling yesterday
to thank me?
She finds Mr.
Pope a treasure.
Lady Katherine said she.
You have given
me a treasure.
Are any of your younger
sisters out, Miss
Bennett?
Yes, ma'am.
All All what?
All five out
at once.
Very odd.
And you?
Only the second
the ones out
before the elder
ones are married.
Your younger sisters
must be very young.
Yes.
My youngest is not 16.
Perhaps she is for young
to be much in company.
But really, Mom,
I think it would
be very hard
upon younger sisters
that they
should not have
their share of society
in amusement
because the may not have
the means or inclination
to marry early.
The last born
has as good a
right to the pleasures
of youth at the first
and to be kept back
on such a motive.
I it would not
be very likely
to promote
sisterly affection
or delicacy of mind
upon my word.
Said Her Ladyship.
You give your opinion
decidedly for
so young a person.
Pray.
What is your age
with three younger
sisters grown up?
Replied Elizabeth,
smiling.
Ladyship can hardly
expect me to own it.
Lady Catherine
seemed quite astonished
at not receiving
a direct answer.
And Elizabeth suspected
herself
to be the first creature
who had ever
dare to trifle
with so much
dignified impertinence.
You cannot be
more than 20.
I am sure.
Therefore, you need
not conceal your age.
I am not one in 20.
When the gentleman.
Had joined them
and tea was over.
The card
tables were placed.
Lady Catherine, Sir
William and Mr..
And Mrs.
Collins
sat down to quadrille,
and as Mr.
Burke chose
to play it Casino.
The two
girls had the honor
of assisting Mrs.
Jenkinson
to make up her party.
Their table was stupid.
Scarcely
a syllable was uttered
that did not
relate to the game,
except when Mrs.
Jenkinson expressed
her fears of Mr.
Burke's being too
hot or too cold.
Or having too much
or too little light.
A great deal
more passed
at the other table.
Lady Catherine was,
generally speaking,
stating the mistakes
of the three others
or relating
some anecdote
of herself.
Mr.
Collins was employed
in agreeing
to everything
Her Ladyship said,
thanking her
for every fish he won
and apologizing
if he thought
he won too many.
Sir William
did not say much.
He was storing his
memory with anecdotes
and noble names.
When Lady
Catherine and her
daughter had played
as long as they chose,
the tables
were broken up.
The carriage was offered
to Mrs.
Collins,
gratefully accepted
and immediately ordered.
The party then gathered
round the fire
to hear Lady determine
whether they would
have on the morrow.
From these instructions,
they were summoned
by the arrival
of the coach.
And with many
speeches of.
Thankfulness on Mr.
Collins side
and as many boughs on
Sir William's,
they departed.
As soon as they had
driven. From the door.
Elizabeth was called on
by her cousin
to give her opinion
of all that
she had
seen at Rose things
which, for
Charlotte's sake,
she more favorable
than it really was.
But her
commendation, though
costing her
some trouble.
Could by no means.
Satisfy Mr.
Collins.
And he was very soon
obliged
to take her
ladyship praise
into his own hands.
Chapter 30
Sir William stayed
only a week
at Hunt's effort,
but his visit
was long enough
to convince
of his daughters
being most
comfortably settled.
And after possessing
such a husband
and such a neighbor
as were not.
Often met with.
While Sir
William was with them.
Mr.
Collins,
devoted his morning
to driving him out
at his gig
and showing him
the country.
But when he went away.
The whole
family returned
to their
usual employments,
and Elizabeth
was thankful
to find that
they did not see more
her cousin
by the alteration.
For the chief
of the time
between breakfast
and dinner
was now passed by him
either
at work in the garden
or in reading
and writing
and looking out
of the window
in his own book room,
which fronted the road.
The room in which.
The lady
sat was backwards.
Elizabeth had at first
rather wondered that
Charlotte
should not prefer
the dining parlor
for common use.
It a better sized room
and had a more
pleasant aspect.
But she soon.
Saw that her friend
had an excellent reason
for what she did.
For Mr.
Collins
would undoubtedly
have been much less
his own apartment
had they sat in one.
Equally lively.
And she gave
Charlotte credit
for the arrangement.
From the drawing room,
they could distinguish
nothing in the lane
and were indebted Mr.
Collins
for the knowledge
of what carriages
went along
at how often,
especially Mr.
Burke
drove by in her phaeton,
which he never failed
coming to
inform them of,
though it happened
almost every day.
She not on,
frequently stopped
at the parsonage
and had a few minutes
conversation
with Charlotte.
But was.
Scarcely ever
prevailed upon
to get out.
Very few days
passed in, which Mr.
Collins did
not walk to Rose Kings
and not many in which
his wife did
not think it necessary
to go likewise and tell.
Elizabeth recollected
that there might
be other family
livings to.
Be disposed of.
She could not
understand.
The sacrifice
of so many hours now
and then
they were honored
with a call
from Her Ladyship
and nothing escaped
her observation
that was passing
in the room
during these visits,
she examined into
their employments,
looked at their work
and advised
them to do it
differently.
Found fault
with the arrangement
of the furniture
or detected
the housemaid
in negligence
and she accepted
any refreshment
seemed to do it
only for the sake of
finding out that Mrs.
Collins's joints of meat
were too large
for her family.
Elizabeth soon
perceived.
That.
This great lady was.
Not in condition.
Of the
peace of the county.
She was the most active
magistrate
in her own parish.
The minutest concerns
of which were carried
to her by Mr.
Collins.
And whenever
any of the cottagers
were disposed
to be
quarrelsome,
discontented
or too poor,
she slid forth
into the village
to settle
their differences,
silence their complaints
and scold
them into harmony
and plenty.
The entertainment
of dining at rose rings
is repeated about twice
a week
and allowing
for the loss
of Sir William and there
being only
one card table in the.
Every such entertainment
was the counterpart
of the first.
Their other engagements
were few
as the style
of living
in the neighborhood
in general
was beyond Mr.
Collins reach.
This, however,
was no evil
to Elizabeth,
and upon the whole
she spent her time
comfortably enough.
There were half hours
of pleasant conversation
with Charlotte,
and the weather
was so fine
for the time year
that she had often
great enjoyment
out of doors,
her favorite walk,
and where
she frequently went
while the others
were calling on
Lady Catherine was along
the open grove,
which edged
that of the park
where there was a nice,
sheltered path
which no one
seemed to value
but herself,
and where
she felt
beyond the reach of Lady
Catherine's curiosity.
In this quiet way.
The first
fortnight of her visit
soon passed away.
Easter was approaching
and the week preceding
it was to bring
an addition
to the family
at Rose Ings.
Which in so.
Small a circle
must be important.
Elizabeth had heard soon
after her arrival
that Mr.
Darcy was expected there
in the course
of a few weeks,
and though
there were not
many of
her acquaintances
whom she did not prefer,
his coming
would furnish one
comparatively new
to look at
in their roses parties.
And she might
be amused in.
Seeing how hopeless Ms..
Bayley's designs on him
were by his behavior
to his cousin for whom
he was
evidently destined
by Lady Catherine.
Who talked of his.
Coming
with the
greatest satisfaction,
spoke of him in terms
of the
highest admiration,
and seemed almost angry,
find that
he had already
been frequently
seen by Ms..
Lucas and herself.
His arrival
was soon
known at the parsonage
for Mr.
Collins was walking
the whole morning
within view
of the lodge's
opening into Hunt's
four lane.
In order to have.
The earliest
assurance of it.
And after making his bow
as the carriage
turned into the park,
hurried home
with the
great intelligence.
On the
following morning,
he hastened to Rose's
to pay his respects.
There were two nephews
of Lady Catherine
to require them for Mr.
Darcy had
brought with him
a Colonel Fitzwilliam,
the younger
son of his uncle,
Lord Blanc,
and to the
great surprise
of all the party.
When Mr.
Collins returned.
The gentleman
accompanied.
Him.
Charlotte had seen them
from her husband's room,
crossing the road
and immediately
running into the other,
told the girls
what an honor
they might
expect, adding.
I may thank you, Eliza.
For this peace of.
Civility. Mr.
Darcy would never have
come so
soon to wait upon me.
Had scarcely
time to disclaim
all rights
to the compliment.
Before their approach
was announced
by the doorbell.
And shortly afterwards,
the three gentlemen
entered the room.
Colonel Fitzwilliam
led the way.
Was about 30.
Not handsome, but.
In person,
and addressed
most truly
the gentleman.
Mr.
Darcy looked
just as he had
been used
to look
in Hertfordshire,
paid his compliments
with his usual
reserved Mrs.
Collins. And.
Whatever might be
his feelings
toward her friend
met her
with every appearance
of composure.
Elizabeth merely
curtsy to him
without a word.
Colonel
Fitzwilliam entered
into conversation
directly
with the readiness
and ease
of a well-bred man
and talked
very pleasantly.
But his cousin,
after having addressed
a slight observation
on the house
and garden to Mrs.
Collins.
Sat for some.
Time without speaking.
To anybody.
At length, however,
his civility was so
far awakened
as to inquire
of Elizabeth,
the health
of her family.
She answered him
in the usual way
and after a moment's
pause, added.
My eldest
sister has been in town
these three months.
Have you never happened
to see her?
That she was
perfectly sensible,
that he never had.
But she wished to.
See whether he
would betray
any consciousness
of what had passed
between the
Bengalis and Jane?
And she thought
he looked
a little confused
as he answered that he.
Had never been
so fortunate
as to meet Miss Bennett.
The subject was pursued
no farther,
and the gentleman soon
afterwards went away.
Chapter 31
Colonel Fitzwilliams
Manners
were very much admired
at the parsonage,
and the ladies all felt
that he must add
considerably
to the pleasures
of their engagements
at Rose Ings.
It was some.
Days, however,
before they received
any invitation thither.
For while
there were visitors
in the house.
They could
not be necessary.
And it was not
till Easter day,
almost a week
after the
gentleman's arrival,
that they were honored
by such an attention.
And then they were
merely asked
on leaving church
to come there
in the evening.
For the last week,
they had seen
very little of Lady
Catherine
or her daughter.
Colonel Fitzwilliam
had called it
the parsonage
more than once
during the time.
But Mr.
Darcy,
they had only
seen a church.
The invitation
was accepted, of course,
and at a proper hour,
they joined the party
and Lady
Katherine's
drawing room.
Her ladyship
received them civilly,
but it was plain
that their company was
by no means
so acceptable
as when she could
get nobody else.
And she was in fact
almost engrossed
by her nephews
speaking to them,
especially to Darcy,
much more
than to any other person
in the room.
Colonel Fitzwilliam
seemed really glad
to see them.
Anything was a welcome
relief to him
that Rosing and Mrs.
Collins
pretty friend had.
Moreover, his fancy
very much.
He now seated himself
by her and talked
so agreeably of Kent
and Hertfordshire,
of traveling
and staying at home, of.
New books.
And music
that Elizabeth had never
been half so well
entertained in that
room before.
And they conversed with
so much spirit and flow
as to draw the attention
of Lady
Catherine herself,
as well as of Mr.
Darcy.
His eyes had been soon
and repeatedly charged
towards them
with a look
of curiosity,
and that her ladyship,
after a while shared
the feeling was more
openly acknowledged.
For she did not.
Scruple to call out.
What is it
that you were
saying, Fitzwilliam?
What is it
you are talking of?
What are you telling
Miss Bennett?
Let me hear what it is.
We are speaking
of music, madam.
Said he, when.
No longer able
to avoid a reply.
Of music,
then pray
speak aloud.
It is of all subjects,
my delight.
I must have my
share in
the conversation.
If you are
speaking of music.
There are few people
in England,
I suppose have more true
enjoyment of
music than myself
or of a better
natural taste.
If I had ever learned,
I should have been
a great proficient
and so would Anne,
if her health
had allowed her
to apply,
I am confident
that she would have
performed delightfully.
How does Georgiana
get on Darcy?
Mr.
Darcy spoke
with affectionate
praise of his sister's
proficiency.
I am very glad to hear
such a good
account of her.
Said Lady Catherine.
And pray her from me
that she cannot expect
to excel if she does not
practice a good deal.
I assure you, madam.
He replied.
That she does not need
such advice.
She practices
very constantly.
And so much the better.
It cannot be done
too much.
And when I next
write to her,
I shall charge
not to neglect it
on any account.
I often tell
young ladies
that no excellence
in music
is to be acquired
without constant
practice.
I have told Ms..
Bennett several times
that she will
never play really well
unless she
practices more.
And though Mrs.
Collins has
no instrument,
she is very welcome.
As I have often told her
to come to Rose
every day and play
on the piano
Forte and Mrs.
Jenkinson's room,
she would be in nobody's
way, you know.
And that part
of the house.
Mr.
Darcy looked little
ashamed of
his aunt's ill breeding
and made no answer.
When coffee.
Was over,
Colonel Fitzwilliam
reminded Elizabeth
of having
promised to play.
To him.
And she sat down
directly
to the instrument.
He drew a chair
near her.
Lady Catherine
listened to half a.
Song and then.
Talked as before
to the other nephew,
till the latter walked
away from her
and, making
with his
usual deliberation
towards the piano Forte.
Stationed.
Himself so as to command
a full view of the fair
performer's countenance.
Elizabeth saw
what he was doing
and at the
convenient pause
turned to him
with an arch
smile and said.
You mean to frighten
me, Mr.
Darcy,
by coming in all this
state to hear me?
I will not be alarmed.
Your sister does play
so well.
There is a.
Stubbornness about me
that never can bear
to be frightened
at the will of. Others.
My courage
always rises at every
attempt to intimidate.
I shall not
say that you
are mistaken.
He replied.
Because you could
not really believe me
to entertain
any design of alarming.
You and I
have had the pleasure
of your acquaintance
long enough to know
that you find
great enjoyment
in occasionally
professing opinions
which in fact
are not your own.
Elizabeth
laughed heartily
at this picture
of herself
and to
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
Your cousin
will give you
a very
pretty notion of me
and teach you
not to believe a word
I say.
I am
particularly unlucky
in meeting
with the person, so able
to expose
my real character
in a part of the world
where I'd hoped
to pass myself off
with some
degree of credit.
Indeed, Mr.
Darcy.
It is very
and you to mention
all that
you knew
to my disadvantage
in Hertfordshire
and give me leave to say
very impolitic too,
for it
is provoking me
to retaliate and such
may come out as will
shock your relations
to hear.
I am not afraid of you.
Said he smilingly.
Pray.
Let me hear
what you have
to accuse him of.
Pride,
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
I should like
to know how he
behaves among strangers.
You shall here, then
must prepare yourself
for something
very dreadful.
The first time of my
ever seeing him
in Hertfordshire.
You must know that bull.
And this bull.
What do you think
he did?
He danced only
for dances, though.
Gentlemen.
Scarce.
And to my
certain knowledge,
more than one young lady
was sitting down
in want of a partner.
Mr.
Darcy, you cannot.
Deny the fact.
I had not at that time
the honor
of knowing any lady
in the assembly
beyond my own party.
True.
And nobody can ever
be introduced
in a ballroom.
Well, kind of.
Fitzwilliam,
what do I play next?
My fingers
await your orders.
Perhaps.
Said Darcy.
I should have judged
better had
I sought
an introduction, but I.
I'm ill qualified
to recommend myself
to strangers.
Shall we ask your cousin
the reason of this?
Said Elizabeth, still
addressing
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
Shall we ask him why?
A man of sense.
And education
and who has lived in
the world
is ill qualified
to recommend himself
to strangers?
I can answer
your question,
said Fitzwilliam
without applying to him.
It is
because he will
not give himself
the trouble.
I certainly
have not the talent
which some
people possess,
said Darcy
of conversing easily
with those
I have never
seen before.
I cannot catch that
tone of conversation
or appear
interested in
their concerns,
as I often see done.
My fingers,
said Elizabeth.
Do not move over
this instrument
in the masterly manner
in which I see
so many women do.
They have not the same
force or rapidity
and do not produce
the same expression.
But then I have always
supposed it
to be my own fault
because I will not take
the trouble
of practicing.
It is not that
I do not believe fingers
as capable
as any other woman
of superior execution.
Darcy
smiled and said.
You are perfectly right.
You have employed
your time much better.
No one admitted
to the privilege
of hearing.
You can think
anything wanting.
We, neither of us
performed to strangers
here.
They were
interrupted by lady
who called out to know
what they were
talking of.
Elizabeth immediately
began playing again.
Lady Catherine
approached and after
listening
for a few minutes, said
to Darcy.
Miss Bennet
would not play at all
amiss
if she practiced more
and would have
the advantage
of a London master.
She has a very
good notion
of fingering,
though her taste is not
equal to arms
and would have been a
delightful performer
had her health
allowed her to learn.
Elizabeth
looked at Darcy
to see how cordially
he ascended
to his cousin's praise,
but neither
at that moment
nor any other
could she discern
any symptom of love.
And.
From the whole
of his behavior to Mr.
Burke.
She derived this comfort
from his bingley.
That he might.
Have been
just as likely
to marry her had
she been his relation.
Lady Catherine
continued her remarks
on Elizabeth's
performance.
Mixing with.
Their many instructions.
On execution and taste.
Elizabeth received them
with all the
forbearance of civility,
and at the request
of the gentleman,
remained
at the instrument
until her lady ships
carriage was
ready to take them
all home.
Chapter 32.
Elizabeth was sitting
by herself
the next morning
and writing to Jane
while Mrs.
Collins and Mariah
were gone on business
into the village.
When she
startled by a ring
at the door,
the sergeant
signal of a visitor
as she had heard
no carriage.
She thought it.
Not unlikely
to be Lady Catherine.
And under
that apprehension.
Was putting.
Away her half
finished letter
that she might escape
all impertinent
questions.
When the door opened
and to her
very great surprise, Mr.
Darcy and Mr.
Darcy only entered
the room.
He seemed
astonished, too,
at finding her alone
and apologized
for his intrusion
by letting her know
that he had understood
all the ladies
were to be within.
They then sat down,
and when her inquiries
after roses were made,
seemed in danger
of sinking into
total silence.
It was absolutely
necessary, therefore,
to think of something.
And in
this emergency
recollecting,
when she had
seen him
last in Hertfordshire
and feeling curious
to know what
he would say
on the subject
of their
hasty departure,
she observed.
How very suddenly
you will, quitted.
Netherfield last
November, Mr.
Darcy.
It must have been a most
agreeable surprise
to Mr.
Bingley to see you all
after him so soon,
for if
I recollect right.
He went back to the day
before
he and his sisters were.
Well, I hope when
you left London.
Perfectly so.
I thank you.
She found that
she was to receive
no other answer.
And after a short
added.
I think
I have understood
that Mr.
Bingley has
not much idea of ever
returning to
Netherfield again.
I have never heard him
say so, but
is probable
that he may spend
very little of his time
there in future.
He has many friends
and he is at
a time of life
when friends
and engagements
are continually
increasing.
If he means to be back
little at Netherfield,
it would be better
for the neighborhood
that he should give up
the place entirely for.
Then we might possibly
get a settled
family there.
But perhaps Mr.
Bingley did not
take the house too much
for the convenience
of the neighborhood
as for his own.
And we must expect him
to keep it
or quit
it on the
same principle.
I should be surprised,
said Darcy.
If he were to give it up
as soon as any eligible
purchase offers.
Elizabeth made
no answer.
She was afraid
of talking
longer of his friend.
And having
nothing else to say
was now.
Determined
to leave the trouble of
finding a
subject to him.
He took the
hint and soon began.
With.
This seems
a very
comfortable house.
Lady Katharine,
I believe, did
a great deal to it
when Mr.
Collins
first came to Hansford.
I believe she did,
and I am sure she could
not have bestowed
her kindness
on a more
grateful object.
Mr.
Collins appears
very fortunate
in his choice of a wife.
Yes, indeed.
His friends
may well rejoice
in his having met
with one of the
very few sensible women
who would have
accepted him
or have made him happy
if they had.
My friend
has an
excellent understanding,
though I am not certain
that I consider her
marrying Mr.
Collins
as the wisest thing
she did.
She seems perfectly
happy, however,
and in a
prudential light.
It is certainly
a very good
match for her.
It must be
very agreeable
to her to be settled
so easy a distance
of her own family
and friends.
An easy distance,
do you call it?
It is nearly 50 miles
on.
What is 50
miles of good road?
Little more than.
Half a day's journey.
Yes.
I call it
a very easy distance.
I should never have
considered the distance
as one of the
advantages of the match.
Cried Elizabeth.
I should never have
said Mrs.
Collins was settled
near her family.
It is a proof of
your own attachment
to Hertfordshire.
Anything beyond
the very neighborhood
of Long Bourne,
I suppose, would
appear far.
As he spoke,
there was a
sort of smile
which Elizabeth fancied
she understood.
He must be supposing her
to be thinking of Jane
and Netherfield.
And she blushed
as she answered.
I do not.
Mean to say that
a woman may.
Not be settled
to near her family
this far.
And then
there must be relative
and depend on many
varying circumstances.
Well, there is
fortune to.
Make the expenses
of traveling.
Unimportant distance
becomes no evil.
But that is not the case
here.
Mr. and Mrs.
Collins
have a comfortable
income,
but not such a one
as will
allow of frequent
journeys.
And I am persuaded
my friend would
not call herself
near her family.
Under less than half
the pleasant distance.
Mr.
Darcy drew his chair
a little towards
her and said.
You cannot have a right
to such a very
strong local attachment.
You cannot have
been always at born.
Elizabeth
looked surprised.
The gentleman
experienced
some change of feeling.
He drew back his chair,
took a.
Newspaper
from the table,
and glancing it
sat in a colder voice.
Are you pleased
with Kent?
A short
dialog on the subject
of the country ensued
on either
side, calm and concise.
And soon put an end.
To by the entrance
of Charlotte,
and her sister
just returned
from her walk.
The tattered
hat surprised them.
Mr.
Darcy related
the mistake
which had occasion to,
on Mr.
Bennett hand
after sitting
a few minutes longer
without saying
much to anybody.
Went away.
What can.
Be the meaning of.
This?
Said Charlotte.
As soon as he was gone.
My dear Eliza.
He must be in
love with you.
Oh, he would
never have called on us
in this familiar way.
But when Elizabeth
told of his silence,
it did not seem
very likely
even to
Charlotte's wishes
to be the case.
And after various
conjectures,
they could at last
only suppose his visit
to proceed
from the difficulty
of finding
anything to do,
which was the
more probable
from the time of year.
All field
sports were over
within doors.
There was Lady
Catherine books
and a billiards table.
But a gentleman cannot
always be within doors
and in the nearness
of the parsonage
or the pleasantness
of the walk to it, or
of the people
who lived in it.
The two cousins
found a temptation
from this period
of walking thither
almost every day.
They called
at various times
of the morning,
sometimes separately,
sometimes together,
and now
and then accompanied
by their aunt.
It was plain to them all
that Colonel
Fitzwilliam came
because he had pleasure,
their society.
Of persuasion.
Which of course
recommended him
still more.
And Elizabeth
was reminded
by her own satisfaction
in being with him,
as well as by
his evident admiration
of her, of former
favorite George Wickham.
And though in.
Comparing them, she saw
there was less
captivating
softness in Colonel
Fitzwilliams manners.
She believed he.
Might have the best
informed mind.
But why Mr.
Darcy came
so often to
the parsonage.
It was more difficult
to understand.
It could not be for.
Society,
as he frequently
sat there
10 minutes together
without opening lips.
And when he did speak,
it seemed.
The effect of necessity
rather than of choice.
A sacrifice
to propriety.
Not a.
Pleasure to himself.
He seldom appeared
really animated.
Mrs.
Collins knew
not what to make of him.
Colonel Fitzwilliams,
occasionally
laughing at
his stupidity, proved
that he was
generally different,
which her own
knowledge of him
could not have told her.
And as
she would like
to believe this
change the
effect of love
and the object of that
love, her friend Eliza,
she set herself
seriously at work
to find it out.
She watched him
whenever were
at Rose Kings
and whenever
he came to Hansford.
But without
much success,
he certainly looked
at her friend
a great deal.
But the expression
of that
look was disputable.
It was an
steadfast gaze.
But she often doubted.
Whether there were
much admiration in it.
And.
Sometimes it
seemed nothing
but absence of mind.
She had once.
Or twice suggested
to Elizabeth
the possibility of his
being partial to her.
But Elizabeth
always laughed
at the idea, and Mrs.
Collins
did not think it right
to press the subject
from the danger
of raising expectations,
which might only end
in disappointment.
For, in her opinion,
it admitted
not of a doubt that all
her friends dislike
would vanish.
If she could suppose.
Him to be in her power
in her kind
schemes for Elizabeth.
She sometimes
planned her marrying
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
He was,
beyond comparison,
the most pleasant man.
He certainly admired
her and.
His situation in life
was most eligible.
But to counterbalance
these advantages, Mr.
Darcy had considerable
patronage in the church,
and his cousin
could have none at all.
Chapter 33.
More than once
did Elizabeth
in her ramble
within the park,
unexpectedly meet Mr.
Darcy.
She felt
all the perverse
ness of the Miss Chance
that should bring him
where no one else
was brought
and to prevent
its ever happening
again.
Took care to inform him
at first
that it was a favorite
haunt of hers.
How it could occur
a second time,
therefore was very odd.
Yet it's dead.
And even a third.
It seemed like
willful ill nature
or a voluntary penance,
for on these.
Occasions it was not.
Merely
a few formal inquiries
and an awkward pause
and then away.
But he actually.
Thought it
necessary to turn back
and walk with her.
He never said
a good deal,
nor did she give herself
the trouble of talking
or of listening much.
But it struck her
in the course
of their third rencontre
that he was asking
some odd, unconnected
about her
pleasure and being at.
Hunt's offered
her love
of solitary walks
and her opinion of Mr.
and Mrs.
Collins happiness
and that and speaking
of Rose Ings
and her
not perfectly
understanding the House.
He seemed to expect that
whenever she came into
Kent again.
She would be
staying there too.
His words
seemed to imply it.
Could he have Colonel
Fitzwilliam
in his thoughts?
She supposed
if he meant.
Anything,
he must mean an allusion
to what might arise
in that quarter.
It's distressed her
a little,
and he was quite glad
to find herself
at the gate in the Pales
the parsonage.
She was engaged
one day as she walked.
In, perusing
Jane's last letter
and dwelling
on some passages
which proved that
Jane had not
written in spirits when.
Instead of being again
surprised by Mr.
Darcy.
She saw and.
Looking up
that Colonel Fitzwilliam
was meeting her,
putting away her letter
immediately
and forcing a smile.
She said,
I did not
before that
you ever walked
this way.
I have been making
the tour of the park.
He replied.
As I generally do
every year,
and intended to close it
with a call
at the parsonage.
Are you going
much farther?
No.
I should have
turned in a moment.
And accordingly
she did turn
and they walked towards
the parsonage together.
Do you suddenly leave
Kent on Saturday?
She said.
Yes, if Darcy does
not put it off again.
But I am
at his disposal.
He arranges the business
just as he pleases.
And if not able to
please himself
in the arrangement,
he has at least.
Pleasure
in the great power.
Of choice.
I do not know anybody
who seems more
to enjoy the power
of doing what he likes
than Mr.
Darcy.
He likes to
have his own way.
Very well.
Replied
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
But so we all do.
It is
only that
he has better means
of having it
than many others
because he is rich
and many
others are poor.
I speak feeling
like a younger son,
you know.
Must be inured
to self-denial.
Independence
in my opinion.
The youngest
son of an earl can know
very little of either.
Now, seriously, what.
Have you ever known of?
Self-denial?
Independence.
When have you
been prevented
by want of money going
wherever you chose
or preparing anything
you had a fancy for?
These are home
questions,
and perhaps I cannot say
that I have experienced
many hardships
of that nature.
But in matters of
greater weight,
I may suffer from
the want of money.
Younger sons
cannot marry
where they like.
And less where they like
women of.
Fortune, which I think
very often they do.
Our habits of expense
make us too dependent,
and there are not many
in my rank of life
who can afford to marry
without some attention
to money.
Is this.
Thought Elizabeth.
Meant for me?
And she colored
at the idea.
But recovering herself
said in a lively town.
And pray.
What is the usual price
of an old younger son?
Unless the elder brother
is very sickly,
I suppose
you would
not ask about ?50,000.
He answered her
in the same style
and the subject dropped
to a silence,
which might
make him fancy
her affected
with what had passed.
She soon afterwards
said.
I imagine
your cousin
brought you down
with him.
Chiefly
for the sake of
having someone at his.
Disposal.
I wonder he does
not marry to secure
a lasting convenience
of that kind,
but perhaps his sister
does as well
for the present,
and as she is
under his so care,
he may do what he likes
with her.
No, said
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
That is an advantage
which he must
divide with me.
I am joined with him
in the guardianship
of Miss Darcy.
Oh, you indeed.
And pray,
what sort of guardians
do you make?
Does your charge
give you much trouble?
Young ladies of her age
are sometimes
a little
difficult to manage.
And she has the true
Darcy spirit.
She may like to have
her own way.
As she spoke,
she observed him
looking at her earnestly
and the manner
in which
he immediately
asked her why.
She suppose
Miss Darcy likely
to give them
any uneasiness,
convinced her
that she had somehow
or other
got pretty near
the truth.
She directly replied.
You need not
be frightened.
I never heard any harm
of her, and I dare say
she is
one of the
most tractable
creatures in the world.
She is a very
great favorite
with some ladies
of my acquaintance.
Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley.
I think I have heard you
say that you know them.
I know them a little.
Their
brother is a pleasant
gentleman like man.
He is a
great friend of doses.
Oh, yes.
Said Elizabeth dryly.
Mr.
Darcy is uncommonly kind
to Mr.
Bingley
and takes
a prodigious deal
of care of him.
Care of him?
Yes.
I really believe
Darcy does
take care of him
in those points
where he most
wants care.
From something
that he told me.
And our journey hither.
I have reason
to think Bingley
very much
indebted to him.
But I ought to beg
his pardon.
For
I have no right
to suppose that
Bingley was the
person meant
it was all conjecture.
What is it you mean?
It is a circumstance
which Darcy, of course,
could not wish
to be generally known.
Because if it were to
get round
to the lady's family,
it would be an
unpleasant thing.
You may depend upon
my not mentioning it.
And remember that I
have not much reason
supposing it
to be Bingley.
What he told me
was merely this
that he
congratulated himself
on having lately
saved a friend
from the inconveniences
of a most imprudent.
But without
mentioning names
or any
other particulars,
and I only suspected it
to be Bingley
from believing him,
the kind of young man
to get into a
scrape of that sort,
and from knowing them
to have been together
the whole
of last summer.
Did Mr.
Darcy give you reasons
for this interference?
I understood that
there were
some very strong
objections
against the lady.
And what art did he use
to separate them?
He did not talk to me
of his own arts.
Said Fitzwilliam,
smiling.
He Only told me
what I have
now told you.
Elizabeth made no answer
and walked on her heart,
swelling with.
Indignation.
After watching her
a little.
Fitzwilliam her
why she was
so thoughtful.
I am thinking of
what you've
been telling me,
said she.
Your cousin's conduct
does not suit
my feelings.
Why was he to be
the judge?
You are rather
disposed to call
his interference
officious.
I do not see what right.
Mr.
Darcy had to decide
on the propriety of his.
Friends in coronation,
or why,
upon his own judgment
alone,
he was to determine
and direct
in what manner
his friend
was to be happy.
But.
She continued,
recollecting,
as we know,
none of the particulars.
It is not fair
to condemn him.
It is not to be.
Suppose that
there was much
affection in the case.
That is not
an unnatural surmise,
said Fitzwilliam.
But it is lessening
the honor
of my cousin's triumph.
Very sadly.
This was.
Spoken justly.
But it appeared to her.
So just a picture of Mr.
Darcy.
That she would not.
Trust herself
with an answer
and therefore abruptly
changing
the conversation talked
on indifferent matters
until they reached the.
Parsonage.
Their shut into own room
as soon as
their visitor left them.
She could think
without interruption
of all that
she had heard.
It was not to
be suppose that.
Any other people
could be meant
than those with whom.
She was connected.
There could not exist
in the world
two men over whom Mr.
Darcy could have
such boundless.
Influence
that he had been.
Concerned
in the measures taken
to separate
Bingley and Jane.
She had never doubted.
But she.
Had always attributed
to Miss Bingley
the principal design
and arrangement of them.
If his.
Own vanity,
however,
did not mislead him.
He was the cause.
His pride.
And Caprice,
the cause of all
the Jane had suffered.
And still continue
to suffer.
He had ruined for
a while
every hope of happiness
for the
most affectionate,
generous
heart in the world.
And no one could.
Say how lasting an
evil he might
have inflicted.
There were
some very
strong objections
against the lady.
What Colonel
Fitzwilliams words
and strong objections
probably were.
Her having one uncle
who was a
country attorney
and another
who was in business
in London.
To Jane
herself, she.
There could be
no possibility
of objection.
All loveliness
and goodness, as she is
her understanding.
Excellent.
Her mind improved
and her
manners captivating.
Neither could anything
be urged
against my father,
who, though
with some peculiarities,
has abilities. Mr.
Darcy himself
need not disdain
and respectability,
which he will
probably never reach.
When she thought
of her mother,
her confidence
gave way a little.
But she would
not allow that.
Any objections?
There had
material weight with Mr.
Darcy,
whose pride
she was convinced
would receive
a deeper wound
from the want
of importance
in his
friend's connections
than from
their want of sense.
And she was quite.
Decided at last
that he had been
partly governed
by this kind of pride
and partly
by the wish
of retaining Mr.
Bingley for his sister.
The agitation and tears
which the subject
occasioned
brought on a headache
and it grew
so much worse
towards the evening.
That added
to her unwillingness
to see Mr.
Darcy.
It determined her
not to attend her
cousin's terrorizing
where they were engaged
to drink tea.
Mrs.
Collins,
seeing that
she was really unwell,
did not press her to go
and as much as possible
prevented her husband
from pressing her.
But Mr.
Collins could
not conceal
his apprehension
of Lady Katharine's
being rather displeased
by her staying at home.
Chapter 34.
When they were gone,
Elizabeth,
as if intending
to exasperate herself
as much as possible, Mr.
Darcy. Chose.
For her employment
the examination
of all the letters
which Jane had
written to her
since her being in Kent.
They contained
no actual complaint,
nor was there revival
of past occurrences
or any communication
of present suffering.
But in all and in
almost every
line of each, there was
a want of
that cheerfulness which.
Had been used.
To characterize
her style.
And which.
Proceeding
from the serenity
of a mind
at ease with itself
and keenly disposed
towards
everyone,
had been scarcely
ever clouded.
Elizabeth noticed
sentence, conveying
the idea of uneasiness
with an attention
which it had
hardly received
on the first perusal.
Mr.
Darcy shameful boast
of what misery he'd
been able to inflict.
Gave.
Her a keener
sense of her
sister's sufferings.
It was some consolation
to think
that his visit to Rosing
was to end
on the day
after the next,
and a still greater
that in
less than a fortnight.
She should herself be
with Jane again.
And.
Unable to contribute
to the recovery
of her spirits.
By all the defection
could do.
She could not.
Think of Darcy's
leaving Kent
without remembering
that his cousin
was to go with him.
But Colonel Fitzwilliam
had made it clear
that he had
no intentions at all
and agreeable as he was.
She did not.
Mean to be
unhappy about him.
While this point,
she was suddenly roused
by the sound
of the doorbell
and her spirits
were a little flattered
by the idea
of its being.
Colonel
Fitzwilliam himself.
Who had once.
Before,
called late
in the evening
and might now
come to inquire,
particularly after her.
But the idea was soon
banished and her spirits
were very
differently affected,
when, to her
utter amazement,
she saw Mr.
walk into the room
in a hurried manner.
He immediately began
an inquiry
after her health
and putting his visit
to a wish of hearing
that she were better.
She answered him
with cold civility.
He sat down
for a few moments
and then getting up,
walked about the room.
Elizabeth was surprised,
but said not a word.
After a silence
of several minutes.
He came towards her
in an agitated manner
and thus began
in vain.
Have I struggled?
It will not do.
My feelings will
not be repressed.
You must allow
me to
tell you how ardently
I admire and love you.
Elizabeth's astonishment
was beyond expression.
She stared.
Colored.
Doubted.
And was silent.
This, he considered
sufficient encouragement
and the avowal
of all that he felt
and had long felt
for her immediately
followed.
He spoke well,
but there were feelings
besides those
at the heart
to be detailed
and was not
more eloquent
on the subject
of tenderness
than of pride.
His sense of her
inferiority of its
being a degradation
of the family obstacles
which had
always opposed.
Inclination.
Were dwelt on
with a warmth which.
Seemed due
to the consequence
he was wounding.
But was very unlikely
to recommend his suit
in spite of her
deeply rooted dislike.
She could not be.
Insensible
to the compliment
to such a
man's affection.
And though
her intentions
did not vary
for an instant,
she was at first sorry
for the pain
he was to receive
till roused
to resentment
by his
subsequent language.
She lost
all compassion
and anger.
She tried, however,
to compose herself
to answer him with.
Patience when.
He should have done.
He concluded
with representing to her
the strength of
that attachment.
Which.
In spite
of all his endeavors,
he had found impossible
to conquer,
and with expressing
his hope
that it would
now be rewarded,
her acceptance
of his hand.
As he said this, she.
Could easily
see that he had no doubt
of a favorable answer.
He spoke of apprehension
and anxiety.
But his.
Countenance expressed
real security.
Such a circumstance
could only
exasperate further.
And when he ceased,
the color rose
into her cheeks.
And she said.
In such cases
as it is,
I believe
the established mode
to express
a sense of obligation
for the
sentiments of out,
however unequally
they may be returned.
It is natural
that obligation
should be felt.
And if I could
feel gratitude,
I would now thank you.
But I cannot.
I have never.
Desired to.
A good opinion,
and you have
certainly bestowed
it most unwillingly.
I am sorry
to have occasioned
pain to anyone.
It has been most
unconsciously done,
however,
and I hope would be
of short duration.
The feelings
which you tell me
have long prevented
the acknowledgment
of your regard can have
little difficulty
in overcoming it.
After this explanation.
Mr.
Darcy, who was leaning
against the mantelpiece
with his eyes
fixed on her face,
seemed to
catch her words
with no less resentment
than surprise.
His complexion
became pale with anger,
and the disturbance
of his mind was visible
in every feature.
He was struggling,
the appearance
of composure
and would not
open his lips
till he believed himself
to have attained it.
The pause was
to Elizabeth's feelings.
Dreadful.
At length,
with the voice
of forced
calmness, he said.
And this is
all the reply,
which I am to have
the honor of expecting.
I might perhaps
wish to be informed.
Why, with so little
endeavor at civility,
I am thus rejected.
But it is of
small importance.
I might as well inquire,
replied she, why,
with so evident
of offending
and insulting the
you chose to tell me
that you liked me
against your will,
against your reason,
and even against
your character?
Was not this some excuse
for incivility?
If I was in?
But I have
other provocations.
You know,
I have
had not my feelings
decided against you?
Had they been
indifferent
or had
they even
been favorable?
Do you think that
any consideration would.
Tempt me
to accept the man
who has been.
The means
of ruining
perhaps forever,
the happiness
of the most
beloved sister,
as she pronounced.
These words, Mr.
Darcy changed color,
but the emotion
was short
and he listened
without attempting
to interrupt her
while she continued.
I have every reason
in the world
to think of you.
No motive can excuse
the unjust
and ungenerous part.
You acted there.
You dare not.
You cannot deny
that you have been
the principal,
if not the only means
of dividing them
each other and exposing
one to the center
of the world,
the caprice
and instability,
and the other
to its derision
for disappointed hopes
and involving them both
in misery of
the acute ist kind.
She paused and saw
with no
slight indignation
that he was listening
with an air
which proved him
wholly unmoved
by any
feeling of remorse.
He even looked at her
with a smile of affected
incredulity.
Can you deny that
you have done it?
She repeated
with assumed
tranquility.
He then replied.
I have no wish
of denying that
I did everything
in my power
to separate my friend
from your sister,
or that I rejoice
in my success
towards him.
I have been
kinder than
towards myself.
Elizabeth disdained the
appearance of noticing
this civil reflection.
But its meaning
did not escape.
Nor was it likely
to conciliate her.
But it is not
merely this affair,
she continued,
on which my dislike
is founded
long before it had.
Even taken place.
My opinion of
you was decided.
Your character
enfolded in the recital,
which I received
many months ago from Mr.
Wickham on this subject.
What can you
have to say?
In what imaginary
act of friendship
can you hear?
Defend yourself?
Or under
what misrepresentation
can you hear
impose upon others?
You take an
eager interest
in that gentleman's
concerns.
Said D'Arcy, in a less
tranquil tone
and with a
heightened color.
Who that knows
what his misfortunes
have been can.
Help feeling an
interest in him.
His misfortunes.
Repeated.
Darcy contemptuously.
Yes, His
misfortunes have
been great indeed.
And of your infliction?
Cried Elizabeth.
With energy.
You have reduced him
to his present state
of poverty.
Comparative poverty.
You have withheld
the advantages
which you must know
to have been designed
for him.
You have deprived
the best years
of his life.
That independ,
which was no less
his do than his dessert.
You have done all this,
and yet you can treat
the mention
of his misfortune
with contempt
and ridicule.
And this.
Cried Darcy.
As.
He walked with quick
steps across the room.
Is your opinion of me?
This is the estimation
in which you hold me.
I thank you
for explaining it
so fully.
My faults,
according to
this calculation,
are heavy indeed.
But perhaps added
he stopping in his walk
and turning towards her.
These offenses might
have been overlooked
had not your pride
been hurt by my honest
confession
of the scruples
that had long
prevented my any
serious design?
These bitter accusations
might have
been suppressed
had I,
with greater policy,
concealed my struggles
and flattered
into the belief
of my being impelled
by unqualified,
unalloyed inclination,
by reason,
by reflection,
by everything
but disguise of
every sort
is my abhorrence.
Nor am I ashamed
of the feelings
I related.
They were natural
and just.
Could you expect me
to rejoice
in the inferiority
of your connections?
To congratulate myself
on the hope of relations
whose condition in life
is so decidedly
beneath my own?
Elizabeth Felt herself
growing more angry
every moment.
Yet she tried to
the utmost
to speak with composure
when she said.
You are mistaken, Mr.
Darcy.
If you suppose that
the mood
of your declaration
affected.
Me in any other way.
Then as it spared
the concern
which I might have
felt in refusing you,
had you behaved in a
more gentleman.
Like manner.
She saw
him start at this.
But he said nothing.
And she continued.
You could not have made
the offer of your hand
in any possible.
Way that would
have tempted me
to accept it
again.
His astonishment
was obvious,
and he looked at her
with an expression
of mingled incredulity
and mortification.
She went on
from the very beginning,
from the first moment
I may almost say,
of my acquaintance
with you,
your manners
impressing me
with the fullest belief
of your arrogance,
your conceit,
and your selfish disdain
for the feelings
of others.
Was that just a form
the groundwork
of disapprobation on
which succeeding
events have built
so immovable to dislike?
And I had not known you
a month before.
I felt that you were
the last man
in the world whom I ever
be prevailed
on to marry.
You have said
quite enough, Madam.
I perfectly comprehend
your feelings
and have now
only to be ashamed
of what my own
have been.
Forgive me
for having
taken up
so much of your time
and accept
my best wishes
for your health
and happiness.
And with these words,
he hastily left the room
and heard him.
The next moment,
open the French door
and quit the house.
The tumult of.
Her mind was now
painfully great.
She knew
not how to support.
Herself
and from
actual weakness,
sat down
and cried
for half an hour.
Her astonishment,
as she reflected.
On what had passed
was increased.
By every review.
Of it
that she should receive.
An offer of marriage
from Mr.
Darcy.
But he should
have been in love
with her
for so many months.
So much in love
as to wish to marry her
in spite
of all the objections
which had made him
prevent his friends
marrying her sister,
which must appear
at least
equal force in his.
Own case was almost.
Incredible.
It was gratifying
to have inspired
unconsciously so
strong in affection.
But his.
Pride. His.
Abominable pride,
his shameless avowal
of what he had done
with respect to Jane,
his unpardonable
assurance
and acknowledging,
though
he could not justify it,
and the unfeeling manner
in which.
He had mentioned Mr.
Wickham, his cruelty.
Towards whom he had not.
Attempted to deny.
Soon overcame the pity,
which the consideration
of his attachment
had for a
moment excited.
She continued in very
agitated reflections,
till the sound of Lady
Katherine's carriage
made her feel
how unequal she was
to encounter
Charlotte's observation
and hurried
her way to her room.
Chapter 35
Elizabeth awoke
the next morning
to the same thoughts
and meditations
which had at length,
closed her eyes.
She could not
yet recover
from the surprise
of what had happened.
It was impossible
to think of
anything else
and totally
indisposed
for employment.
She Resolved soon
after breakfast
to indulge herself
in air and exercise.
She was proceeding
directly
to her favorite walk
when the recollection
of Mr.
Darcy sometimes coming
there stopped her.
And instead of entering
the park,
she turned up the lane,
which led her farther
from the turnpike road.
The park
paling was still
the boundary
on one side,
and she soon passed
one of the gates
into the ground.
After
walking two
or three times
along that
part of the lane,
she was tempted
by the pleasantness
of the morning
to stop at the gates
and look into the park.
The five weeks
which she had now
passed in Kent
had made a great
in the country,
and every day
was adding to the
verdure of the
early trees.
She was on the point
of continuing her walk
when she caught
a glimpse
of a gentleman within
sort of grove,
which edged the park.
He was moving that way
and fearful
of its being. Mr.
Darcy,
she was
directly retreating,
but person who advanced
was now
near enough to see her
and stepping forward
with eagerness,
pronounced her name.
She had turned away,
but on hearing herself,
called though in a voice
which proved it
to be Mr.
Darcy, she moved again
towards the gate.
He had by that time
reached it also
and holding out a letter
which instinctively
took said
with a look of haughty
composure.
I have been
walking in the grove
some time
in the hope of
meeting you.
Will you do me
the of
reading that letter?
And then, with a slight
bow turned again
into the plantation
and was soon out
of sight,
with no
expectation of pleasure,
but with the
strongest curiosity.
Elizabeth opened
the letter and to her
still increasing wonder,
perceived
an envelope
containing
two sheets
of letter paper written
quite through
in a very close hand.
The envelope itself
was likewise full.
Pursuing her way
along the lane,
she then began it.
It was dated from Rosing
at 8:00 in the morning
and was as follows.
Be not alarmed,
madam, on receiving
this letter
by, the apprehension
of its
containing
any repetition
of those sentiments
or renewal
of those offers
which were last night
so disgusting to you.
I write
without any intention
painting you
or humbling myself
by dwelling on wishes,
which for the
happiness of both,
cannot be too soon
forgotten,
and the effort
which the formation,
the perusal
of this letter
must occasion
should have been spared,
had not my character
required it
to be written and read.
You must therefore
pardon the freedom with.
I demand your attention.
Your feelings
I know
will be
studied unwillingly,
but I demand it
of your justice.
Two offenses
of a very
different nature
and by
no means of
equal magnitude.
You last night
laid to my charge.
The first mentioned
was that regardless
of the sentiments
of either
I had detached Mr.
Bingley
from your sister.
And the other
that I had, in defiance
of various claims,
in defiance of honor
and humanity, ruined
the immediate prosperity
and blasted
the prospects of Mr.
Wickham willfully
and wantonly
to have thrown
off the
companion of my youth
the acknowledged
favorite of my father,
a man who had
scarcely any
other dependents
than on our patronage
and who had been brought
up to expect
its exertion
would be
a depravity
to which
to separation of
two young persons
whose affection
could be the growth
of only a few weeks
could bear
no comparison.
But from the severity of
that blame
which was last night
so liberally bestowed,
respecting
each circumstance,
I shall hope to be
in future secured.
When the
following account of my
and their motives
has been read.
If in the explanation
of them
which is due to myself,
I am under the necessity
of relating feelings
which may be
offensive to yours.
I can only say that
I am sorry.
The necessity
must be obeyed
and further apology
would be absurd.
I had not been long
in Hertfordshire before.
I saw in common
with others
that Bingley preferred
your elder sister
to any other
young woman in
the country.
But it was
not till the
evening of the dance
at Netherfield
that I had
any apprehension
of his feeling,
a serious attachment.
I had often
seen him in love before
at that ball while,
I had
the honor of
dancing with you.
I was first
made acquainted
by Sir William Lucas's
accidental information
that Bigley's attentions
to your sister
had given rise
to a general expectation
of their marriage.
He spoke of it
as a certain event
of which the time alone
could be undecided.
From that moment,
I observed my friend's
behavior attentively,
and I could
then perceive
that his partiality
for Miss
Bennett was beyond what
I had ever
witnessed in him.
Your Sister.
I also watched
her look and manners
were open, cheerful
and engaging as ever,
but without any symptom
of peculiar regard.
And I remained
from the
evening's scrutiny
that though
she received
his attentions
with pleasure,
she did not invite them
by any participation
of sentiment.
If you have not
been mistaken here,
I must have been
in an error.
Your superior
knowledge of your sister
must make the
latter probable.
If it be so,
if I have been misled
by such error
to inflict pain on her,
your resentment has
not been unreasonable.
But I shall not scruple
to assert
that the serenity
of your sister's
countenance and air
was such
as might have given
the most acute
observer
a conviction that
however amiable
her temper,
her heart was not likely
to be easily touched.
That was desirous
of believing
her indifferent
is certain.
But I will venture
to say
that my investigations
and decisions
are not
usually influenced
by my hopes or fears.
I did not believe her
to be indifferent
because I wished it.
I believed it on
impartial conviction
as truly as
I wished it, in reason.
My objections
to the marriage
were not merely those
which I last night
acknowledged
to have required
the utmost force
of passion to put aside.
In my own case,
the want connection
could not be so great
an evil to my friend
as to me.
But there were other
causes of repugnance.
Causes which, though
still existing
and existing
to an equal degree.
In both instances,
I had myself endeavored
to forget
because they were
not immediately
before me.
These causes
must be stated,
though briefly.
The situation
of your mother's
family, though
objectionable,
was nothing
in comparison of that
total want of propriety
so frequently,
so almost uniformly
betrayed by herself,
by your three
younger sisters,
occasionally even
by your father.
Pardon me.
It pains me
to offend you,
but amidst your concern
for the defects
of your
nearest relations
and your displeasure
at this
representation of them,
let it give
you consolation
to consider
that to have
conducted yourselves
so as to avoid
any share of the light.
Censure is praise
no less
generally bestowed
on you
and your eldest sister
than it is
honorable to the sense
and disposition of both.
I only say,
Father, that from
what passed
that evening,
my opinion of all
parties was confirmed
and every inducement
heightened
which could have led me
before
to preserve friend
from what
I esteemed
a most
unhappy connection.
He left Netherfield
for London
on the day following.
As you,
I am certain, remember
with the design
of soon returning,
the part
which I acted is now
to be explained.
His sister's uneasiness
had been equally excited
with my own.
Our coincidence
of feeling
was soon discovered
and alike
sensible that no time
was to be lost
in detaching
their brother.
We shortly resolved on
joining him
directly in London.
We accordingly went,
and then
I readily engaged
in the office
of pointing out
to my friend the certain
evils of such a choice.
I described
and enforced
them earnestly.
But however,
this remonstrance
might have staggered
or delayed
his determination.
I do not suppose that
it would ultimately
have prevented
the marriage
had it not been
seconded by
the assurance
which I hesitated.
Not in giving
of your sisters
indifference.
He had before
believed her
to return his affection
with sincere,
if not with
equal regard.
But Bingley has great
natural modesty,
with a
stronger dependance
on my judgment
than on his own.
To convince him,
therefore,
that he had deceived
himself
was no very
difficult point
to persuade him against
returning into
Hertfordshire
when that conviction had
given was scarcely
the work of a moment.
I cannot blame myself
for having done
thus much.
There is but
one part of my conduct
in the whole affair on
I do not reflect
with satisfaction.
It is that
I condescended to adopt
the measures
of art so far
as to conceal from him
your sisters being
in town.
I knew it
myself as it was known
to Miss Bingley,
but her brother
is even yet
ignorant of it,
that they might have met
without ill
consequences.
Perhaps Probable.
But his regard
did not appear to me
enough extinguished
for him to see her
without some danger.
Perhaps this
concealment,
this disguise
was beneath me.
It is done, however,
and it was done
for the best.
On this subject,
I have nothing
more to say.
No other apology
to offer.
If I have wounded
your sister's feelings,
it was unknowingly done.
And though
the motives
which govern me,
may to you
very naturally
appear insufficient,
I have not yet
learned to condemn them
with respect to that
other more
weighty accusation
of having injured Mr.
Wickham.
I can only refuted
by laying
before you
the whole of
his connection
with my family
of what
he has particularly
accused me.
I am ignorant
but of the truth of what
I shall relate.
I can summon more
than one witness
of undoubted veracity.
Mr.
Wickham is the son of
a very respectable man
who had for many years
the management
of all
the Pemberley Estates,
and whose good conduct
in the discharge
of his trust,
naturally inclined
my father,
to be of service to him.
And on George Wickham,
who was his godson.
His kindness
was therefore
liberally bestowed.
My father
supported him at school
and afterwards
at Cambridge.
Most important,
assistance
as his own father,
always poor
from the
extravagance of
his wife,
would have been unable
to give him
a gentleman's education.
My father was
not only fond of this
young man's society
whose manners
were always engaging.
He had also the
opinion of him
and hoping the church
would be his profession,
intended to provide
for him in it.
As for myself,
it is many, many years.
I first began
to think of him in a
very different manner.
The vicious
propensities, the
want of principle,
which he was careful
to guard
from the knowledge
of his best friend,
could not escape
the observation
of a young man of nearly
the same age
with himself,
and who
had opportunities
of seeing him
in unguarded moments,
which Mr.
Darcy could not have.
Here again,
I shall give you pain.
To what degree?
You only can tell.
But whatever may be
the sentiments which Mr.
Wickham has created
a suspicion
of their nature,
shall not prevent me
from unfolding
his real character.
It adds even
another motive.
My excellent father died
about five years ago,
and his attachment
to Mr.
Wickham was to the last.
So steady
that in his will he
particularly
recommended it to me
to promote advancement
in the best manner
that his profession
might allow.
And if he took orders
desired that
a valuable family living
might be his
as soon
as it became vacant,
there was also a
legacy of ?1,000.
His own father did
not long survive mine,
and within half a year
from these events, Mr.
Wickham wrote
to inform that
having finally resolved
against taking orders,
he hoped
I should not think it
unreasonable for him
to expect
some more immediate
pecuniary advantage
in lieu of
the preferment
by which
he could not
be benefited.
He had some intention,
he added,
of studying the law,
and I must be aware
that the interest ?1,000
would be
a very
insufficient support
therein.
I rather wished
and believed him
to be sincere,
but at any rate
was perfectly ready
to accede his proposal.
I knew that Mr.
Wickham ought
not to be a clergyman.
The business
was therefore
soon settled.
He resigned all claim
to assistance
in the church where.
It possible
that he could
ever be in a situation
to receive it and
accepted in return.
?3,000.
All connection between
us seemed now dissolved.
I thought to ill of him
to invite him
to Pemberley
or admit
his society in town.
In town
I believe
he chiefly lived.
But his studying
the law
was a mere pretense
and being now free
from all restraint.
His life was a life
of idleness
and dissipation.
For about three years,
I heard little of him,
but on the decease
of the incumbent
of the living,
which had
been designed for him,
he applied to me again
by letter
for the presentation.
His circumstances
he assured me
and I had no difficulty
in believing
it were exceedingly bad.
He had found the law
a most
unprofitable study
and was now
absolutely resolved
on being ordained.
If I would present him
to the living
in question
of which he trusted,
there could
be little doubt,
as he was well assured
that I had no other
person to provide for
and I could not have my
revered father's
intentions.
You will hardly
blame me for
refusing to comply
with this entreaty
or for resisting
every repetition of it.
His resentment
was in proportion
to the
distress of
his circumstances,
and he was doubtless
as violent
in his abuse of me,
to others
as in his reproaches
to myself.
After this period,
every appearance
of acquaintance
was dropped.
How he lived?
I know not.
But last summer
he was again
most painfully brooded
on my notice.
I must now mention
a circumstance
which I would wish
to forget myself
and which no obligation
less than the present
should induce me
to unfold to
any human being.
Having said thus, much,
I feel no doubt of
your secrecy.
My sister,
who is more
than ten years
my junior,
was left
to the guardianship
of my mother's
nephew,
Colonel Fitzwilliam
and myself.
About a year ago
she was
taken from school
and an establishment
formed for her
in London.
And last summer
she went with the lady
who presided it
to Ramsgate
and thither
also went Mr.
Wickham, undoubtedly
by design,
for that
proved to have been
a prior acquaintance,
him and Mrs.
Young,
in whose character
we were most
unhappily deceived
and by her connivance
and aid.
He so far
recommended himself
to Georgiana,
whose affection at heart
retained
a strong impression
of his kindness
to her as a child,
that she was persuaded
to believe
herself, love,
and to
consent to an elopement.
She was then but 15,
which must be
her excuse,
and after
stating her imprudence,
I happy to add
that I owed the
knowledge of
it to herself.
I joined them
unexpectedly a
day or two
before the
intended elopement,
and then Georgiana,
unable to support
the idea of grieving
and defending a brother
whom she
almost looked up
to as a father,
acknowledged
the whole To me.
You may imagine what
I felt and how I acted.
Regard
for my sisters
credit and feelings
prevented any
public exposure.
But I wrote to Mr.
Wickham,
who left the place
immediately,
and Mrs.
Young was,
of course,
removed from her charge.
Mr.
Wickham's chief
object
was unquestionably
my sister's fortune,
which is ?30,000.
But I cannot help
supposing that
the hope of revenge
ing himself on me
was a strong inducement.
His revenge
would have
been complete.
Indeed.
This, Madam,
is a faithful
narrative of every event
in which we have been
concerned together.
And if you do
not absolutely reject
it is false.
You, I hope, equip me
henceforth of cruelty
towards Mr.
Wickham.
I know
not in what manner under
what form of falsehood
he has imposed on you,
but his success is not
perhaps to be
wondered it
ignorant as you
previously were,
of everything
concerning either
detection could not
be in your power
and suspicion, certainly
not in your inclination.
You may possibly wonder
why all this was
not told you last night,
but I was not
then muster
enough of myself
to know what could
or ought to be revealed
for the truth
of everything
here related.
I can appeal more
particularly
to the testimony
of Colonel Fitzwilliam,
who from
our near relationship
and constant intimacy
and still more as one
of the executors
of my father's will,
has been unavoidably
acquainted
with every particular
of these transactions.
If your
abhorrence of me
should make
my assertions valueless,
you cannot be prevented
by the same cause
from confiding
in my cousin
and that there may be
the possibility
of consulting him.
I shall endeavor
to find some opportunity
of putting this letter
in your hands
in the course
of the morning.
I will only add.
God bless you.
Fitzwilliam
Darcy.
Chapter 36.
If Elizabeth, when Mr.
Darcy gave her
the letter,
did not expect it
to contain
a renewal of his offers.
She had formed
no expectation
at all of its contents,
but such as they were.
It may well be suppose
how eagerly
she went through them.
And what a contrary
a t of emotion they
her feelings,
as she read,
were scarcely
to be defined
with amazement.
Did she first
understand
that he believed
any apology
to be in his power,
and steadfastly
what she that
he could have
no explanation.
To give, which.
Suggest sense of shame
would not conceal
with a strong prejudice
against everything
he might say.
She began his account
of what had happened
at another field.
She read with
an eagerness
which hardly left
her power
of comprehension,
and from impatience
of knowing
what the next sentence
might bring,
was incapable
of attending
to the sense of the one
before her eyes,
his belief of her
sister's insensibility.
She instantly resolved
to be false,
and his account
of the real
the worst objections
to the match
made her too angry
to have any wish of
doing him justice.
He expressed
no regret
for what he had done,
which satisfied her.
His style was.
Not penitent,
but haughty.
It was all pride
and insolence.
But when this
subject was
succeeded
by his account of Mr.
Wickham, when she read
with somewhat
clearer attention
a relation of events.
If.
True,
must overthrow
every cherished
opinion of his worth,
and which bore
so alarming an affinity
to his own
history of himself.
Her feelings were yet
more acutely painful
and more difficult
of definition.
Astonishment,
apprehension,
and even horror
oppressed her.
She wished.
Discredited entirely
repeatedly exclaiming.
This must be false.
This cannot be.
This must be
the grossest falsehood.
And when she had gone
through the
whole letter,
the scarcely
knowing anything
of the last page,
or to put it
hastily away, protesting
that she would
not regarded,
never look in it again
in this perturbed state
of mind with thoughts
that could not
rest on anything.
She walked on.
But it would not do.
In half a minute,
the letter
was unfolded again
and collecting herself
as well as she could.
She again began
the mortifying
perusal of,
all that
related to Wickham,
and commanded herself
so far as to examine
the meaning
of every sentence.
The account
of his connection
with the Pemberley
family
was exactly what he had
related himself
and the kindness of the
late Mr.
Darcy.
Though
she had not before known
its extent, agreed
equally well
with his own words
so far,
each recital
confirmed the other.
But she came
to the will.
The difference
was great.
What Wickham had.
Said of the living
was fresh in her memory,
and as she recalled
his very words,
it was impossible
not to feel that
there was duplicity
on one side
or the other.
And for a few moments
she flattered herself
that her wishes
did not her.
But when she read
and reread
with the
closest attention,
the particulars
immediately
following of Wickham's
resigning all pretenses
to the living
of his receiving in lieu
so considerable
a sum as ?3,000.
Again, was she forced.
To hesitate?
She put down the letter,
weighed
every circumstance
with what she meant
to be impartiality
deliberated
on the probability
of each statement,
but with little success
on both sides,
it was only assertion.
Again, she read on.
But every line proved
more clearly
that the affair which
she had believed it
impossible
that any contrivance
could so represent
as to render Mr.
conduct in it
less than infamous,
was capable of a turn,
which must
make him
entirely blameless
throughout the whole.
The extravagance and.
General profligacy
which he not to lay
at Mr.
Wickham's charge,
exceedingly shocked her,
the more
so as she could
bring no proof
of its injustice.
She had never heard
of him
before his entrance
into the blank militia.
In which.
He had engaged
at the persuasion
of the young man who,
on meeting him
accidentally in town,
had there
renewed a
slight acquaintance
of his former
way of life,
I think had been known
in Hertfordshire.
What he told himself
as to his real
character
had information
been in her power.
She had never felt
a wish of inquiring.
His countenance, voice
and manner
had established him
at once
in the possession
of every virtue.
She tried to recollect
some instance
of goodness,
some undistinguished
trait of integrity
or benevolence
that might rescue him
from the attacks of Mr.
Darcy, or at least
by the predominance
of virtue, atone
for those casual errors
under which
she would endeavor
to class what Mr.
Darcy had described
as the idleness and vice
many years continuance.
But no such recollection
befriended her.
She could see
him instantly before her
and every charm of
air and address.
But she could remember
no more substantial good
than the
general approbation
of the neighborhood
and the regard
which his social powers
had gained him
in the mess.
After pausing
on this point
a considerable while,
she once more
continued to read.
But alas, the story
which followed
of his designs
on Miss Darcy received
some confirmation
from what had passed
between Colonel
Fitzwilliam herself
only the morning before,
and at last
she was referred
for the truth
of every particular
to Colonel
Fitzwilliam himself,
from whom
she had
previously received
the information
of his near concern,
all his
cousin's affairs,
and whose character
she had no
reason to question.
At one time
she had almost resolved
on applying to him.
But the idea was checked
by the awkwardness
of application
and at length, wholly
banished by
the conviction that Mr.
Darcy would
never haphazard
in such a proposal.
If he had not been well.
Assured of his cousin's
corroboration.
She perfectly remembered
everything
that had passed
in conversation
between Wickham
and herself
in their first evening
at Mr.
Phillips,
as many of
his expressions
were still fresh
in her memory.
She Was now struck
with the impropriety
of such communications
to a stranger
and wondered
it had
escaped her before
she saw the delicacy
of putting himself
forward as he had done,
and the inconsistency
of his professions
with his conduct.
She remembered
that he had boasted
of having no fear
of seeing Mr.
Darcy, that Mr.
Darcy might
leave the country,
but that he should
stand his ground.
Yet he had avoided.
The Netherfield Ball
the very next week.
She remembered also that
till the
Netherfield family
had quitted the country,
he had told his story
to no one but herself
and that
after their removal
it had been everywhere
discussed that he had
then no reserves,
no scruples
in thinking Mr.
Darcy's character,
though
he had assured her
that respect
for the father
would always prevent
his exposing the son.
How differently
did everything
now appear
in which
he was concerned?
His attentions to Ms..
King were
now the consequence
of use
solely and hatefully.
Mercenary
and the mediocrity
of her fortune
proved no longer
the motivation
of his wishes,
but his eagerness
to grasp at anything.
His behavior to herself
now have had no
tolerable motive.
He had either
been deceived
with regard
to her fortune or had
been gratifying
his vanity
by encouraging
the preference
which she believed
she had
in cautiously shown
every lingering struggle
in his favor, grew
fainter and fainter
and in farther
justification of Mr.
Darcy.
She could not
but allow Mr.
Bingley,
when questioned by Jane,
had long ago asserted
his blameless ness
in the affair that proud
and repulsive
as were his manners.
She had never
in the whole course
of their acquaintance
and acquaintance,
which had latterly
brought them
much together
and given her
a sort of intimacy
with his ways.
Seen anything that.
Betrayed him
to be unprincipled
or unjust,
anything that
spoke him of
or immoral habits
that among his
own connections,
he was esteemed
and valued.
That even Wickham.
Had allowed him
married his brother
and that she had often
heard him speak
So affectionately
of his sister
as to prove him capable
of some amiable feeling
that had his actions
being what Mr.
Wickham
represented them.
So gross violation
of everything right?
Could have been
concealed from
the world.
And that friendship
between a person
capable of it
and such an amiable man
as Mr.
Bingley
was incomprehensible.
She grew absolutely
ashamed of herself,
of neither Darcy
nor Wickham.
Could she think
without feeling
she had been blind,
partial.
Prejudiced, absurd.
How have I acted?
She cried.
I, who prided myself
in my discernment.
I have.
Valued myself in my.
Abilities,
who have often disdained
generous candor
of my sister
and gratified my vanity
in useless
or claimable mistrust.
How humiliating
is this discovery yet?
How just a humiliation.
Had I been in love,
I could not have been
more wretchedly blind.
But vanity, not love,
has been mercifully
pleased
with the preference
of one and offended
by the neglect
of the other
on the very beginning
of our acquaintance.
I have courted
repossession
and ignorance and driven
reason away where I
the were concerned.
Till this moment
I never knew myself.
From herself to Jane.
From Jane to Bingley.
Her thoughts
were in a line
which soon
brought to her
recollections Mr.
Darcy's explanation
had appeared
very insufficient.
And she read it again
widely different was the
effect of a
second perusal.
How could she
deny that
credit to his assertions
in one instance,
which she had
been obliged
to give in the other?
He declared himself
to be totally suspicious
of her
sister's attachment,
and she could not,
remembering
what Charlotte's
opinion had always been.
Neither could she deny
the justice
of his
description of Jane.
She felt that
Jane's feelings, though
fervent,
were little displayed,
and that there was
a constant complacency
in her errant manner,
not often united
with great sensibility.
When she.
Came to
that part of the letter
in which her family
were mentioned in terms
of such mortifying, yet
merited reproach.
Her sense of shame
was severe.
The justice
of the charge
struck her too
forcibly for denial
and the circumstances
to which
he particularly
alluded as having passed
at the Netherfield Ball
and as confirming
all his
first disapprobation.
Could not have.
Made a
stronger impression
on his mind
than on hers.
The compliment
to herself
and her sister
was not and felt.
It soothed.
But could not
console her
for the contempt
which had
thus been self attracted
by the
rest of her family.
And as she considered
that Jane's
disappointment
had in fact
been the work of her
nearest relations
and reflected
how materially
the credit of both
must be hurt by such
impropriety of conduct.
She felt depressed
beyond anything
she had ever known
before.
After wandering along
the lane for 2 hours,
giving way
to every variety
of thought,
to reconsidering events,
determining
probabilities
and reconciling herself
as well as she could
to a change so sudden
and so important.
Fatigue and
a recollection
of her long absence
made at length
return home.
And she entered
the house
with the wish
of appearing
cheerful as usual,
and the resolution
of repressing
such reflections
as must make her unfit
for conversation.
She was immediately.
Told that
the two gentlemen
from Rosing
that each called
during her absence, Mr.
Darcy, only for a few
minutes to take leave,
but that
Colonel Fitzwilliam
had been sitting
with them least an hour,
hoping for her
return and.
Almost.
Resolving to walk
after her
till she could be found.
Elizabeth could,
but just a concern
in missing him.
She really rejoiced it.
Colonel Fitzwilliam
was no longer an object.
She could think only
of her letter.
Chapter 37.
The two
gentlemen left roses
the next morning,
and Mr.
Collins, having been
in, waiting
near the lodges
to make them
his parting obeisance,
was able to bring home
the pleasing
intelligence
of their appearing
in very good health
and in
as tolerable spirits
as could be expected
after the melancholy
seems so lately
gone through it
rose ings to rose ings.
He then hastened
to console Lady
Catherine
and her daughter,
and on his return
brought back
with great satisfaction
a message her ladyship
importing that
she felt herself so dull
as to make her
very desirous
of having them
all to dine with her.
Elizabeth
could not see
Lady Catherine
without recollecting
that.
Had she chosen it,
she might by this time
it be presented to her
as her future niece.
Nor could she think
without a smile of
what her lady ships
indignation
would have been.
What would she said?
How would she have
behaved?
Where questions
with which
she amused herself.
Their first subject
was the diminution
of the Rose Ings party.
I assure you
I feel it exceedingly.
Said Lady Catherine.
I believe
no one feels
the loss of friends
so much as I do.
But I am particularly
attached
to these young men
and know them to be
so much to me.
They were excessively
sorry to go, but so
they always are.
The dear Colonel
rallied his spirits
tolerably till
just at last,
but Darcy
seemed to feel it
most acutely.
More, I think, than
last year.
His attachment
to Rosing certainly
increases, as.
Mr.
Collins had a compliment
and an allusion
to throw in here,
which were
kindly smiled on
by the mother
and daughter.
Lady Catherine.
After dinner
that Miss Bennett
seemed out of spirits
and immediately
accounting for it
by herself, by supposing
that she did
not like to
go home again so soon.
She added,
What if that is
the case?
You must write
to your mother
and beg that you may
stay a little longer.
Mrs.
Collins will be
very glad of
your company, I am sure.
I much obliged,
your Ladyship,
for your kind
invitation.
Replied.
Elizabeth.
But it is not in
my power.
To accept. It.
I must.
Be in town next.
Saturday.
Why?
At that rate,
you will have been here
only six weeks.
I expected you
to stay two months.
I told Mrs.
Collins, sir,
before you came.
There can be no
for your going so soon.
Mrs.
Bennett
could certainly
spare you
for another fortnight.
But my father cannot.
He wrote last week
to hurry my.
Oh, your father, of
course, may spare you
if your mother can.
Daughters are never of
so much consequence
to a father.
And If you will stay
another month complete,
it will be in my power
to take one of you
as far as London.
For I am going there
in early June
for a week.
And as Dawson does
not object
to the British box,
there would be
very good room
for one of you.
And indeed,
if the weather should
happen to be cool.
I should not object
to taking you
both as you are.
Neither of you large.
You are all
kindness, madam.
But I believe
we must abide
by our original plan.
Lady Catherine
seemed resigned.
Mrs..
You must send a
servant with them.
You know,
I always speak my mind.
And I cannot bear
the idea of
two young women
traveling
post themselves.
It is highly improper.
You must contrive
to send somebody.
I have
the greatest
dislike in the world.
That sort of thing.
Young women
should always be
properly guarded
and attended
according to
their situation in life.
When my niece Georgiana
went to Ramsgate
last summer,
I made a point of her
having to spend servants
to go with her.
Miss Darcy,
the daughter of Mr.
Darcy, of Pemberley,
and Lady Ann,
could not have appeared
with propriety
in a different manner.
I am excessively
attentive
to all those things.
You must send John
with the young
lady's Mrs.
Collins.
I am glad it occurred
to me to mention it, for
it would
really be discreditable
to you
to let them go alone.
My uncle is
to send a servant
for us?
No.
Your uncle.
He keeps a manservant,
does he?
I am very glad
you have
somebody who thinks
of these things.
Where shall you
change horses?
No, Bromley, of course.
If you mention my name
at the bell, you
will be attended to.
Lady Catherine had many
other questions to ask
respecting their journey
and how she did
not answer them
all herself.
Attention was necessary,
which Elizabeth believed
to be lucky for her,
or with a mind occupied.
She might have forgotten
where she was.
Reflection
must be reserved
for solitary hours.
Whenever she was alone,
she gave way to it
as the greatest relief
had. Not a day.
Went by
without a solitary walk.
In which
she might indulge.
In all the delight
of unpleasant
recollections.
Mr.
Darcy's letter.
She was in a fair
way, soon
knowing by heart.
She studied
every sentence,
and her feelings towards
its writer were at times
wildly different.
When she remembered
the style of
his address,
she was still
full of indignation.
But when she considered
how unjustly she had
condemned
and upbraided him,
her anger was turned
against herself,
and his disappointed
feelings became
the object of.
His attachment.
Excited.
Gratitude.
His general character.
Respect.
But she could
not approve him.
Nor could she
for a moment, repent.
Her refusal
or feel
the slightest
inclination ever
to see him again
in her own
past behavior.
There was
a constant source
of vexation and regret,
and in the unhappy
defects of her family,
a subject of yet
heavier chagrin.
They were hopeless
of remedy.
Her father, contented
with laughing at them,
would never
exert himself
to restrain
the wild giddiness
of his
youngest daughters.
And her mother,
with manners
so far
from right herself
was entirely insensible
of the evil.
Elizabeth had
frequently united
with Jane in an endeavor
to check the imprudence
of Catherine and Lydia.
But while they
were supported
by their
mother's indulgence.
What chance.
Could there be of.
Improvement?
Catherine Weak
spirited, irritable
and completely under
Lydia's guidance,
had been
always affronted
by their advice.
And Lydia,
self-willed and careless
with scarcely
giving them a hearing.
They were ignorant,
idle and vain.
While
there was
an officer on merit
and they would
flirt with him.
And while Maritain
was within
a walk of Long Bourn,
they be going there
forever.
Anxiety on Jane's behalf
was another
prevailing concern.
Had Mr.
Darcy's explanation
by restoring Bingley
to all her former good.
Opinion heightened
the sense.
Of what Jane had lost.
His affection was proved
to have been sincere
and his conduct
cleared of all blame.
Alas, Annie could attach
the implicit ness
of his confidence
in his friend.
How grievous
then, was the thought
that of a situation
so desirable
in every respect,
so replete
with advantage,
so promising
for happiness.
Jane had been deprived
by the folly and decorum
of her own family.
When to
these recollections
was added.
The development
of Wickham's character.
It may be easily
believed that
the happy spirits,
which had seldom
been depressed before,
were now
so much affected
as to make it
almost impossible
for her to
appear tolerably
cheerful.
Their engagements at
Rose things were less
frequent
during the last
week of her
stay as they had
been at first.
The very last evening
was spent there.
At Her Ladyship again
inquired, minutely
into the particulars
of their journey,
gave them directions
as to the best
method of packing,
and was so urgent
on the necessity
of placing gowns
in the only right way
that Mariah herself
obliged on her return
to undo all the work
of the morning
and pack her
trunk afresh
when they parted.
Lady Catherine,
with great
condescension.
Wished them a.
Good journey
and invited them
to come to Hunt's
Fort again next year.
And Mr.
Burke exerted herself
so far as to curtsy
and hold out her hand
to both.
Chapter 38.
On Saturday
morning,
Elizabeth and Mr.
Collins met
for breakfast
a few minutes
before the others
appeared,
and he the opportunity
of paying
the parting civilities
which he
deemed indispensable if
necessary.
I know not,
Miss Elizabeth.
Said he.
Whether Mrs.
Collins has yet
expressed her
sense of your kindness
in coming to us.
But I am very certain
you will not
leave the house
without receiving her.
Thanks for it.
The favor of
your company
has been much felt.
I assure you.
We know how little
there is to tempt anyone
to our humble abode.
Our plain manner
of living,
our small rooms
and few domestics.
And the little we see of
the world
must make dunsford
extremely dull
to a young lady
like yourself.
But I hope you will
believe us.
Grateful
for the condescension
and that we have
done everything
in our power
to prevent you spending
your time unpleasantly.
Elizabeth was
eager with her
thanks and assurances
of happiness.
She had spent.
Six weeks
with great enjoyment.
And the.
Pleasure of being
with Charlotte
and the kind attention
she had received
must make her feel
the obliged.
Mr.
Collins was gratified
and with a more smiling
solemnity, replied.
It me
the greatest
pleasure to hear
that you have passed
your time
not disagreeable.
We have certainly done
our best and most
fortunately,
having it in our power
to introduce you
to very superior
and from our connection
with Rose things,
the frequent means
of varying
the humble home scene.
I think we may flatter
ourselves
that your Hansford
visit cannot
have been
entirely irksome.
Our situation
with regard to Lady
Katharine's
family is indeed
the sort
of extraordinary
advantage and
blessing which
few can boast.
You see on
what a footing we are,
you see how continually
we are engaged there.
In truth,
I must acknowledge that
with all
the disadvantages
of this
humble parsonage,
I should not think
anyone abiding in
it is an object
of compassion
while they are sharers
of our intimacy,
it rose King's.
Words were insufficient
for the elevation
of his feelings,
and he was obliged
to walk about the room
while Elizabeth tried
to unite civility
and truth in a few short
sentences.
You may,
in fact, carry
a very favorable
report of us
into Hertfordshire.
My dear cousin,
I flatter myself.
At least
that you will be able
to do so.
Lady Katherine's
great attentions to Mrs.
Collins.
You have been a daily
witness of
and altogether, I trust
it does not appear
that your friend has
drawn an unfortunate.
But on this
point it will be
as well Be silent only.
Let me assure you,
my dear Miss Elizabeth,
that I can from
my heart
most cordially wish
you equal Felicity
in marriage.
My Dear
Charlotte and I have
but one mind
and one way of thinking.
There is,
in everything,
a most remarkable
resemblance of character
and ideas between us.
We seem
to have been designed
for each other.
Elizabeth could
safely say
that it was a
great happiness
where that.
Was the case
and with equal.
Sincerity, could add
that she firmly.
Believed and rejoiced.
In his
domestic comforts.
She was not sorry,
however, to have
the recital of them
interrupted by the lady
from whom they sprang.
Poor Charlotte.
It was.
Melancholy
to leave her to such.
Society.
But she had chosen. It
with her eyes open.
And.
Though
evidently regretting
that her visitors were.
To go, she did not seem.
To ask for compassion.
Her home
and her
housekeeping, her parish
and her poultry
and all their dependent
concerns.
Had not yet.
Lost their charms.
At length, the
chairs arrived.
The trunks were
fastened on the parcels
placed within,
and it was pronounced
to be ready
after an affectionate
parting between
the friends.
Elizabeth was attended
to the carriage by Mr.
Collins,
and as they walked down
the garden,
he was commissioning her
with his best respects
to all her family,
not forgetting his
thanks for the kindness
he had received
long in the winter
and his compliments
to Mr. and Mrs.
Gardner, though unknown.
He then handed her in.
Maria followed
and the door
was on the point
of being closed.
When.
He suddenly
reminded them with some.
Consternation,
that they.
Had hitherto
forgotten to leave
any message
for the ladies
at Rosen's.
But he added.
You will,
of course,
wish to have
your humble respects
to them
with your grateful
thanks for their
kindness to you while
you have been here.
Elizabeth made
no objection.
The door was
then allowed to be shut
and the carriage
drove off.
Good gracious!
Cried Maria,
after a few
minute's silence.
It seems,
but a day or two
since we first came.
And yet how many things
have happened?
A great many indeed.
Said her companion
with a sigh.
We have died
nine times at roses.
Besides drinking tea.
That twice.
How much?
I shall to tell.
Elizabeth
added privately,
and how much
I shall have to conceal.
Their journey
was performed
without much
conversation
or any alarm.
And within 4 hours
of their leading
Hunt's herd,
they reached Mr.
Gardiner's house,
where they were
to remain a few days.
Jane looked
well and Elizabeth
had little opportunity
studying her spirits
amidst the
various engagements
which the kindness of
her aunt
had preserved for them.
But Jane was to go home
with her,
and at Long Bourne,
there would be leisure
enough for observation.
It was not.
Without an effort,
meanwhile,
that she could wait
even for long.
Born before
she told her
sister of Mr.
Darcy's proposals.
To know.
That she had
the power of revealing
what would
so exceedingly
astonish Jane.
And must.
At the same time
so highly gratify
whatever of her
own vanity.
She had not yet
been able to reason away
with such a temptation
to openness, as nothing
could have conquer
to the state
of indecision
which she remained
as to the extent of what
she should communicate
and her fear
if she once entered
on the subject
of being hurried
into repeating
of Bingley,
which might only grieve
her sister further.
Chapter 39.
It was the
second week in
May in which
the three young ladies
set out together
from Grace Church Street
for the Town of Blank
in.
And as they drew near
the appointed inn
where Mr.
Bennett's carriage
was to meet them,
they quickly perceived
in token of the coachman
punctuality.
Both Kitty and Lydia
looking out
of a dining
room upstairs.
These two girls
had been above
an hour in the place,
happily employed
in visiting
an opposite milliner,
watching the Sentinel
on guard and dressing
salad and cucumber.
After welcoming
their sisters,
they triumphantly
displayed a table
set out
with such cold meat
as an in larder
usually affords,
exclaiming.
If not, this nice.
Is not this
an agreeable surprise?
And we mean
to treat to all?
Added Lydia.
But you must lend us
the money.
We have just spent hours
at the shop there.
Then showing her
purchases.
Look here.
I have bought
this bonnet.
I do not think
it is very pretty.
But I thought
I might as well buy.
It is not.
I shall put it to pieces
as soon as I get home
and see
if I can make it.
Up any better.
And when her sisters
abused it as ugly,
she added
with perfect unconcern.
Oh, but they were two
or three
much uglier in the shop.
And when I
bought some prettier
colored satin
to trim it with fresh.
I think
it would be
very tolerable.
Besides, it
will not much signify
what one wears.
This summer.
After the
have left Merton
and they are going
in a fortnight.
Are they indeed?
Cried Elizabeth,
with the
greatest satisfaction.
They are going to
be encamped
near Brighton,
and I do so want
Papa to.
Take us all there
for the summer.
It would be
such a delicious scheme
and I daresay
it would cost.
Hardly anything.
At all.
Mama would like to go to
of all things.
Only think
what a miserable else
we shall have.
Yes, thought Elizabeth.
That would be
a delightful scheme
indeed.
And completely
do for us at once.
Good heaven, Brighton
and a co camp
full of soldiers to us
who have been
overstretched already
by one poor
regiment of militia
and the monthly bulls
of Meriton.
Now, I have got
some news for you.
Said Lydia,
as they sat
down at table.
What do you think?
It is excellent news,
capital news.
And about a.
Certain person
we all like.
Jane and Elizabeth
looked at each other
and the waiter was told
he need not stay.
Lydia laughed
and said hi.
That is just like
your formality
and discretion.
You thought the
waiter must not here
as if he cared.
I daresay
he often has worse
things said than
I am going to say.
But he is an
ugly fellow.
I am glad he's gone.
I never saw such
long chin in my life.
Well,
but now for my news.
It is about Dear
Wickham.
Too good for the waiter,
is it not?
There is no danger
of Wickens
marrying Mary King.
There is for you.
She is gone
down to her uncle
at Liverpool.
Gone to stay.
Wickham is safe
and Mary.
King is safe.
Added Elizabeth safe
from a connection.
Imprudent as to fortune.
She is grateful
for going away if.
She liked.
Him.
But I hope there's
no strong attachment
on either
side, said Jane.
I am sure
there is not on his.
I will answer for it.
You never
catch three
straws about her
who could about such
a nasty, freckled
little thing.
Elizabeth
was shocked to think
that, however incapable
of such coarseness
of expression herself,
the coarseness
of the sentiment
was little other
than her
own breasted
harbored and
fancy liberal.
As soon as all had eight
and the elder ones paid.
The carriage was ordered
and after
some contrivance
the whole party
with all their
boxes, work
bags and parcels
and the
unwelcome additions
of Kitty
and Lydia's purchases
were seated in it.
How nicely
we were all crammed.
In, cried Lydia.
I am glad I bought
my bonnet.
If it is only for.
The fun
of having
another band box.
Well, now
let us be
quite comfortable
and snug
and talk and laugh
all the way home.
And in the first place,
let us hear
what has happened to you
all since she went away.
Have you seen.
Any pleasant men?
Have you had
any flirting?
I was in great hopes
that one of you
have got a husband
before you came back.
Jane will be quite
an old maid soon,
I declare.
She's almost in 20.
Lord, how ashamed
I should be
of not being married
before three and 20
by Aunt
Philips wants you.
So to get husbands,
you can't think.
She says.
Lizzie,
it better have taken Mr.
Collins,
but I do not think
it would have been
any fun in it.
Lord, how
I should like
to be married
before any of you.
And then I
would chaperon
you about to
all the balls.
Dear me,
we had such a good.
Piece of fun
the other day.
It kind of.
Forced us, Kitty and me,
to spend the day there.
And Mrs.
Foster promised
to have a little dance
in the evening by the.
By Mrs.
Foster me
as such friends.
And so she asked the two
Harringtons to come.
But Harriet was ill,
and so Pen was forced
to come by herself.
And then what
do you think we did?
We dressed up
Shamblin and women's
clothes on purpose
to pass for a lady only.
Think What fun.
Not a soul knew of it,
but kind of.
Mrs.
Foster and Kitty had me,
except my aunt.
We were forced to borrow
one of her gowns.
And you cannot
imagine how
well he looked
when Danny and Wickham
and Pratt
and two or three
more of the men came in.
They did not know him
in the least.
Lord, how I laughed.
And so did Mrs.
Foster.
I thought
I should have died.
And that made
the men
suspect something.
And then they soon
found out what
was the matter
with.
Such kind of histories
and their parties
and good jokes.
Did Lydia, assisted
by Kitty's hints
and additions,
endeavored
to amuse her companions
all the way too long
born.
Elizabeth listened
as little as she could,
but there was
no escaping
the frequent mention
of Wickham's name.
They reception
at home was most kind.
Mrs.
Bennett rejoiced
to see Jane
in undiminished beauty.
And.
More than once
during dinner, did Mr.
Bennett say voluntarily
to Elizabeth.
I am glad you are.
Come back, Lizzy.
Their party
in the dining room
was large
for almost all.
Lucas's came
to meet Mariah
and hear the news,
and various were
the subjects
that occupied them.
Lady Lucas
was inquiring of Mariah
after the welfare
and poultry
of her eldest daughter.
Mrs.
Bennett
was doubly engaged
on the one hand,
collecting an account
of the present
fashions from Jane,
who sat some way
below her
and on the other,
retailing them
all to the younger
Lucas's and Lydia,
in a voice rather louder
than any other
persons, was enumerating
the various pleasures
of the morning
to anybody
who would hear her.
Oh, Mary, said she.
I wish.
She had gone with us.
We had such fun
as we went along
kitty night
you up the blinds and.
Pretended
there was nobody.
In the couch.
And I should have gone
to all the way
if Kitty
had not been sick.
And When we got
to the George,
I do think we behaved
very handsomely.
If we treated
the other three
with the nicest cold
luncheon in the world.
And if you would
have gone,
we would have
treated you too.
And then we came away
with such.
I thought we never
should have got
into the couch.
I was ready to die
of laughter.
And then we were.
So merry
all the way home.
We talked
and laughed so loud
that anybody
might have heard it
ten miles off
to this.
Mary very gravely
replied.
Far be it
from me, my dear sister,
To depreciate
such pleasures,
they would be congenial
with the.
Generality of
female minds.
But I confess
they would
have no charms.
For me,
I should infinitely.
Prefer. A book.
But at his answer,
Lydia heard not a word.
She seldom
listened to anybody
for more than
half a minute
and never attended
to Mary at all.
In the afternoon.
Lydia was urgent,
but the rest
of the girls
to walk to Maritain
and to see
how everybody went on.
But Elizabeth steadily
opposed the scheme.
It should not.
Be said that
the Miss Bennetts
could not be at home
half a day
before they were
in pursuit
of the officers.
There was
another reason, too,
for her opposition.
She dreaded seeing Mr.
Wickham again
and was resolved
to avoid it
as long as possible.
The comfort to her
of the regiment's
approaching
removal was indeed
beyond expression.
In a fortnight
they were to go,
and once gone
she hoped
there could be
nothing more to
plague her.
On his account.
She had not been.
Many hours
at home before.
She found that
the Brighton scheme,
of which Lydia
had given them a hint at
the end,
was under frequent
discussion
between her parents.
Elizabeth saw directly
that her father
had not the smallest.
Intention of yielding.
But his answers
were at the same time
so vague and equivocal
that her mother, though
often disheartened,
had never yet despaired
of succeeding.
At last.
Chapter 40.
Elizabeth's
impatience
to acquaint Jane
with what had happened
could no longer
be overcome
and at length resolving
to suppress
every particular
in which
her sister was concerned
and preparing her
to be surprised
she related to her.
The next morning,
the chief of the scene
between Mr.
Darcy and herself.
Miss.
Bennett's astonishment,
was seen lessened
by the strong
sisterly partiality
which made
any admiration
of Elizabeth appear
perfectly natural,
and all surprise
was shortly lost
other feelings.
She was sorry that Mr.
Darcy should have
delivered his sentiments
in a manner
so little suited
to recommend them.
But still more.
Was she
grieved for
the unhappiness
which her sister's
refusal must
have given him?
His being so sure
of succeeding was wrong,
said she,
and certainly ought
not to have appeared.
But consider how much
it must increase
his disappointment.
Indeed,
replied Elizabeth.
I am heartily
sorry for him, but he.
Has other feelings
which will.
Probably soon drive away
his regard for me.
You do not blame me,
however,
for refusing him
blame you?
Oh, no.
But you blame me
for having spoken
so warmly of Wickham?
No, I not know
that you were wrong
in saying what you did.
But he will know it
when I tell you
what happened
the very next day.
She then spoke
of the letter,
repeating the whole
its contents
as far as
they concerned.
George Wickham.
What a stroke.
Was this for?
Poor Jane.
Who would willingly
have gone
through the world
without believing
that so much wickedness
existed in?
The whole
race of mankind,
as it was
here, collected
in one individual.
Nor was Darcy's
vindication, though
grateful to her feelings
capable of consoling her
for such discovery.
Most earnestly,
did she labor
to prove
the probability of error
and seek to clear
the one
without involving
the other.
This will not do,
said Elizabeth.
You will never be able
to make both of them
good for anything.
Take your choice.
But she must be
satisfied with only one.
There is
but such a quantity
of merit between them.
Just enough to make one
good sort of man.
And of late,
it has been shifting
about pretty much
my part.
I am inclined
to believe it all.
Darcy's.
But you shall do
you choose.
It was some time,
however, before a smile
could be extorted
from Jane.
I do not know.
And I've been more
shocked, said she.
We can very bad.
It is almost past
belief.
And poor Mr.
Darcy.
Dear Lizzie only.
Consider what
he must have suffered
such a disappointment.
And with the knowledge
of your ill opinion too.
And having to
relate such
a thing of his sister.
It is really
too distressing.
I am sure you must
feel it so how?
No.
My regret
and compassion
are all done away
by seeing you
so full of both.
I know you will do him
such ample justice
that I am going
every moment
more unconcerned,
indifferent.
Your profusion
makes me saving.
And if you lay.
Bent to him much longer,
my heart will be
as light as a feather.
Poor Wickham.
There is an expression
of goodness
in his countenance.
Such an openness
and gentleness
in his manner.
There
certainly was
some great.
Mismanagement
in the education
of those two young.
One has got
all the goodness
and the other will
the appearance of it.
I never thought Mr.
Darcy
so deficient
in the appearance of it
as you used to do.
And yet
I to be
uncommonly clever
in taking so.
Decided dislike to him
without any.
Reason.
It is such a spur
to one's genius,
such an opening for wit
to have.
A dislike of that.
Kind.
One may be.
Continually abusive.
Without saying.
Anything just
but one cannot be.
Always laughing at a man
without now and then.
Stumbling on
something witty.
Lizzie,
when you first read
that letter,
I am sure you could
not treat.
The matter as you do.
Now.
Indeed,
I could not.
I was uncomfortable
enough.
I may say unhappy
and with no one
to speak to
about what I felt.
No, Jane.
To comfort me
and say
that I had not been
so very weak and vain
and nonsensical
as I knew I had.
Oh, how I wanted you.
How unfortunate that you
should have used her
very strong expressions
in speaking of Wickham
to Mr. Darcy.
But now they do appear
so wholly undeserved.
Certainly.
But the misfortune of.
Speaking.
With bitterness
is the most
natural consequence
of the.
Prejudices I had.
Encouraging.
There's one point on
which I want
your advice.
I want to be told
whether I ought
or ought not to make
our acquaintance
in general.
Understand Wickham's.
Miss Bennet
paused a little
and then replied.
Surely
there can be no occasion
for exposing him
so dreadfully.
What is your opinion
that it ought
not to be attempted?
Mr.
Darcy has not
authorized me
to make his.
Communication.
Public.
On the contrary,
every particular.
Relative to
his sister
was meant be kept.
As much as
possible to myself.
And if I endeavor
to, one deceive.
People
as to the rest of.
His conduct,
who will believe me?
The general.
Prejudice against Mr..
Darcy.
So violent
that it would be
the death of half
the good people
in Meriden
to attempt
to place him
in an amiable light.
I am not equal to it.
Wickham will soon
be gone.
And therefore,
it will not.
Signify
anyone here what.
He really is.
Sometime hence,
it will all
be found out.
And then make me laugh
at that stupidity
and not
knowing it before.
At present, I will say
nothing about it.
You are quite right.
To have his errors made
public
might ruin him forever.
He is now perhaps
sorry for what
he has done and anxious.
To reestablish.
Character.
We must
not make him desperate.
The tumult of
Elizabeth's mind
was allayed
by this conversation.
She had got rid of
two of the secrets
which had weighed on her
for a fortnight
and was certain
of a willing
listener in Jane
whenever she might wish
to talk again of either.
But there was
still something
lurking behind,
of which prudence
forbade the disclosure.
She dared not
relate the other
half of Mr.
Darcy's letter,
nor explain
to her sister
how sincerely
she'd been valued
by her friend.
Here was knowledge
in which no one could,
and she was sensible
that nothing less
than a perfect
understanding
between the parties
could justify her
and throwing off
this last
encumbrance of mystery.
And then said she,
if that very
improbable event.
Should ever take place.
I shall merely
be able to tell what.
Bingley may tell
in a much more agreeable
manner. Himself.
The liberty
of communication
be mine till it has
lost all its value.
She was now.
On being settled at home
at leisure,
to observe
the real state
of her sister's spirits.
Jane was not happy.
She still cherished
a very tender affection
for Bingley, having
never even
fancied herself
in love before.
Her regard at all
the warmth of
first attachment,
and from her age
and disposition
greater steadiness
than most.
First attachments
often boast.
And so fervently did
she value
his remembrance
and prefer him
to every other man
that her good sense
and all her attention
to the feelings
of her friends
were requisite to check
the indulgence
of those regrets,
which must have
been injurious
to her own health
and their tranquility.
Well, as he said, Mrs.
Bennet, one day,
what is your opinion.
Now of the sad
business of Jane's?
For my part,
I am determined
never to speak
of it again to anybody.
I my sister Philip.
So the other day.
But I cannot find out
the chains
or anything of him
in London.
Well, he's
a very undeserving
young man,
and I do not suppose
there is
the least chance
in the world
for ever
getting him now.
There is no talk of you
coming to
Netherfield again
in the summer,
and I've inquired
of everybody to.
Who is likely to know.
I do not
believe you will
ever live at Netherfield
any more.
Oh, well, just.
Just as he chooses.
Nobody wants him
to come.
Though
I shall always say
he used my daughter
extremely ill.
And if I was her,
I would not have
put up with it.
Well,
I comfort, as I am sure
Jane will
die of a broken heart.
And then
he would be sorry
for what he has done.
But Elizabeth
could not receive
comfort from.
Such expectation,
and she.
Made no answer.
Well, Lizzie.
Continued her mother
soon afterwards.
So the Collins is
very comfortable.
Do they? Well.
Well I only
hope it will last.
And what
sort of table do
they keep?
Charlotte is an
excellent manager,
I daresay.
If she is half as sharp
as her mother,
she is saving enough.
There's
nothing extravagant
in their housekeeping,
I daresay.
No, nothing at all.
A great deal
of good management
depend upon it.
Yes. Yes.
They will take care
to outrun their income.
They will
never be distressed
for money.
Well, much good.
May it do them.
And so I suppose
they often talk
of having no known born
when your father
is dead.
They look upon it
quite as their own,
I dare
say, whenever
that happens.
It was a subject which
they could not mention
before me.
No,
it would have
been strange
if they had.
But I make no doubt
they often talk of it
between themselves.
Well,
if they can be easy
with an estate
that is not
lawfully their own.
So much the better.
I should be ashamed
of having one
that was only
entailed on me.
Chapter 41
The first week
of their return
was soon gone.
The second began.
It was the last
of the regiment
stay in Meriton
and all the young ladies
in the neighborhood
were drooping apace.
The dejection was
almost universal.
The elder Miss Bennetts
alone were still able
to eat, drink and sleep
and pursue
the usual course
of their employments
very frequently.
Were they reproached
for this insensibility
by, Kitty and Lydia,
whose own
misery was extreme,
and who could
not comprehend such hard
heartedness
in any of the family?
Good heavens.
What is to become us?
What are we to do?
What they often exclaim
in the
bitterness of woe.
How can you be
so smiling?
Lizzie?
Their affectionate
mother, shared
all their grief.
She remembered
what she had herself
endured on
a similar occasion five
and 20 years ago.
I am sure, said she.
I cried for two together
when Colonel
Miller's regiment
went away.
I thought I should have
broken my heart.
I am sure I shall break.
Mine, said Lydia.
If could but
go to Brighton.
Observed Mrs.
Bennett.
Oh, yes,
if one could but
go to Brighton.
But Papa is
so disagreeable.
Her little sea bathing,
which set me up forever.
And my Aunt Philips
is sure it would do me
a great deal of good.
Added Kitty.
Such were
the kind of lamentations
resounding perpetually
through long born house.
Elizabeth tried
to be diverted by them,
but all sense
of pleasure was lost
and shame.
She felt anew
the justice of Mr.
Darcy's objections
and never had
she been so
much disposed to pardon
his interference
in the views
of his friend.
But the gloom.
Of Lydia's prospect
was shortly
cleared away, for.
She received an.
Invitation from Mrs.
Forster,
the wife of the colonel
of the regiment.
To.
Accompany her
to Brighton.
This invaluable friend
was a very young woman
and very lately married.
A resemblance
in good humor and good
spirits had recommended
her and Lydia
to each other.
And out of their
three months
acquaintance,
they had been.
Intimate to.
The rapture of Lydia
on this occasion.
Her adoration of Mrs.
Foster,
the delight of Mrs.
Bennett and the.
Mortification of Kitty.
Are, scarcely
to be described
wholly inattentive
to her
sister's feelings.
Lydia flew
about the house
in restless ecstasy,
calling for everyone's
congratulations
and to laughing
and talking
with more violence
than ever.
Whilst the luckless
kitty continued
in the parlor,
we refined at her
fate, in terms
as unreasonable
as her accent
was peevish.
I cannot see why Mrs.
Foster should not ask me
as well as Lydia,
said she,
though I am not
a particular friend.
I have just
as much right
to be asked as she has
and more to for
I am two years older.
In vain
did Elizabeth attempt
to make her reasonable
and Jane
to make her resigned as?
For Elizabeth herself?
This invitation
was so far
from exciting in her
the same feelings
as in her mother
and Lydia
that she considered it
as the death warrant
of all possibility
of common
sense for latter
and detestable as such,
a step
must make her
worth known.
She could not
help secretly
advising her father
not to let her go.
She represented to him
all the improprieties
of Lydia's
general behavior,
the little advantage
she could derive
from the friendship
of such a woman as Mrs.
Foster
and the probability
of her
being yet more imprudent
with such a companion
at Brighton,
where the temptations
must be
greater than at home.
He heard her attentively
and then said.
Lydia will never be easy
until she has
exposed herself
some public
place or other, and
we can never
expect it to do it
with so little expense
or inconvenience
to her family.
As under the
present circumstances.
If you were aware.
Said Elizabeth.
Of the
very great disadvantage
to us all,
which must arise.
From the public
notice of Lydia's.
Unguarded
and imprudent manner
nay, which has
already arisen from it.
I am sure you would
judge differently
in this affair
already arisen.
Repeated Mr.
Bennett.
What has she
frightened away
some of your lovers?
Poor little Lizzie.
But do not be cast down.
Such squeamish
youths as cannot bear
to be connected
with a little absurdity
and not worth a regret.
Come,
let me see
the list of the
pitiful fellows
who have been kept
aloof by Lydia's folly.
Indeed,
you are mistaken.
I have no such
injuries to resent.
It Is not of particular,
but of general evils,
which I am now
complaining.
Our importance,
our respectability
in the world
must be affected.
By the wild.
Volatility,
the assurance
and disdain
of all restraint.
Which marks
Lydia's character.
Excuse me for I
must speak plainly.
If you, my dear father,
will not
take the trouble
of checking her
exuberant spirits
and of teaching her
that her
present pursuits
are not to be
to the business
of her life,
she will soon be beyond
the reach of amendment.
Her character
will be fixed,
and she will, at 16,
be the most
determined flirt
that ever made herself
or her family
ridiculous.
A flat
to in the worst
and meanest
degree of flirtation.
Without any attraction
beyond youth
and a tolerable person.
And from the ignorance
and emptiness
of her mind,
wholly unable
to ward off any portion
of that
universal contempt
which her rage
for admiration
will excite.
And this danger, Kitty,
also is comprehended.
She will follow
wherever lady leads
vain, ignorant,
idle and, Absolutely
uncontrolled.
Oh, my dear
father,
can you suppose it
possible
that they will
not be censured
and despised.
Wherever they are known.
And that their sisters
will not be often
involved in
the disgrace?
Mr.
Bennett saw that her
whole heart
was in the subject
and affectionately
taking her
hand, said in reply.
Do not make yourself
uneasy, my love.
Wherever you and
Jane are known,
you must be respected
and valued
and you will not appear
to less advantage
for having a couple of
or I may say three
very silly sisters.
We shall have no peace
at long bonnets.
Lydia does not
go to Brighton.
Let her go then.
Colonel
Foster is a sensible
man and will
keep her out
of any real mischief.
And she is luckily
too poor
to be an object of prey
to anybody at Brighton.
She will be of
less importance,
even as a common flirt,
than she has been here.
The officers will find
women
better worth
their notice.
Let us hope, therefore,
that her being there
may teach her
her own insignificance.
At any rate,
she cannot grow
many degrees worse
without authorizing us
to lock her up
for the rest
of her life.
With this answer,
Elizabeth was forced
to be content.
But her own
continued the same,
and she left him
disappointed and sorry
it was not
in her nature, however,
to increase
her vexations
by dwelling on them.
She was.
Confident of having
performed her.
Duty.
And to fret over
unavoidable evils
or augment them
by anxiety.
Was no.
Part of her disposition.
Had Lydia and her
mother known
the substance
of her conference
with their father,
their indignation
would hardly
have found expression
in their united ability
in Lydia's imagination.
A visit to Brighton
comprised
every possibility
of earthly happiness.
She saw
with the creative
eye of fancy
the streets of that gay
bathing. Place.
Covered with officers.
She saw herself object.
Of attention
to tens and.
Scores of them
at present, unknown.
She saw all
the glories of the camp,
its tents
stretched forth
and beauteous
uniformity lines
crowded with the young
and the gay
and dazzling
with scarlet.
And to complete the.
View, she saw herself
seated beneath a tent.
Tenderly flirting
with at least
six officers at once.
Had she known, her
sister
sought to tear her
from such prospects
and such realities
as these.
What would have.
Been her.
Sensations?
They could have
been only understood
by her mother,
who might have felt
nearly the same.
Lydia is going to
Brighton was all that
consoled her for her
melancholy conviction
of her husband's
never intending
to go there himself.
But they were entirely
ignorant of
what had passed,
and their
raptures continued
with little intermission
to the very day of
Lydia's leaving home.
Elizabeth was
now to see Mr.
Wickham
for the last time,
having been frequently
in company with him
since her return.
Agitation
was pretty well
over the agitations
formal partiality
entirely, so.
She had.
Even learned to detect
in the very gentleness
which had first
delighted her
an affectation
and a sameness
to disgust and weary
in his present
behavior to herself.
Moreover,
she had a fresh source
of displeasure
for the inclination.
He soon testified
of renewing
those intentions,
which had marked
the early part of their
could only serve
after what
had since passed.
To provoke her,
she lost
all concern
for him
in finding herself
thus selected
as the object
of such idle
and frivolous gallantry.
And while she
steadily repressed.
It could not.
But feel the reproof
contained
in his believing
that however long
and for whatever cause
his attentions
had been withdrawn, her
vanity would
be gratified
and her preference
secured at any time
by their renewal.
On the very last
day of the regiment's
remaining at Meriton,
he dined
with the other officers
at Long Bourn,
and so little was
Elizabeth disposed apart
from him in good humor
that on his making
some inquiry
as to the manner
in which her time
had passed at
Hunt's effort,
she mentioned Colonel
Fitzwilliams and Mr.
Darcy's having
both spent
three weeks at Raisings
and asked him
if he was acquainted
with the former.
He looked surprised,
displeased,
alarmed.
But with a.
Moment's recollection
and a returning smile,
replied
that he had formerly
seen him often,
and after observing
that he was a very
gentleman like man,
asked her
how she had liked him.
Her answer was
warmly in his favor
with an air
of indifference.
He soon
afterwards added.
How long did you say
that he was at Rosing?
Nearly three.
And you saw
him frequently?
Yes, almost
every day.
His manners are
very different
from his cousins.
Yes, very different.
But I think Mr.
Darcy improves upon
acquaintance.
Indeed.
Cried Mr.
Wickham with a look
which did not
escape her.
And pray.
May I?
But checking himself,
he added
in a gay or tone.
Is it in address
that he improves?
Has he deigned to add
aught of civility
to his ordinary style?
For I dare not hope.
He continued in a lower
and more serious tone.
That he has improved
in essentials.
Oh, no,
said Elizabeth.
In essentials,
I believe
he is very much
what ever was.
While she spoke,
Wickham.
Looked as if scarcely
knowing
whether to rejoice
over her words
or to
distrust their meaning.
There was a something
in her countenance
made him
listen
with an apprehensive
and anxious attention.
While she added,
When I said that
he improved
on acquaintance,
I did not mean that
his mind or his.
Manners were
in a state of.
Improvement,
but that from
knowing him better,
his disposition was
better understood.
Wickham's alarm
now appeared
in a heightened
complexion
and agitated look.
For a few.
Minutes.
He was silent
till shaking off
his embarrassment.
He turned to her again
and said in the gentlest
of accents.
You who so well know
feelings towards Mr.
Darcy,
will readily comprehend
how sincerely
I must rejoice
that he is wise enough
to assume
even the appearance
of what is right.
His pride
in that direction
may be of service,
if not to himself,
to many others,
for it must deter him
from such
foul misconduct
as I have suffered by.
I only fear that
the sort of cautiousness
to which you, I imagine,
have been eluding
is merely adopted
on his visits
to his aunt,
of whose good opinion
and judgment
stands much in awe.
His fear of
her has always operated.
I know when
they were together
and a good deal
is to be imputed
to his wish of
forwarding the match
with Mr. Borg,
which I am certain
he has very
much at heart.
Elizabeth could
not repress
a smile at this,
but she answered.
Only by a
inclination of the head.
She saw that he wanted
to engage her
on the old subject
of his grievances,
and she was in no humor
to indulge him.
The rest of the evening
passed the appearance
on his side
of usual cheerfulness,
but with
no further attempt
to distinguish
Elizabeth.
And they parted at last
with mutual civility.
And.
Possibly mutual desire
of never meeting again.
When the party broke up,
Lydia returned with Mrs.
Forrester to Maritain.
From whence
they were to
set out early
the next morning.
The separation
between her
and her family
was rather noisy
than pathetic.
Kitty was the only
one who shed tears.
But she did.
Weep from vexation
and envy.
Mrs.
Bennett was diffused
in her good wishes
for the Felicity
of her daughter
and impressive
in her injunctions
that she should not
miss the opportunity
of enjoying herself
as much as possible.
Advice
which there was
reason to believe
would be
well attended to
and in the
clamorous happiness
of Lydia herself
in bidding farewell.
The more gentle ideas
of her sisters
were uttered
without being heard.
Chapter 42.
Had Elizabeth's opinion
been all drawn
from her own family?
She could not
have formed
a very pleasing
opinion of conjugal
felicity or
domestic comfort.
Her father captivated
by youth and beauty
and that appearance
of good humor,
which youth
and beauty
generally give,
had married a woman
whose weak understanding
and a liberal mind
had very early
in their marriage,
put an end
to all real affection
for her.
Respect, esteem
and confidence
had vanished forever.
And all his views.
Of domestic
happiness
were overthrown.
But Mr.
Bennett was not
of a disposition
to seek comfort
for the disappointment
which his own imprudence
brought on
in any of
those pleasures,
which too often consoled
the unfortunate
for their folly
or their vice.
He was fond
of the country
and of books,
and from these tastes
arisen
his principal
enjoyments.
To his wife.
He was very little
otherwise indebted
then, as her ignorance
and folly
had contributed.
To his amusement.
This is not.
The sort of happiness
which a man would
in general
a wish to
owe to his wife,
but where
other powers
of entertainment
are wanting.
The true philosopher
will derive benefit from
such as are given.
Elizabeth, however,
had never
been blind
to the impropriety
of her father's
behavior.
As a husband.
She had always seen it
with pain.
But respecting
his abilities
and grateful
for his affectionate
treatment of herself.
She endeavored to forget
what she could
not overlook
and to banish
from her thoughts
that continual breach
of conjugal obligation
and decorum.
Which, in.
Exposing his wife
to the contempt
of her own
children,
was so
highly reprehensible.
But she had never.
Felt so strongly
as now the disadvantages
which must attend
the children
of so unsuitable
a marriage,
nor ever been
so fully aware
of the evils
arising from
so ill judged
a direction
of talents, talents
which rightly used
might at
least have preserved
the respectability
of his daughters.
Even.
If incapable
of enlarging the mind of
his wife.
When Elizabeth
had rejoiced
over Wickens departure,
she found
little other cause
for satisfaction
and the
loss of the regiment.
Their parties abroad
were less
varied than before.
And at home
she had a mother
and sister
whose constantly
at the dullness
of everything
around them.
Threw a.
Real gloom
over their
domestic circle.
And though
Kitty might in time
regain her
natural degree of sense,
since the disturbance
her brain were removed,
her other sister
from whose
disposition greater evil
might be apprehended,
was likely
to be hardened
in all her folly
and assurance by.
A situation of double.
Danger
as a watering place
and a. Camp.
Upon the whole.
Therefore, she.
Found
what has been
sometimes found
before that an event
to which
she had been
looking forward
with impatient desire,
did not in taking place,
bring all the
satisfaction
she had
promised herself.
It was consequently
necessary
to name some other
for the commencement
of actual Felicity
to have some other point
on which her wishes
and hopes
might be fixed,
and by again enjoying
the pleasure
of anticipation console
for the present
and prepare for
another disappointment.
Her tour to the Lakes
was now
the object of her
happiest thoughts.
It was
the best consolation
all the
uncomfortable hours
which the discontented
ness of her mother
and Kitty
made inevitable.
And could she
have included
Jane in the scheme?
Every part of it
would have been perfect.
But it is fortunate,
thought she,
that I have something
to wish for where
the whole arrangement
complete
my disappointment
would be certain.
But by carrying with me
one ceaseless source
of regret in.
My sister's absence.
I may reasonably hope
to have
all my expectations
of pleasure realized.
A scheme
which every
part promises delight
can never be successful
and general
disappointment
is only warded.
Off by the defense
of some little
peculiar vexation.
When Lydia
went away, she
promised to
write very often
and very minutely
to her mother and Kitty.
But her letters
were always
long expected
and always very short.
Those To her, mother
contained little else
than that.
They were just returned
from the library
where such
and such officers
had attended them,
and where she had
seen such
beautiful ornaments
as made her quite wild.
That.
She a new gown
or a new parasol, which
she would have described
more fully,
but was obliged
to leave off
in a violent hurry,
as Mrs.
Foster called her,
and they were
going off to the camp
and from
her correspondent
with her sister,
there was still less
to be learned.
For her.
Letters to Kitty, though
rather longer, were much
too full of lines
under the
words to be made public.
After.
The first or three
weeks of her absence.
Health.
Good humor
and cheerfulness
began to reappear
at long born.
Everything more
a happier aspect.
The families
who had been in town,
the winter
came back again
and summer finery
in summer
engagements arose.
Mrs.
Bennett was restored
to her
usual
querulous serenity,
and by the
middle of June.
Kitty was so much.
Recovered as to be able
to enter
Maritain without tears.
An event of such happy
promise
as to make
Elizabeth hope
that by
the following Christmas
she might be
so tolerably reasonable
as to not mention
officer above
once a day.
Alas, by some cruel
and malicious
arrangement
at the War Office,
another regiment
should be quartered
in Britain.
The time fixed
for the
beginning of their tour
was now fast
approaching.
And a fortnight
only was.
Wanting of it.
When a letter arrived
from Mrs.
Gardiner,
which had once delayed
its commencement
and curtailed
its extent, Mr.
Gardiner would
be prevented by business
from setting out
until a fortnight later
in July
and must be in
London again
within a month.
And as that left
too short
a period
for them to so far
and see
so much
as they had proposed.
Or at least to see it.
With the leisure
and comfort
they had built
on, they were obliged
to give up the legs
and substituted
more contracted tour,
and according
to the present plan,
were to go no farther
northwards
than Derbyshire.
In that country
there was enough
to be seen
to occupy the chief
of their three
weeks and.
To Mrs. Gardiner.
It had a peculiarly
strong attraction
the town
where she had
formerly passed
some years of her life
and where
they were now to spend
a few days
was probably as great
an object.
Her curiosity
as all
the celebrated beauties
of Matlock, Chatsworth,
Dovedale, or the peak.
Elizabeth
was excessively
disappointed.
She had set her heart
on seeing lakes
and still thought
there might have
been time enough.
But it was her business
to be satisfied and
certainly her
temper to be happy
and all was soon
right again
with the mention
of Derbyshire.
There were many
ideas connected.
It was impossible.
For her to see the word
without thinking
of Pemberley
and its owner.
But surely, said she,
I may enter his county
without.
Impunity and rob it
of a few petrified spies
without his
perceiving me.
The period of
expectation was
now doubled.
Four weeks
were to pass away
before her
uncle and
aunt's arrival.
But they did pass away.
And Mr.
and Mrs.
Gardner,
with their
four children,
did at length appear
at Long Bourn.
The children,
two girls of six
and eight years old
and two younger boys,
were to be left
out of the particular
care of their cousin
Jane,
who was the
general favorite
and whose steady sense
and sweetness
of temper
exactly adapted her
for attending to them
in every way,
teaching them,
playing with them
and loving them.
The gardener stayed
only one night
at Long Bourn
and set off
the next morning
with Elizabeth
in pursuit
of novelty
and amusement.
One enjoyment was.
Certain that of suitable
nursing companions.
A suitable nest
which comprehended
health and temper
to bear barren
conveniences,
cheerfulness to enhance
every pleasure
and affection
and intelligence.
Which might.
Supply it
among themselves
if there were
disappointments abroad.
It is not the object.
Of this work
to give a description
of Derbyshire,
nor of any of the
remarkable places
through which their root
thither lay.
Oxford.
Blenheim.
Warwick Kenilworth,
Birmingham, etc.
are sufficiently known.
A small part
of Derbyshire
is all the
present concern
to the little town
of Lampton.
The scene of Mrs.
Gardner's former
and where she had
lately learned
some acquaintance
still remained.
They bent their steps
after having seen
all the
principal wonders
of the country.
And within.
Five miles of Lambton
Elizabeth
found from her aunt
that Pemberley
was situated.
It was not in
their direct road, nor
more than a mile
or two out of it.
In talking over their
roots the.
Evening before, Mrs..
Gardner expressed
an inclination
to see the place again.
Mr.
Gardner
declared
his willingness.
And.
Elizabeth was applied to
for her approbation.
My love
should not
you like to see of place
of which you've heard
so much.
Said her aunt.
A place too,
with which
so many of your
acquaintances
are connected.
Wickham passed
or his You fail,
you know.
Elizabeth was
distressed.
She felt that
she had no business
at Pemberley
and was obliged
to assume
a disinclination
for seeing it.
She must own that.
She was tired
of seeing great houses.
After going
over so many,
she really had
no pleasure
in fine carpets or satin
curtains.
Mrs.
Gardiner
abused her stupidity.
If it were.
Merely a fine house.
Richly furnished,
said she.
I should not
care about it myself.
But the grounds
are delightful.
They have some of the
finest.
Woods in the country.
Elizabeth Said no more.
But her mind could
not acquiesce.
The possibility
of meeting. Mr.
Darcy
while viewing the place
instantly occurred.
It would be dreadful.
She blushed at the very
and thought it would be
better to speak
openly to her
aunt than to run
such a risk.
But against this
there were objections
and she finally
resolved that
it could be
the last resource
if her inquiries
to the absence of
the family
were unfavorably
answered.
Accordingly,
when she retired
at night.
She asked the.
Chambermaid
whether Pemberley were
not a very fine place.
What the name
of its proprietor.
And with no
little alarm,
whether the family
were down
for the summer.
I most welcome negative
followed
the last question
and her alarm's
now being removed.
She was at
leisure to feel
a great deal
of curiosity,
to see
the house herself.
And when the subject
was revived
the next morning
and she was again
applied to.
Could.
Readily answer
and with a proper
air of.
That she had.
Not really
any dislike
to the scheme.
To Pemberley, therefore,
they were to go.
Chapter 43.
Elizabeth,
as they drove along,
watched
for the first appearance
of Pemberley words
with some perturbation.
And when at last
they turned in
at the lodge.
Her spirits were in
a high flutter.
The park was very large
and contained.
Great variety of ground.
They entered it
in one of
its lowest points
and drove for some time
through a beautiful wood
stretching over
a wide extend.
Elizabeth's mind
was too full
for conversation,
but she saw and admired
every remarkable spot
and point of view.
They gradually ascended
for a half mile
and then
found themselves
at the top
of a considerable
eminence
where the wood ceased
and the eye
was instantly caught
by Pemberley House,
situated on the opposite
side of a valley
into which the road
with some
abruptness wound.
It was a large,
handsome stone building,
standing
well on rising ground
and backed by a ridge
of high woody hills.
And in front a stream
of some
natural importance
were swelled
into greater,
but without any
artificial appearance.
Its Banks
were neither formal
nor falsely adorned.
Elizabeth was delighted.
She had never
seen a place
for which nature
had done more or where
natural beauty had been.
So little counteracted
by an awkward taste.
They were all of them,
warm in
their admiration.
And at that moment,
she felt that to be
mistress of Pemberley
might be something.
They descended the hill
crossed the bridge
and drove to the door.
And while
examining the near
aspect of the house,
all her apprehension
of meeting
its owner returned.
She dreaded lest
the chambermaid
had been mistaken
on applying
to see the place.
They were admitted
into the hall.
And Elizabeth, as they
waited for
the housekeeper,
had leisure
to wonder at her
being where she was.
The housekeeper
came a respectable
looking elderly woman,
much less fine
and more civil
than she had
any notion
of finding her.
They followed her
into the dining parlor.
It was a large
well-proportioned room,
handsomely fitted up.
Elizabeth After
slightly surveying,
it went to a window
to enjoy its prospect.
The hill, crowned
with wood,
which they
had descended,
receiving increased
from the distance,
was a beautiful object.
Every disposition
of the ground was.
Good,
and she
looked on the
whole scene.
The river,
the trees
scattered on its banks
and the winding
the valley.
As far as she could
trace it with delight
as they passed
into other rooms.
These objects
were taking
different positions,
but from every window
there were
beauties to be seen.
The rooms were lofty
and handsome
and their furniture
suitable to the fortunes
of its proprietor.
But Elizabeth saw
with admiration
of his taste
that it was
neither gaudy
nor uselessly fine,
with less of splendor
and more real
elegance than the
furniture of Rosen's.
And of this place.
Thought she.
I might have
been mistress.
With these rooms,
I might now
have been
familiarly acquainted.
Instead of viewing
them as a stranger,
I might have
rejoiced in them
as my own and welcomed
to them as visitors,
aunt and uncle.
But no.
Recollecting herself.
That could never be.
My aunt and uncle
would have been
lost to me.
I should not
have been allowed
to invite them.
This was a
lucky recollection.
It saved her
from something
very like regret.
She longed to
inquire of
the housekeeper
whether her master
was really absent,
but had not the courage
for it.
At length, however,
the question
was asked by her uncle,
and she turned away
with alarm, while Mrs.
Reynolds replied
that he was adding.
But we expect him
tomorrow
with the large
party friends.
How rejoiced
was Elizabeth
that their own journey
had not, by
any circumstance,
been delayed a day?
Her aunt now
called her
to look at a picture.
She approached
and saw
the likeness of Mr.
Wickham,
suspended amongst
several other miniatures
over the mantelpiece.
Her aunt asked her
smilingly how she liked.
The housekeeper
came forward
and told them
it was a picture
of a young gentleman,
the son of her late
master steward,
who had been
brought up by him
at his own expense.
He Has now gone
into the army,
she added.
But I am afraid
he has turned out
very wild.
Mrs.
Gardner looked
at her niece
with a smile.
But Elizabeth
could not return it.
And that said, Mrs.
Reynolds, pointing
to another of
the miniatures.
Is my master
and very like him.
It was drawn
at the same time
as the other
about eight years ago.
I have heard much
of your master's
fine person.
Said Mrs.
Gardner,
looking at the picture.
It is a handsome face.
But Lizzie you.
Can tell us
whether it is like or.
Not. Mrs.
Reynolds Respect
for Elizabeth
seemed to increase
on this intimation
of her
knowing her master.
Does that young lady
know Mr.
Darcy?
Elizabeth colored and.
Said a little.
And do you not think
of a very handsome
gentleman, ma'am?
Yes, very handsome.
I am sure I know
none so handsome.
But in the gallery.
Upstairs.
You will see
a finer, larger
picture of him
than this.
This room was my late
master's favorite room.
And these miniatures are
just as
they used to be then.
He was very
fond of them.
This accounted
to Elizabeth for Mr.
Wickham's
being among them.
Mrs.
Reynolds
then directed their
to one of Mrs.
Darcy Drawn
when she was only
eight years old.
And as Miss Darcy is
handsome as her brother.
Said Mrs.
Gardiner.
Oh, yes
The handsomest
young lady
that ever was seen
and so accomplished.
She plays and sings
all day long.
And the next room
is a new instrument.
Just come down for her
a present
from my master.
She comes here tomorrow
with him.
Mr.
Gardiner,
whose manners
were very easy
and pleasant,
encouraged her
communicative ness
by his questions
and remarks.
Mrs.
Reynolds, either
by pride or attachment,
had evidently
great pleasure
in talking of her
master and his sister.
Is your master
much at Pemberley
in the course
of the year?
Not so
much as I could wish.
But I dare say
he may spend
half his time here.
And Miss
Darcy is always down
for the summer months.
Except
Thought Elizabeth
when she goes
to Ramsgate.
If you must
have would marry.
You might see
more of him.
Yes, sir.
But I do not know
when that be.
I do not know
who is good
enough for him.
Mr. and Mrs.
Gardiner smiled.
Elizabeth
could not help, saying.
It is very much
to his credit.
I am sure that
you should think so.
I say no more
than the truth.
And everybody will say
that knows him.
Replied the other.
Elizabeth thought
this was going
pretty far
and she listened
with increasing
astonishment.
The housekeeper added.
I have never known
a cross word
from him in my life,
and I have known him
ever since he was
four years old.
This was praise
of all others.
Most extraordinary,
most opposite
to her ideas.
That he was.
Not a good tempered
man, had been
her firmest.
Opinion.
Her keenest
attention was awakened.
She longed to hear more
and was grateful,
her uncle, for saying.
There are
very few people of whom
so much can be said.
You are lucky
in having such a master.
Yes, sir.
I know I am.
If I were to
go through the world,
I could not
meet with the better.
But I have always
observed that they
who are good natured,
when children
are good natured,
when they grow up.
And he was always
the sweetest tempered,
generous hearted boy
in the world.
Elizabeth
almost stared at her.
Can this be Mr.
Darcy?
Thought she.
His father was
an excellent man.
Said Mrs.
Gardiner.
Yes, ma'am.
That he was indeed.
And his son will be
just like him,
just as affable
to the poor.
Elizabeth
listened.
Doubted.
And was impatient
for more.
Mrs.
Reynolds could
interest her on
no other point.
She related the subject
of the pictures,
the dimensions
of the rooms
and the price,
the furniture in vain.
Mr.
Gardiner, highly amused
by the kind of family
prejudice
to which he attributed
her excessive
commendation of
her master.
Soon led again
to the subject.
And she dwelt
with energy
on his many merits
as they proceeded
together up
the great staircase.
He is the best landlord
and the best master.
Said she, that ever
not like the wild
young men nowadays
who think of nothing
but themselves.
There is not one of
his tenants
or servants,
but will give him
a good name.
Some people call him
proud, but I am.
I never saw
anything of it.
To my fancy
it is only
because he does
not rattle away
like other young men
in what an amiable light
does this place him
thought Elizabeth,
this fine
account of him.
Whispered her
aunt as they walked.
Is not quite.
Consistent
with his
behavior to our.
Poor friend.
Perhaps we might
be deceived.
That is not very likely.
Our authority
was too good.
On reaching
the spacious
lobby above,
they were shown into a
very pretty sitting room
lately, fitted up
with greater elegance
and lightness
than the
apartments below,
and were informed
that it was but
just done
to give pleasure to Mr.
Darcy, who had taken
a liking to the room
when last at Pemberley.
He certainly
a good brother.
Said Elizabeth,
as she walked towards
one of the windows.
Mrs.
Reynolds anticipated
Miss Darcy's delight
when she should
enter the room.
And this is all ways
the way with him.
She added,
Whatever can
give his sister
any pleasure is sure
to be done in a moment.
There is nothing
he would not do for her.
The picture gallery
and two
or three
of the
principal bedrooms were
all that remain
to be shown,
and the former were
many good paintings.
But Elizabeth knew
nothing of the art
and from such
as had been already
visible below.
She had willingly
turned to look
at some drawings
of Miss Darcy's
and crayons,
whose subjects
were usually
more interesting
and also
more intelligible.
In the gallery,
there are
many family portraits,
but they could
have little
to fix the attention
of a stranger.
Elizabeth walked in
quest of the only face
whose features
would be known to her.
At last,
it arrested her
and she beheld
a striking resemblance
to Mr. Darcy.
With such a smile over
the face
as she remembered
to have sometimes seen,
when he looked at her,
she stood
several minutes
before the picture
in earnest contemplation
and returned to it again
before they quitted
the gallery.
Mrs.
Reynolds informed them
that it had been taken
in his
father's lifetime.
There was
certainly at this moment
in Elizabeth's mind,
a more gentle sensation
towards the original
than she had ever felt
at the height
of their acquaintance.
The commendation
bestowed on him by Mrs.
Reynolds was of
no trifling nature.
What's praise
is valuable
than the praise
of an
intelligent servant
as a brother,
a landlord, a master.
She considered
how many
people's happiness
were in
his guardianship.
How much of pleasure
or pain
was it in his power
to bestow?
How much of good or evil
must be done by him?
Every idea
that had been
brought forward
by the housekeeper
was favorable
to his character
and as she stood
before the canvas
on which
he was represented
and fixed
his eyes upon herself.
She thought of his.
Regard
with a deeper
sentiment of gratitude
than it ever
raised before.
She remembered
its warmth and softened.
Its impropriety
of expression.
When all of the house
that was open
to general
inspection
had been seen.
They returned downstairs
and taking leave of
the housekeeper
were consigned
over to the gardener
who met them
at the hall door
as they walked
across the hall
towards the river.
Elizabeth turned back
to look again.
Her aunt and uncle
stopped also.
And while the former
was conjecturing
as to the date
of the building,
the owner of it himself
suddenly came forward
from the road,
which led behind it
to the stables.
They were within
20 yards of each other
and so abrupt
with his appearance
that it was impossible
to avoid his sight.
Their eyes instantly met
and the cheeks of both
were over.
Spread
the deepest blush.
He absolutely stared
and for a moment
seemed immovable
from surprise.
But shortly
recovering himself,
advanced
toward the party
and spoke to Elizabeth,
if not in terms
of perfect composure,
at least of
perfect civility.
She had instinctively
turned away,
but stopping
on his approach
received,
his compliments
with an embarrassment,
impossible
to be overcome,
had his first appearance
or his resemblance
to the picture
they had just
been examining
been insufficient
to assure the other two
that they now saw Mr..
The gardener's
expression of surprise
and beholding his master
must immediately
have told it.
They stood a.
Little aloof
while he was talking
to their.
Niece,
who astonished and.
Confused scarcely
dared lift
her eyes to his face.
And knew not.
What answer.
She returned to
his civil inquiries
after her family
amazed at the alteration
of his manners
since they last parted.
Every sentence
that he uttered
was increasing
her embarrassment
and every idea
of the impropriety
of her being found there
recurring to her mind.
The few minutes
in which they continued
were some of
most uncomfortable
in her life.
Nor did he seem
much more at ease
when he spoke.
His accent
had none of its
usual sedate ness,
and he repeated
his inquiries
as to the time of her
having left long born
and of her
having stayed
in Derbyshire so often
and in so hurried away
as plainly spoke
the distraction
of his thoughts.
At length,
every idea
seemed to fail him,
and after
standing a few moments
without saying a word,
he suddenly
recollected himself
and took leave.
The others
then joined her
and expressed
admiration
of his figure.
But Elizabeth heard
not a word and wholly
engrossed by her own
feelings,
followed them
in silence.
She was overpowered
by shame and vexation.
Her coming
there was the
most unfortunate,
the most ill.
Judged.
Thing in the world.
How strange
it must appear to him.
And what a.
Disgraceful light.
Might it not strike
so vain?
A man it might seem, if.
She had purposely
thrown herself
in his way.
Again.
Oh, why did she come?
Or why did he does.
Come a day before
he was expected?
Had they been only
10 minutes sooner,
they should have
been beyond the reach
of his discrimination.
For it was.
Plain that he was
that moment arrived.
That moment
alighted from his horse
or his carriage.
She blushed again.
And again
over the perverse
ness of the.
Meeting and his behavior
so strikingly altered.
What could it mean
that he should.
Even speak to her was.
Amazing.
But to speak
with such civility,
to inquire.
After her family.
Never in her life
had she seen his manners
so little dignified.
Never had
he spoken
with such gentleness
as on this
unexpected meeting.
What a country
did it offer to his last
address
and rousing spark
when he put his
letter into her hand.
She knew not.
What to think
or how to
account for it.
They had now entered
a beautiful walk
by the side
of the water,
and every step
was bringing forward
a nobler fall of ground
or a finer
reach of the woods
to which
they were approaching.
But it was some time
before Elizabeth,
the sensible
of any of it.
And though she answered
mechanically
to the repeated appeals
of her aunt and uncle,
and seemed to
direct her eyes
to such objects,
they pointed out
she distinguished
no part of the scene.
Her thoughts
were all fixed
on that
one spot
at Pemberley House,
whichever it might be.
Where Mr.
Darcy then was.
She longed to know what.
At the moment
was passing in his mind
in what manner
he thought of her,
and whether in defiance
of everything
she was still
dear to him.
Perhaps he'd been civil
only because
he felt himself at ease.
Yet There had been that
in his voice,
which was not like ease.
Whether he had felt
more of pain
or of pleasure
in seeing her,
she could not tell.
But he certainly had not
seen her with composure
at length.
However,
the remarks
of her companions
on her absence of mind
aroused her,
and she felt
the necessity
of appearing
more like herself.
They entered the woods
and putting a due
to the river
for a while ascended
some of the
higher grounds
when in spots
where the opening
of the trees
gave the AI power
to wander,
where many
charming views
of the valley,
the opposite dales
with the long
range of woods
over spending money
and occasionally part
of the stream, Mr.
Gardner expressed
a wish of going
round to the whole park,
but feared
it might be
beyond a walk
with a triumphant smile.
They were told
that it was ten
miles round.
It settled the matter
and they pursued
the accustomed circuit,
which brought them again
after some time,
and a descent.
Among hanging woods.
To the edge of the water
and one of its
narrowest parts.
They crossed it
by a simple bridge
in character
with the general
Arab scene.
It was a spot
less adorned than any
they had yet visited,
and the valley here
contracted into a glen
allowed room
only for the stream
and a narrow walk amidst
the rough coppice wood.
Which bordered it.
Elizabeth
to explore its windings.
But when they
had crossed.
The bridge
and perceived
their distance from the.
House.
Mrs.
Gardner,
who was not
a great walker, could go
no further and thought
only of returning
to the carriage
as quickly as possible.
Her niece
was therefore
obliged to submit
and they took their way
towards the house
on the opposite
side of the river
in the
nearest direction.
But their progress
was slow.
For Mr.
Gardiner, though
seldom able to indulge,
the taste,
was very
fond of fishing,
and with so much
engaged in
watching the occasional
appearance of,
some trout in the water
and talking to the man
about them
that he advanced
but little.
Whilst wandering on in.
This slow manner,
they were again
surprised.
And Elizabeth's
astonishment
was quite equal
to what it had
been at first
by the sight of Mr.
Darcy approaching them
and at
no great distance.
The walk.
Here, being here less
sheltered than
on the other side,
allowed them to see him
before they met.
Elizabeth,
however astonished,
was at least
more prepared
for an interview
than before
and resolved to appear
and to speak
with calmness
if he really intended
to meet them.
For a.
Few moments.
Indeed,
she felt that he would
probably strike
into some other path.
The idea lasted
while the turning
in the walk
concealed him
from their view,
the turning past.
He Was immediately
before them
with a glance.
She saw that he had lost
none of his
recent civility
and to
imitate his politeness.
She began, as they met
to admire
the beauty of the place.
But she had not got
beyond the.
Words
delightful and charming.
When some unlucky
recollections of traded
and she fancy
that praise
of Pemberley from her
might be mischievously
construed,
her color changed.
And she said no.
More. Mrs.
Gardiner
was standing
a little behind,
and on her pausing,
he asked her
if she would do him
the honor of
introducing him
to her friends.
This was a stroke
of civility
for which
she was quite unprepared
and could
hardly suppress
a smile at his being.
Now seeking
the acquaintance
of some of those
very people against
whom his Pride
had revolted
in his offer to herself.
What would be
his surprise?
Thought she.
When he knows who
they are,
he takes the
now for people
of fashion.
The introduction,
however,
was immediately made,
and as she named
their relationship
to herself.
She.
Stole a sly look at him
to see how he bought
and was not without
the expectation
of his decamping as fast
as he could
from such
disgraceful companions.
But he was surprised by
the connection
was evident.
He sustained
it, however,
with fortitude.
And so far.
From going away
turned his back
with them
and entered
into conversation
with Mr. Gardner.
Elizabeth could
not but be pleased.
Could not.
But to triumph.
It was consoling
that he should know.
She had some relations
for whom there was.
No need to blush.
She listened
most attentively
to all that passed
between them and gloried
in every expression,
every sentence
of her uncle,
which marked
his intelligence
his taste
or his good manners.
The conversation soon
turned upon fishing,
and she heard Mr.
Darcy invite him
with the
greatest civility
to fish
there as often
as he chose,
while he continued
in the neighborhood,
offering at
the same time
to supply him
with fishing tackle
and pointing out
those parts
of the stream
where there was most
usually sport.
Mrs.
Gardiner,
who was walking
arm in arm
with Elizabeth,
gave her a look.
Expressive of wonder.
Elizabeth said nothing,
but it gratified her
exceedingly.
The compliment must be
all for herself.
Her astonishment
was extreme
and continually
was she repeating?
Why is he so altered
from what
cannot proceed?
It cannot be for me
at cannot be for.
My that his manners
and thus.
Softened my reproof
that Hansford
could not work
such a change as this.
It is impossible
that he should
still love me.
After walking
some time in this way.
The two ladies in front,
the two gentlemen
behind.
On resuming their.
Places
after descending
to the brink
of the river
for the
better inspection
of some
curious water plant.
Their chance
be a little alteration.
It originated in Mrs.
Gardner.
Who, fatigued.
By the exercise
of the morning,
found Elizabeth's arm
inadequate
to her support
and consequently
preferred husband's.
Mr.
Darcy took her
place by her knees,
and they walked
on together.
After a short silence,
the lady first spoke.
She wished him.
To know
that she had
been assured his absence
before she came
to the place,
and accordingly began
by observing
that his arrival
had been
very unexpected.
For your housekeeper.
She added, informed us
that she would
certainly not be here
till tomorrow.
And indeed,
before we left Bakewell,
we understood that
you were not immediately
expected in the country.
He acknowledged
the truth of it all
and, said that
business with
his steward
had occasioned
his coming forward
a few hours
before the rest
of the party
with whom
he had been traveling.
They will join me early
tomorrow.
He continued.
And among them are some
who will claim
an acquaintance
with you.
Mr.
Bingley and his sisters.
Elizabeth answered
only by a slight bow.
Her thoughts were
instantly driven
back to the time
when Mr.
Bingley,
his name,
had been
the last mention
between them.
And if she might judge.
By his complexion,
his mind was not
very differently
engaged.
There is also one person
in the party.
He continued
after a pause.
Who more particularly
wishes
to be known to you.
Will you allow me,
or do I ask too much
to introduce my sister
to acquaintance
during your stay
at Lambton?
The surprise of such
an application
was great indeed.
It was too.
Great for her to know
in what manner
she acceded to it.
She immediately felt
that whatever
desire Ms..
Darcy
might have of
being acquainted
with her
must be the work
of her brother.
And without
looking farther,
it was satisfactory.
It was gratifying
to know
that his resentment
not made him
think really ill of her.
They now walked.
On in silence,
each of them
deep in thought.
Elizabeth was
not comfortable.
That was impossible.
But she was flattered
and pleased.
His wish of introducing
his sister to her
was a compliment
of the highest kind.
They soon.
Outstripped the others.
And when they
had reached
the carriage.
Mr. and Mrs.
Gardiner were half
a quarter of a mile.
Behind.
He then asked her to
walk into
the house, but.
She declared herself
not tired,
and they stood
together on the lawn.
At such a time
might have been.
Said and silence
was very awkward.
She wanted to talk.
But there seemed
to be an embargo
on every.
Subject.
At last, she recollected
that she had
been traveling,
and they talked
of Matlock and Dovedale
with great perseverance.
Yet Time
and her
aunt moved slowly,
and her patience
and her ideas
were nearly worn out
before the Ted was over.
After Mr.
and Mrs.
Gardner's coming up,
they were all pressed
to go into the house
and take
some refreshment,
but this was declined
and they parted on
each side with utmost.
Mr.
Darcy handed the
ladies
into the carriage,
and when it drove off,
Elizabeth
saw him
walking slowly towards
the house.
The observations
of her uncle
and aunt now began,
and each of them
pronounced him
to be
infinitely superior
to anything
they had expected.
He is perfectly
well behaved, polite
and unassuming.
Said her uncle.
There is something
a little stately in him,
to be sure.
Replied her aunt.
But it is confined
to his air and
is not unbecoming.
I can now
say with the housekeeper
that, though
some people may
call him proud,
I have seen
nothing of it.
I was never
more surprised
than by his behavior.
To us
it was more than civil.
It was really attentive
and.
There was no necessity
for such attention.
His acquaintance
with Elizabeth
was very trifling.
To be sure, Lizzie.
Said her aunt.
He is not so handsome
as Wickham or.
Rather,
he has not
Wickham's countenance
for his speech
as a perfectly good.
But how came.
You to tell me
that he was so.
Disagreeable?
Elizabeth
excused herself
as well as she.
Could.
Said she had
liked him better
when they had met in
Kent than before,
and that she had
never seen him
so pleasant
as this morning.
But perhaps he may be
a little whimsical
in his civilities.
Replied her Uncle.
Your great man
of an hour,
and therefore
I shall not
take him at his word
about fishing
as he might
change his mind
another day and warn me
of his grounds.
Elizabeth felt
that they had
entirely misunderstood
his character,
but said nothing.
From what we have
seen of him.
Continued Mrs..
Gardiner.
I really should not
have thought
that he could have.
Behaved in so cruel
a way by as.
He has done
by poor Wickham.
He has not an
ill natured look.
On the contrary,
there is something
pleasing about his mouth
when he speaks.
And there is
something of dignity
in his countenance.
Would not give one
an unfavorable idea
of his heart.
But to be sure,
the good lady
who showed us
his house
did give him a most
flaming character.
I could
hardly have
laughing aloud.
Sometimes but
he is a liberal master,
I suppose,
and that in the eye of
a servant
comprehends
every virtue.
Elizabeth
here felt herself
called on to
say something
in vindication
of his behavior
to Wickham,
and therefore gave them
to understand
in as guarded
a manner as she.
Could that by what she.
Had heard
from his relations
in Kent.
His actions were capable
of a very different
and that his character
was by
no means so faulty,
nor Wickham's
so amiable
as they had
been considered
in Hertfordshire.
In confirmation of this,
she related
the particulars
all the
pecuniary transactions
in which
they had been connected
without actually
naming her authority,
but stating it
to be
such as might
be relied on.
Mrs.
Gardiner was surprised
and concerned.
But as they were
now approaching
the scene
of her former pleasures.
Every.
Idea gave way
to the charm
of recollection,
and she was too
much engaged
in pointing out
to her husband
all the interesting
and its environs
to think of
anything else.
Fatigued as she had
been by the morning's
walk.
They had no.
Sooner dined
than she set off again
in quest of her
former acquaintance,
and the evening
was spent
in the satisfactions
of an intercourse
renewed after many years
discontinuance.
The occurrences
of the day
were too full
of interest
to leave
Elizabeth much attention
for any of these
new friends.
And she could.
Do nothing but think
and think with wonder
of Mr.
Darcy's civility
and above all of his
wishing her to be
acquainted with
his sister.
Chapter 44.
Elizabeth
had settled it that Mr.
Darcy would
bring his sister
to visit her
the very day
after her
reaching Pemberley,
and was consequently
resolved
not to be out of sight
of the
in the whole
of that morning.
But her conclusion
was false.
For on the very morning
after their arrival
at Lambton,
these visitors came.
They had been walking
about the place
with some of
their new friends
and were just returning
to the end
to dress themselves
for dining
with the same family
when the sound
of a carriage
drew them to the window
and they saw a gentleman
and a lady in a car
driving up the street.
Elizabeth, immediately
recognizing the livery.
Guessed what it meant.
And imparted
no small degree
of her surprise
to her relations.
By acquainting.
Them with the honor
which she expected.
Her uncle
and aunt
were all amazement
and the embarrassment
of her matter
as she spoke.
Joined to the
circumstance itself
and many of
the circumstances
of the preceding day
opens to them a new idea
on the business.
Nothing had ever
suggested it before,
but they felt that
there was no other way
of accounting
for such attentions
from such a quarter
than by supposing
a partiality
for their niece.
While these newly born
notions were passing
their heads,
the perturbation
of Elizabeth's feelings
was at every
moment increasing.
She was quite amazed.
At her own
dis composure.
But amongst other
causes of disquiet,
she dreaded, lest
the partiality
of the brother
should have said
too much in her favor
and more than commonly
anxious to please.
She naturally suspected
that every power
of pleasing fail her.
She retreated
from the window,
fearful of being.
Seen, and as.
She walked up
and down the room
endeavoring to compose
herself, saw such
looks of
inquiring surprise
in her uncle
and aunt as
made everything worse.
Miss Darcy
and her
brother appeared,
and this formidable
introduction took place
with astonishment
at Elizabeth.
See that her new
acquaintance was
at least
as much embarrassed
as herself
since her being
at Lambton.
She had heard that
Miss Darcy
was exceedingly proud.
But the observation
of a very few minutes
convinced her
that she was only
exceedingly shy.
She found it difficult
to obtain
even a word from her
beyond a mono syllable.
Mr.
Darcy was tall and
on a larger
scale than Elizabeth,
and though
little more than 16,
her figure was formed
and her
appearance womanly
and graceful.
She was less
handsome than
her brother.
But there was sense
and good humor
in her face,
and her manners were
perfectly unassuming
and gentle.
Elizabeth, who
had expected
to find in her as acute
unembarrassed
an observer as ever Mr.
Darcy had been,
was much relieved
by discerning
such different feelings.
They had not long
been together before.
Mr.
Darcy told her
that Bingley
was also
coming to wait on her,
and she had barely time
to express
her satisfaction
and prepare
for such a visitor.
When Begley's quick step
was heard on the stairs
and in a moment
he entered the room.
All Elizabeth's anger
against him
had been long done away.
But had she still
felt any,
it could
hardly have stood
its ground
against the
unaffected cordiality
with which
he expressed himself on
seeing her again.
He inquired
in a friendly, though
general way,
after her family,
and looked and spoke
with the
same good humored ease
that he had ever done
to Mr.
and Mrs. Gardiner.
He was scarcely a less
interesting personage
than to herself.
They had long wished.
To see him.
The whole
before them, indeed
excited
a lively attention.
The suspicions,
which had just arisen
of Mr.
Darcy and their niece,
directed
their observation
towards each
with an earnest,
though guarded inquiry,
and they soon drew
from those inquiries
the full conviction
that one of them
at least. Knew.
What it was to love.
Of the lady sensations,
they remained
a little in doubt,
but that the gentleman
was overflowing
with admiration
was evident enough.
Elizabeth on her side
had much to do.
She wanted to ascertain
the feelings
of each of visitors.
She wanted
to compose her own
and to make herself
agreeable to all,
and in the latter object
where she feared
most to fail.
She was most
sure of success
for those to
whom she endeavor
to give pleasure
were pre
possessed in her favor.
Bingley was ready.
Georgiana was eager
and Darcy determined
to be pleased
in seeing Bingley.
Her thoughts
naturally flew
to her sister and
oh, how ardently did
she longed to know
whether any of his
were directed in a
like manner.
Sometime
she could fancy
that he talked less than
on former occasions
and once or twice
pleased herself
with the notion
that as
he looked at her,
he was trying to trace
a resemblance.
But though
this might be imaginary,
she could not
be deceived
as to his behavior
to Miss Darcy,
who had been set up
as a rival to Jane,
no look appeared
on either that spoke
particular regard.
Nothing occurred
between them
that could
justify the hopes
of his sister.
On this point,
she was soon satisfied
and two or three
little circumstance
as occurred
are they parted,
which in her
anxious interpretation
denoted a recollection
of Jane,
not until
shared by tenderness
and a wish of
saying more.
That might lead
to the mention of had
he dared,
he observed to her
at a moment
when the others
were talking together,
and in a tone
which had something
of real regret that.
It was a very long time
since he had
the pleasure
of seeing her and.
Before she could reply,
he added.
It is above
eight months.
We have not met
since the 26th
of November,
when we were all dancing
together at Netherfield.
Elizabeth was
pleased to find
his memory so exact,
and he afterwards
took occasion to ask her
when unattended
to by any of the rest
whether all her sisters
were at long born.
There was not much
in the question
nor in the
preceding remark,
but there was a look
and a manner
which gave them meaning.
It was often that
she could turn her
eyes on Mr.
Darcy himself,
but whenever she did
catch a glimpse,
she saw an expression
of general complacence.
And in all that, he said
she heard an so removed
from hauteur
or disdain
of his companions,
as convinced her
that the improvement
of manners
which she had
yesterday witnessed,
however temporary
its existence
might prove,
had at least outlived
one day
when she saw him,
thus seeking
the acquaintance
and courting
the good opinion
of people
with whom
any intercourse
a few months
ago would have been a.
When.
She saw him thus civil
not only to herself,
but to the very
relations
whom he had
openly disdained
and recollected
their last lively
in Huntsmen parsonage.
The difference?
The change was so.
Great and.
Struck
so forcibly on her mind
that she could
hardly restrain
her astonishment
from being.
Never
even in the company
of his dear
friends at Netherfield
or his dignified
relations at Rose Ings.
Had she seen him
so desirous
to please so.
Free from
self consequence
or unbending reserve
as now,
when no importance
could result
from the success
of his endeavors,
and when even
the acquaintance
of those to
whom his attentions
were addressed
would draw down
the ridicule
and censure
of the ladies.
Both of Netherfield
and Rose Ings,
their visitor
stayed with him
above half an hour,
and when they arose
to depart, Mr.
D'Arcy
called on his sister
to join him
in expressing
their wish of seeing Mr.
and Mrs.
Gardner and Miss Bennet
to dinner at Pemberley
before they left
the country.
Miss D'Arcy,
though,
with a diffidence
which marked her
a little in the habit
of giving invitations,
readily obeyed.
Mrs.
Gardner looked
at her niece, desirous
of knowing how she whom
the invitation
most concerned, felt
disposed
as to its acceptance.
But Elizabeth
had turned away
her head.
Presuming, however, that
this studied
avoidance spoke
rather
momentary embarrassment
than any dislike
of the proposal,
and seeing in
her husband,
who was fond of society
a perfect willingness
to accept it,
she ventured to engage
their attendance,
and the day after the
next was fixed on
Bingley expressed great
pleasure
in the certainty
of seeing
Elizabeth again, having
still a great deal
to say to her
and many inquiries
to make
after all
their Hertfordshire
friends.
Elizabeth
construing all this
into a wish of hearing
her speak of her sister.
Was pleased.
And on account
as well as some others
found herself
when their visitors
left them capable
of considering
the last half hour
with some satisfaction
though
while it was passing,
the enjoyment of it
had been little eager
to be alone
and fearful of inquiries
or hints
from her uncle and aunt.
She stayed with them
only long enough
to hear their favorable
opinion of Bingley
and then hurried away
to dress.
But she had
no reason to fear Mr.
and Mrs.
Gardner's curiosity.
It was not their wish
to force her
communication.
It was evident
that she was much better
acquainted with Mr.
Darcy
than they had before.
Any idea.
Of it.
Was evident
that he was very much
in love with her.
They saw much
to interest, but nothing
to justify inquiry
of Mr.
Darcy.
It was now
a matter of anxiety
to think well, and
as far as
their acquaintance
reached,
there was fault to find
they could not
be untouched
by his politeness.
And had they drawn
his character
from their own feelings
and his servants report
without any reference
to any other.
The circle
in Hertfordshire,
to which he was known,
would not have
recognized it for Mr.
Darcy.
There was now
an interest, however,
in believing
the housekeeper
and soon became
sensible that
the authority
of a servant
who had known him
since he was
four years old
and whose own manners
indicated
respectability.
Was not to.
Be hastily rejected.
Neither had anything
occurred
in the intelligence
of their Lampton friends
that could materially
lessen its weight.
They had nothing to
accuse him of,
but pride.
Pride he probably.
Had.
And if not, it would
certainly.
Be imputed
by the inhabitants
of a small market town
where the family did
not visit.
It was acknowledged,
however, that
he was a liberal
and did much good
among the poor
with respect to Wickham.
The traveler
soon found that
he was not held there
in much estimation,
for though
the chief
of his concerns
with the son
of his patron
were imperfectly
understood.
It was yet a.
Well-Known fact that
on his
quitting Derbyshire,
he had left many debts
behind him, which Mr.
Darcy had
afterwards discharged.
As for Elizabeth,
her thoughts
were at Pemberley
this evening,
more than the last.
And the.
Evening, though
as it passed,
it seemed long.
Was not long.
Enough to determine
her feelings towards one
in that mention,
and she lay awake
two whole hours
endeavoring to
make them out.
She certainly did
not hate them.
No hatred
had vanished long.
Ago, and she.
Had almost as long been
ashamed of ever
feeling a dislike
against him.
That could be so called
the respect
created
by the conviction
of his
valuable qualities,
though at first
unwillingly admitted,
had for some time
ceased to be repugnance
to her feeling,
and it was
now heightened
into somewhat
of a friendlier nature
by the testimony
so highly in his favor
and bringing forward
his disposition
and so amiable a light.
Which.
Yesterday had produced.
But above all, above
respect and esteem.
There was a motive
within her of goodwill
which
could not be overlooked.
It was gratitude.
Gratitude not merely
for having
once loved her,
but for loving her
still well enough
to forgive
all the petulance
and acrimony
of her manner
and rejecting him
and all the
unjust accusations
accompanying her
rejection.
He, who
she had been persuaded
with avoid her
as his greatest enemy.
Seemed
on this
accidental meeting,
most eager.
To preserve
the acquaintance,
and without
any indelicate of regard
or any peculiarity
of manner
where their two selves
only were concerned
with soliciting
the good opinion
of her friends
and bent on making her
known to his sister
such a change
in a man of
so much pride.
Exciting
not only astonishment,
but gratitude
for to love
ardent love.
It must be attributed,
and as such
its impression on her
was of a sorts
to be encouraged, as by.
No means unpleasing,
though it.
Could not be
exactly defined.
She respected.
She.
She was grateful to him.
She felt a real interest
in his welfare.
And she only wants
to know
how far she wished
that welfare
to depend upon herself
and how far
would be
for the happiness
of both.
That she
should employ the power
which her fancy told her
she still possessed
of bringing on her
the renewal of
his addresses.
It had been.
Settled in the evening,
the aunt and her niece.
That such a.
Striking civility
has missed
Darcy's in
coming to see them
on the very day
of her arrival
at Pemberley,
for she had reached it
only to a late
breakfast.
Ought to be imitated,
though it could not.
Be equaled
by some exertion
of politeness
on their side,
and consequently
that it would be
highly expedient
to wait on her
at Pemberley
the following morning.
They were therefore
to go.
Elizabeth was pleased,
though,
when she asked herself
the reason.
She had
very little to say
in reply.
Mr.
left them soon
after breakfast.
The fishing scheme
had been renewed
the day before
and a
positive engagement
made of his meeting
some of the gentlemen at
Pemberley before noon.
Chapter 45.
Convinced as
Elizabeth now
was that Ms..
Bailey's dislike
of her
had originated
in jealousy.
She could not help.
Feeling how unwelcome
her appearance
at Pemberley
must be to her,
and was curious to know
with how much civility
on that lady's side,
the acquaintance
would now be.
Renewed.
On reaching the house.
They were shown
through the hall
into the saloon,
whose northern aspect
rendered it
delightful for summer.
Its windows
opening to the ground,
admitted A
most refreshing
view of the high Woody
hills behind the house.
And of the.
Beautiful oaks
and Spanish chestnuts
which were
scattered over
the intermediate lawn.
In this house
were received
by Miss Darcy,
who was sitting there
with Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley
and the lady with whom
she lived in London.
Georgina's
reception of them
was very civil,
but attended
with all
the embarrassment
which, though
proceeding from shyness
and the
fear of doing wrong,
would easily
give to those
who felt themselves
inferior.
The belief of her
being proud
and reserved.
Mrs.
Gardiner and her niece,
however, did her justice
and pitied her by Mrs.
Hurst and Miss Bingley.
They were noticed
only by a curtsey
and on their seated
a pause.
Awkward as such,
pauses must always.
Be succeeded.
For a few moments.
It was first broken
by Mrs.
Annesley, a genteel
agreeable looking woman
whose endeavor
to introduce
some kind of discourse
proved her
to be more
truly well-bred
than either
of the others.
And between her and Mrs.
Gardiner,
with occasional help
from Elizabeth.
The conversation
was carried on.
Miss Darcy
looked as if she wished
for courage
enough to join in it,
and sometimes
to adventure
a short sentence
when there was least
danger of its
being heard.
Elizabeth soon
saw that she was herself
closely
watched by Miss Bingley
and that she
could not speak a word,
especially to Miss Darcy
without calling her
attention.
This observation
would not have
prevented her
from trying
to talk to the latter
had they not been seated
at an
inconvenient distance.
But she was not.
Sorry to be spared
the necessity
of saying much.
Her own thoughts
were employing her.
She expected
every moment
that some of
the gentlemen
would enter the room.
She wished.
She feared that
the master of the house
might be amongst them,
and whether she wished
or feared it.
Most, she could.
Scarcely determine.
After sitting in this
manner
a quarter of an hour
without hearing
the Spengler's voice,
Elizabeth was roused
by receiving
from her a cold inquiry.
After the
health of her family.
She answered with equal
indifference
and brevity,
and the others said
more.
The next variation,
which
their visit afforded
was produced
by the entrance
of servants
with cold meat, cake
and a variety of all
the finest
fruits and season.
But this did not.
Take place
till after many
a significant
look and smile from Mrs.
Ainsley to Mr.
Darcy had been given
to remind her
of her post.
There was employment
for the whole party
for though
they could not all talk.
They could all.
Eat.
And the
beautiful pyramids
of grapes,
nectarines and.
Peaches soon.
Collected them
round the table.
While thus engaged,
Elizabeth
had a fair opportunity
of deciding
whether she most feared
or wished
for the appearance
of Mr.
Darcy by the feelings
which prevailed on his
entering the room.
And then, though,
but a moment before
she had believed her
wishes to predominate,
she began to regret
that he came.
He had been some.
Time with Mr.
Gardiner Who, with two
or three other
gentlemen from
the house, was engaged
by the river
and had left him
only on learning
that the ladies
of the family intended
a visit
to Georgiana that.
Morning.
No sooner did
he appear, then
Elizabeth wisely
resolved to be
perfectly easy
and unembarrassed
a resolution
the more necessary
to be made, but perhaps
not the more
easily kept.
Because she.
Saw that
the suspicions
of the whole party
were awakened
against them
and that
there was
scarcely an eye
which did not
watch his behavior
when he first came
into the room.
In no countenance
was attentive curiosity
so strongly marked
as in Miss Bingley,
in spite of the smiles
which over
spread her face
whenever she spoke
to one of its objects.
For jealousy,
had not yet.
Made her desperate
and her attentions
to Mr.
Darcy were by
no means over.
Miss Darcy,
on her brother's
entrance,
exerted herself
much more to talk.
And Elizabeth saw
that he was anxious
for his sister
and herself
to get acquainted.
And.
Forward it
as much as possible.
Every attempt
at conversation
on either side.
Miss Bingley
saw all this.
Likewise.
And the imprudence
of anger
took the
first opportunity
of saying with sneering
civility.
Pray, Miss Eliza.
Are not the blank shore
militia
removed from Merton.
They must be
a great loss
to your family.
In Darcy's
presence, she
dared not mention
Wickham's name.
But Elizabeth instantly
comprehended
that he was uppermost
in her thoughts
and the
various recollections
connected with him
gave her a moment's
distress.
But exerting herself
vigorously to repel
the ill natured attack,
she presently answered
the question
in a tolerably
detached tone.
While she spoke,
an involuntary glance
showed her Darcy
with a
heightened complexion,
earnestly looking at her
and his sister,
overcome with confusion
and unable
to lift up her eyes.
Had Miss Bingley known.
What pain.
She was then
giving her
beloved friend,
she undoubtedly
would have refrained
from the hint.
But she had.
Merely intended
to dispose Elizabeth
by bringing forward
the idea of a man.
To whom she believed.
Her partial
and to make her betray
a sensibility
which might injure her
in Dorothy's opinion.
And perhaps
to remind the latter
of all the follies
and absurdities by which
some part of her family
were connected
with that corps.
Not a syllable
had ever reached her
of Ms..
Darcy's meditated.
Elopement to no.
Creature.
Had it been revealed
where secrecy
was possible
except to Elizabeth.
And from all being
these connections,
her brother
was particularly anxious
to conceal it
from the very wish
which Elizabeth
had long ago
attributed to him
of their becoming
hereafter her own.
He had certainly
formed such plan
and without meeting
that it should affect
his endeavor
to separate him
from Ms.. Bennett.
It is probable
that it might add
something
to his lively concern
for the welfare
of his friend.
Elizabeth's
behavior, however, soon
quieted his emotion,
and as Miss Bingley,
vexed and disappointed,
dared not approach
near to Wickham.
Georgiana also
recovered in time.
Though not enough.
To be able
to speak anymore.
Her brother,
whose eyes
she feared to meet,
scarcely recollected
her interest
in the affair
and the
very circumstance
which had been
to turn his thoughts
from Elizabeth
seem to have
fixed them on her more
and more cheerfully.
Their
visit did not continue
long after the question
and answer
above mentioned,
and while Mr.
Darcy
was attending them
to their carriage,
Miss Bingley was venting
her feelings
and criticisms
on Elizabeth's person,
behavior and dress.
But Georgiana
would not her.
Her brother's
recommendation
was enough
to ensure her favor.
His judgment
could not her.
And as he had spoken
in such
terms of Elizabeth,
asked to leave Georgiana
without the power
of finding her otherwise
then lovely and amiable.
When Darcy returned
to the saloon, Ms..
Bingley
could not help
repeating to him
some part
of what she had
been saying
to his sister.
How very ill
measles had been.
It looks this
morning, Mr.
Darcy.
She cried.
I never in my life
saw anyone
so much altered
as she is
since the winter.
She's grown so brown
and coarse.
Louisa and
I were agreeing
that we should not
have known her again.
However, little Mr.
Darcy might have
liked such an address.
He contended.
Himself with
coolly replying
that he perceived
no other alteration
than her
being rather tanned.
No miraculous
consequence
of traveling
in the summer.
2 million.
She rejoined.
I must confess
that I never saw
any beauty in her.
Her face is too thin.
Her complexion
has no brilliancy
and features
and not at handsome.
Her nose wants
character.
There is nothing marked
in its lines.
Her teeth are tolerable,
but not out of
the common way.
And for her eyes,
which have sometimes
been called so fine,
I could never
see anything
extraordinary in them.
They have a sharp,
shrewish look,
which I do
not like at all.
And in her hair
altogether,
there is
a self-sufficiency
without fashion,
which is intolerable.
Persuaded as Miss
Bingley was, that Darcy
admired.
This was not.
The best method of
recommending herself.
But angry
people are
not always wise.
And in.
Seeing him
at last, looks.
Somewhat nettled.
She had all the success
she expected.
He was
resolutely silent,
however,
and from a
determination of.
Making him speak,
she continued.
I remember when we first
knew her
in Hertfordshire.
How we all were to find
that she was a
reputed beauty.
And I
particularly recollect
your saying one night
after they had
been dining
at Netherfield,
she a beauty.
I should as soon
call her mother a wit.
But afterwards,
she seemed
to improve on you.
And I believe
you thought her
rather prettier
at one time.
Yes, replied Darcy,
who could
contain himself
no longer.
But that was only
when I first knew her.
For it is many months
since I have
considered her
as one of the women
of my acquaintance.
He then went away
and Miss Bingley
was left
to do
all the satisfaction
of having
forced him to say,
which gave no one
any pain but herself.
Mrs.
Gardiner
and Elizabeth
talked of all
that had occurred
during their visit
as they returned.
Except what.
Had particularly
interested them.
Both.
The look.
Behavior of everybody
they had seen
were discussed.
Except.
Of the person
who had mostly engaged
their attention.
They talked
of his sister,
his friends,
his house, his.
Fruit of.
Everything but himself.
Yet Elizabeth
was longing to know
what Mrs.
Gardiner thought of him,
and Mrs.
Gardiner would have been
highly gratified by her
niece's beginning
the subject
Chapter 46.
Elizabeth had
been a good deal
disappointed in
not finding a letter
from Jane
on their first arrival
at Lambton.
And this disappointment
had been renewed
on each of the mornings
that had now
been spent there.
But on the third,
her opining was over
and her sister justified
by the receipt
of two letters
from her at once on
one of which was marked
that it had been mis
sent elsewhere.
Elizabeth was
not surprised at it.
As Jane had written,
the direction
remarkably ill.
They had just
been preparing to walk
as the letters came in
and her uncle and aunt
leaving her
to enjoy them in quiet
set off by themselves.
The one miss sent must
first be attended to.
It had been written
five days ago.
The beginning.
Contained an account
of all their
little parties
and engagements.
With such.
News as the
country afforded
but the latter half
was dated a day later
and written
in evident agitation.
Gave.
More important
intelligence.
It was to this effect
since writing the above
Dearest.
Lizzie,
something has occurred
of a most unexpected
and serious nature.
But I am afraid
of alarming.
You be assured
that we are all well.
What I have to say
relates to poor Lydia.
An express came at 12
last night, just as
we were all gone to bed
from Colonel Foresta
to inform us
that she was going off
to Scotland
with one of
his officers.
To own the truth
with Wickham.
Imagine our surprise
to Kitty.
However,
it does not seem
so wholly unexpected.
I am very,
very sorry.
So imprudent
to match on both sides.
But I am willing to hope
the best
and that his character
is being misunderstood,
thoughtless
and indiscreet.
I can
easily believe him.
But this step
and that is rejoice
over it, marks
nothing bad at heart.
His choice
is disinterested,
at least for
he must know.
My father
can give her nothing.
A poor mother is
sadly grieved.
My father Bassett.
Better.
How thankful.
My that we never.
Let them know
what has been said
against him.
We must forget
it ourselves.
They were off.
Saturday night
at about 12,
as is conjectured.
But were not.
Missed till yesterday
morning at.
Eight.
The express was
sent off directly.
My dear Lizzie,
they must have passed
within ten miles of us.
Colonel Foster gives us.
Reason to expect him.
Here soon.
Lydia left
a few lines
for his wife,
informing her
of their intention.
I Must conclude for
I cannot be long
for my poor mother.
I am afraid
you will not
be able to make it out.
But I hardly know
what I've written.
Without allowing herself
time for consideration
and scarcely
knowing what she felt.
Elizabeth, on
finishing this letter,
instantly
seized the other
and opening it
with the utmost
impatience.
Read as follows.
It had been written
a day later than
the conclusion
of the first.
By this
time, my dearest sister.
You have received
my horrid letter.
I wish this may
be more intelligible.
But though not for time,
my head is so bewildered
that I cannot answer
for being coherent.
Dearest Lizzie,
I hardly know
what I would write.
But I have bad
news for you.
And it cannot
be delayed.
Imprudent
as the marriage
between Mr.
Wickham
and our polity would be,
we are now anxious
to be assured
that it has taken place.
But there is much too,
much reason to fear
they are not
gone to Scotland.
Colonel Foster came
yesterday, having left
Brighton the day before.
Not too many hours.
After the.
Express.
Though Lydia's short
letter to.
Mrs.
F gave them
to understand
that they were going
to Grafton GREENE.
Something was dropped
by Danny
expressing his belief
that W.
Never intended
to go there
or to marry Lydia
at all,
which was repeated
to Colonel F, who
instantly
taking the alarm set off
from B
intending to
trace their out.
He did trace them
easily to Clapham,
but no further for on.
Entering that place.
They removed
into a Hackney coach
and dismissed the shares
that brought
them from Epsom.
All that is known
after this
is that they were seen
to continue
the London Road.
I know
not what to think.
After making
every possible inquiry
on that side of London,
Colonel F
came on
into Hertfordshire,
anxiously renewing.
Them at all
the turnpikes.
And all
the ends in Barnet,
in Hatfield, but.
Without any success.
No such people.
Had been seen to pass.
Through
with the
kindest concern.
He came on to London
and broke
his apprehensions
to us in a manner
most creditable
to his heart.
I am sincerely
grieved for him and.
Mrs. F.
But no one can throw
any blame on them.
Our distress,
Dear Lizzie,
is very great.
My father and mother
believe the worst.
But I cannot think
so ill of him.
Many circumstances.
Might make it
more eligible
for them to.
Be married in town
than to pursue
that first plan.
And even if he could
form such a design.
Against a young woman
of Lydia's connections.
Which is not likely,
can I suppose her
so lost to everything?
Impossible.
I grieve to find
whoever the Colonel F
is not disposed
to depend
upon their marriage.
He shook his head
when I expressed
my hopes
and said he feared W
was not a man
to be trusted.
My poor
mother is really ill
and keeps her room.
Could she exert herself?
It would be better.
But this is not
to be expected
and to my father,
I never in
my life saw him
so affected.
Poor Kitty has anger
for having
concealed their
attachment.
But as it was a matter
of confidence,
one cannot wonder.
I am truly glad.
Dearest Lizzie,
that you have
been spared
something of these
distressing scenes.
But now, as the first
shock is over,
shall I own that?
I long for your return.
I am not so selfish,
however, as
to press for it.
If in convenient adieu,
I take up my
pen again to
do what I have
just told you
I would not.
But circumstances
are such
that I cannot
help earnestly
begging you
all to come here
as soon as possible.
I know my dear
uncle and aunt so well
that I am not afraid
of requesting it,
though
I have still something
more to
ask of the former.
My father is going.
To London
with Colonel
Foster instantly
to try to discover
what he means to do.
I am sure I know not.
But his
excessive distress
will not allow.
Him to pursue
any measure in the
and safest way.
And kind of.
Foster is obliged
to be at Brighton again
tomorrow evening.
In such an exigency,
my uncle's
advice and assistance
would be
everything in the world.
He Will
immediately comprehend
what I must feel.
And I rely upon
his goodness.
Ho! Where?
Where is my uncle?
Cried Elizabeth,
darting from her seat
as she finished
the letter and eagerness
to follow him
without losing
a moment of time
so precious.
But as she reached,
the door was opened
by a servant.
As Mr.
Darcy appeared,
her pale face,
impetuous manner
made him start,
and before
he could recover himself
to speak,
she in whose mind
every idea
was superseded
by Lydia's situation.
Hastily exclaimed,
I beg your pardon,
but I must leave you.
I must find Mr.
Gardiner,
this moment on business
that cannot be delayed.
I have not
an instant to lose.
Good God.
What is the matter?
Cried He,
with more feeling
than politeness, then
recollecting himself.
I will not detain
you a minute, but let me
or let
the servant go off
to Mr.
and Mrs. Gardiner.
You are not well enough.
You cannot go yourself.
Elizabeth hesitated,
but her
knees trembled under her
and she felt
how little
would be gained by her
attempting
to pursue them,
calling back.
The servant,
therefore she
commissioned him,
though in so breathless
an accent has made her
almost unintelligible.
To fetch his master
and mistress,
whom instantly.
On his.
Quitting the room,
she down unable
to support herself,
and looking
so miserably ill
that it was impossible
for Dorothy to leave her
or to refrain
from saying
in a tone of gentleness
and commiseration.
Let me call your.
Is there nothing
you could take
to give you
present relief?
A glass of wine.
Shall I get you one?
You are very ill.
No, I thank you.
She replied, endeavoring
to recover herself.
There is nothing
the matter with me.
I am quite well.
I am only distressed
by some dreadful news
which I have
just received
from long ball.
She burst into tears,
as she alluded to it
and for a few minutes
could not speak
another word.
Darcy, in
wretched suspense,
could only say something
indistinctly
of his concern
and observe her
in compassionate
silence.
At length
she spoke again.
I have just had a letter
from Jane
with such dreadful news.
It cannot be concealed
from anyone.
My younger sister
has all her friends,
has eloped,
has thrown herself
into the power of
of Mr.
Wickham
had gone off together
from Brighton.
You know him too
well to doubt the rest.
She has no money,
no connections,
nothing that
contempt him.
She is lost forever.
Darcy was fixed
in astonishment when.
I consider.
She added, in a yet
more agitated voice.
That I might have
prevented it.
I who knew what he was
had I explained
some part of it.
Some part of what
I learned to
my own family.
Had his character
being known,
this could
not have happened.
But it is all
all too late now.
I am grieved, indeed.
Cried Darcy.
Grieved, shocked.
But is it certain?
Absolutely certain.
Oh, yes.
They left Brighton
together on Sunday night
and were traced
almost to London,
but not beyond.
They are certainly not
gone to Scotland.
And what has been done?
What has been attempted
to recover her?
My father has
gone to London
and Jane has written
to beg my uncle's
immediate assistance.
Had we shall be off,
I hope, in half an hour.
But nothing can be done.
I know very well
that nothing
can be done.
How is such a man
to be worked on?
How are they
even to be discovered?
I have not
the smallest hope.
It is every way
horrible.
Darcy
shook his head, silent.
Acquiescence.
When my eyes
were opened,
his real character,
who had I known
what I thought,
what I dared to do.
But I knew not.
I was afraid of doing
too much wretched,
wretched mistake.
Darcy
made no answer.
He seemed scarcely
to hear her
and was walking up
and down
room in
earnest meditation.
His brow contracted
his air.
Gloomy, Elizabeth
soon observed,
and instantly
understood it.
Her power was sinking.
Everything must under
such a proof
of family weakness.
Such an assurance
of the deepest disgrace.
She could neither
wonder nor condemn.
But the belief
of his self conquest
brought nothing
to her bosom,
afforded no palliation
of her distress.
It was, on the contrary,
exactly calculated
to make her understand
her own wishes
had never had she
so honestly
that she could
have loved him as now,
when all love
must be in vain.
But self,
though it would intrude,
could not engross her
Lydia, the
the misery
she was bringing
on them all.
Soon swallowed up
every private care
and covering her face
with her handkerchief.
Elizabeth was soon
lost to everything else,
and after a pause
of several minutes,
was only recalled to
a sense of her situation
by the voice
of her companion,
who in a manner
which though it spake
compassion, spoke,
restraint said.
I am afraid
you have been
long desiring
my absence.
Nor have I
anything to
plead an excuse
of my stay.
But real though
unavailing concern
with to heaven
that anything
could be
either said
or done on my part
that might
offer consolation
to such distress.
But I will not torment
you with vain wishes,
which may seem purposely
to ask for your things.
This unfortunate
affair will,
I fear, prevent
my sisters
having the pleasure
of seeing
at Pemberley today?
Oh, yes.
Be so kind
as to apologize
for us to Miss Darcy.
Say that
urgent business calls
as I immediately
conceal unhappy truth.
As long as
it is possible.
I know
it cannot be long.
He readily assures her
of his secrecy, again
expressed his sorrow
for her distress.
Wished it a.
Happier conclusion
that there
was at present
reason to hope.
And leaving
his compliments
for her relations
with only one serious
parting look went away.
As he quitted the room.
Elizabeth felt
how improbable
it was that
they should
ever see each
other again
on such terms
of cordiality,
as had marked
their several meetings
in Derbyshire.
And as she threw
a retrospective glance
over the
whole of
their acquaintance.
So.
Full of contradictions
and varieties, sighed
at the perverse
ness of those feelings
which would have now
promoted its
and would formally
have rejoiced
in its termination.
If gratitude and esteem
are good
foundations
of affection.
Elizabeth's change
of sentiment
will be improbable
nor faulty.
But if otherwise,
if regard
springing from
such sources
is unreasonable
or unnatural
in comparison of
what is so often
described
arising on a
first interview
with its object
and even before
two words
have been exchanged,
nothing can be
said in her defense,
except that
she had given
somewhat of a trial
to the latter
in her partiality
for Wickham,
and that its ill
success might perhaps
authorize her
to seek the other,
less interesting
mode of attachment.
Be that as it may,
she saw him
go with regret.
And in this
early example
of what Lydia's infamy
must produce
found additional anguish
as she reflected
on that
wretched business.
Never since reading
Jane's second letter
had she entertained
a hope of Wickham's
meaning to marry her.
No one but Jane,
she thought,
could flatter
herself with such an.
Expectation.
Was the least of her
feelings
on this development.
While the contents
of the first letter
remained in her mind,
she was all surprise,
all astonishment
that Wickham
should marry a girl
whom it was impossible
could marry for money.
And how Lydia could
ever have attached
him had appeared
incomprehensible.
But now it was
all too natural
for such an attachment
as this.
She have
sufficient charms.
And though she did not.
Suppose Lydia
to be
deliberately engaging
in an elopement
without the
intention of marriage,
she had no difficulty
in believing
that neither her virtue
nor understanding
would preserve her
from falling
an easy prey
she had never perceived,
while the regiment
was in Hertfordshire
that Lydia had any
partiality for him.
But she was convinced
that Lydia wanted
only encouragement
to attach herself
to anybody.
Sometimes one officer,
sometimes
another had been
her favorite
as their attentions
raised them in
her opinion.
her affections had
continually
been fluctuating,
but never
without an object.
The mischief of.
Neglect and mistaken
indulgence towards
such a girl.
Oh, how acutely
did she now feel it?
She was wild to be.
At home, to hear,
to see, to be upon.
The spot,
to share with Jane
in the cares
that must now
fall wholly upon her
in a family so deranged.
A father absent,
a mother incapable
of exertion
and requiring
constant attendance.
And though
almost persuaded.
That nothing
could be done for Lydia,
her uncles interference
seemed of the
utmost importance.
Until he entered
the room,
her patients
were severe.
Mr. and Mrs.
Gardner
had hurried
back in alarm.
Supposing by
the servants
account,
their niece was taken
suddenly ill.
But satisfying them
instantly on that head,
she eagerly communicated
the cause of
their summons, reading
the two letters aloud
and dwelling
on the postscript
of the last
with trembling energy.
Though
Lydia had never been
a favorite with them.
Mr. and Mrs.
Gardner could not be
but deeply afflicted.
Not Lydia only,
but all were
concerned in it.
And after the
first exclamations
of surprise
and horror, Mr.
Gardner
promised
every assistance
in his power.
Elizabeth, though
expecting no less,
thanked him
with tears of gratitude.
And all three
being actuated
by one spirit.
Everything relating
to their journey
was speedily settled.
They were to be off
as soon as possible.
But what is
to be done about?
Cried Mrs.
Gardner.
John told us Mr.
Darcy was here
when you sent for us.
Was it so?
Yes.
And I told him
we should not
be able
to keep our engagement.
That is all settled.
What is all settled?
Repeated the other
as she
ran into her
room to prepare.
And are they upon
such terms
as for how to disclose
the real truth?
Oh, that.
I knew how it was,
but wishes.
Were vain, or at least
could only serve
to amuse her
in the hurry
and confusion
of the following hour.
Had Elizabeth
been at leisure
to be idle.
She would have
remained certain
that all employment
was impossible to one
so wretched as herself.
But she had her share
of business
as well as her aunt.
And amongst the rest
notes to be written
to all their friends
at Lampton with false
excuses
for their
sudden departure.
An hour, however, saw
the whole completed
and Mr.
Gardiner,
meanwhile having
settled his account
at the end.
Nothing remained
to be done but to go.
And Elizabeth,
after all
the misery
of the morning,
found herself
in a shorter
space of time
that she could have.
Supposed.
Seated the carriage
and on
the road to London.
Chapter 47.
I have been
thinking it over again.
Elizabeth said
her uncle,
as they drove
from the town.
And really, upon
serious consideration,
I am much more inclined
than I was
to judge,
as your eldest sister
does, on the matter.
It appears to me
so very unlikely
that any young man
should form
such a design
against a girl
who is by means
unprotected
or friendless,
and who is
actually staying
in his colonel's family,
that I am
strongly inclined
to hope the best.
Could he expect
that her friends
would not step forward?
Could he expect
to be noticed again
by the regiment
after such an affront
to Colonel Foster?
His temptation
is not adequate
to the risk.
Do you really think so?
Cried Elizabeth,
brightening up
for a moment.
Upon my word.
Said Mrs.
Gardiner.
I begin to be of
your uncle's opinion.
It is really too great
a violation
of decency, honor
and for him
to be guilty of.
I cannot think so.
Very ill of Wickham.
Can you yourself,
Lizzie,
so wholly give him up?
Has to
believe I am
capable of it.
Not Perhaps of
neglecting his
own interest,
but of every
other neglect.
I can believe him
capable, if indeed
it should be so.
But I dare not hope it.
Why should they not
go on to Scotland
if that had
been the case.
In the first place?
Replied Mr.
Gardner.
There is no
absolute proof
that they are not gone
to Scotland.
Oh, but they're removing
the shares
and into a Hackney coach
is such a presumption.
And besides, no.
Traces of them
were to be found
on the Barnet Road.
Well, then,
supposing them
be in London.
They may be
there, though,
for the purpose
of concealment
for no more
exceptional purpose.
It is not likely
that money
should be very on either
side.
And it might strike them
that they could be
more economically,
though
less expeditiously
married in London
than in Scotland.
But why all
this secrecy?
Why any
fear of detection?
Why must their marriage
be private?
Oh, no, no.
This is not likely.
Most particular friend,
you see, by
Jean's account
was persuaded
of his
never intending
to marry her.
Wickham will never
marry a woman
without some money.
He cannot afford it.
And What claims
has Lydia?
What attraction has
she beyond youth health
and good humor
that could make him,
for her sake, forego.
Every chance
of benefiting himself.
By marrying?
Well
As to what restraint
the apprehensions
of disgrace
in the Corps might throw
on dishonorable
elopement with her.
I am not able
to judge, for
I know nothing
of the effect
that such a step
might produce.
But as to your
other objection,
I am afraid
it will hardly hold.
Good.
Lydia has no brothers
to step forward,
and he might
imagine for.
My father's.
Behavior
from his indolence
and the.
Little attention he's
ever seemed to give to.
What was going forward
in his family,
that he would
do as little.
And think as
little about it as any
could do in such.
A matter.
But can you think that
Lydia
so lost to everything
but love of him
as to consent,
to live with him
in any terms
other than marriage?
It does seem,
and it is most
shocking indeed.
Replied Elizabeth,
with tears in her eyes.
That a sister's
sense of decency
and virtue
in such a point
could admit of doubt.
But really, I know
not what to say.
Perhaps I am not
doing her justice.
But she is very young.
She has never
been taught to think
on a serious.
And for the
last half year,
nay, for 12 month,
she has been given up
to nothing but amusement
and to vanity.
She's been allowed
to dispose of her time
in the most idle
and frivolous manner
and to adopt
any opinions.
That came in.
Her way since the Blank
were first courted
in Britain.
Nothing but
love, flirtation,
and officers
have been in her head.
She has been
doing everything
in her power
by thinking.
And talking
on the subject
to give greater,
what shall I call it,
susceptibility to her
feelings,
which naturally
lively enough.
And we all know that
Wickham has every charm
of person and address
that can
captivate a woman.
But do you see that?
Jane said her Aunt.
Just not thinks a very
ill of Wickham
as to believe
and capable
of the attempt.
Of whom does
Jane ever think ill?
And who is there?
Whatever might be
that form of conduct
that she would think
capable of
such an attempt
till it were proved
against them?
But Jane knows.
As well as I do.
What Wickham really is.
We both know
that he has
been profligate
in every sense
of the word,
but he has
neither integrity
nor honor that he is
as false and deceitful
as he is insinuating.
And do you really know
all this kind, Mrs.
Gardiner?
His curiosity
as to the mode of her
intelligence was
all alive?
I do indeed.
Replied
Elizabeth Coloring.
I Told you the other.
Day of his infamous
behavior to.
Mr. Darcy.
And you yourself,
when last at long boon
heard, in what manner?
He spoke of the man
who had behaved
with such forbearance
liberality towards him.
And there are
other circumstances
which I am not
at liberty, which
it is not worthwhile
to relate.
But his.
Lies about.
The whole
Pemberley family
Endless.
From what he said of
Miss Darcy,
I was thoroughly
prepared
to see a proud,
reserved,
disagreeable girl.
Yet he knew
to the contrary himself.
He must know.
That was as amiable
and on
pretending as
we have found. Her.
But does
Lydia know
nothing of this?
Can she be as ignorant
of what
you and Jane seem so
well to understand?
Yes That is
the worst of it all.
Till I was in Kent
and saw so much.
Both of Mr.
Darcy and his relation,
Colonel Fitzwilliam.
I was ignorant
of the truth myself.
And when I returned home
the blank,
she was to leave.
Married in a week
or fortnight's time,
as that was the case.
Neither Jane, to whom
I related the whole nor
I thought it necessary
to make our
knowledge public
for what to use.
Could it
apparently be to anyone
that the good opinion,
which all
the neighborhood
had of him,
should then
be overthrown?
And even when
it was settled
that Lydia should go
with Mrs.
Forster, the necessity
of opening her eyes
to his character
never occurred to me
that she could be
in any danger.
From the deception.
Never entered my head
that such a consequence
as this could ensue,
you may easily
believe, was
far enough from
my thoughts
when they all
removed to Brighton.
Therefore you
had no reason,
I suppose
to believe them
fond of each other.
Not the slightest.
I can remember
no symptom of affection
on either side.
And had anything
of the kind
been perceptible.
You must be aware
that ours is
not a family
on which
it could be thrown away.
When first
he entered the Corps.
She was ready
enough to admire him.
But.
So we all were.
Every girl in or near
Meriton
was out of her senses
about him.
For the
first two months,
but he never
distinguished her by any
particular attention.
And consequently,
after a.
Moderate period
of extravagant and wild.
Admiration, her fancy
for him
gave way and others
of the regiment
who treated her
with more distinction
again became
her favorites.
It may be.
Easily.
Believed that however.
Little of novelty
could be added.
Their fears, hopes
and conjectures
on this interesting.
Subject
by its
repeated discussion.
No other
could detain them
from it
long during
the whole of the journey
from Elizabeth,
it was never absent
fixed there
by the keenest
of all anguish,
self reproach.
She could find.
No interval of ease
or forgetfulness.
They traveled
as expeditious
as possible
and sleeping
one night on the road
reached long borne
by dinnertime
the next day.
It was a comfort
to Elizabeth
to consider that
Jane could not
have been wearied
by long expectation.
The little gardener's,
attracted
by the sight
of his shares,
were standing
on the steps
of the house
as they entered
the paddock,
and when the carriage
drove up to the door,
the joyful surprise
that lighted up
their faces
and displayed itself
over their whole bodies
in a variety of capers
and frisks
was the first pleasing
earnest
of their welcome.
Elizabeth jumped out,
and after giving each
of them, a hasty kiss
hurried into
the vestibule, where
Jane,
who came running down
from her mother's
apartment, immediately
met her Elizabeth,
as she affectionately
embraced her,
whilst tears
filled the eyes of.
Both lost not a moment.
And asking
whether anything
had been heard of.
Fugitives.
Not yet,
replied Jane.
But now that
my dear uncle,
come,
I hope
everything will be well.
Is my father in town?
Yes.
He went on Tuesday,
as I wrote you.
Word.
And have you heard
from him often?
We have heard twice.
He wrote to me
a few lines on.
Wednesday to say that
he had arrived
in. Safety
and to give me
his directions,
which I particularly
begged him to do.
He merely added
that he should
write again
till he had something
of importance
to mention.
And my mother.
How is she?
How are you all?
My mother is
tolerably well.
I trust, though
his spirits are
greatly shaken.
She is upstairs.
And will have.
Great satisfaction
in seeing you all.
She does not yet
leave her dressing room.
Mary and Kitty, thank.
Heaven a quite well.
But you.
How are you?
Cried Elizabeth.
You look pale.
How much you must have
gone through?
Her sister,
however, assured her
of being perfectly well.
And their conversation,
which had been passing
while Mr. and Mrs.
Gardner were engaged
with their children,
was now put an end
to by the approach
of the whole party.
Jane ran to her uncle
and and welcomed
and thanked them both
with alternate smiles
and tears
when they were all
in the drawing room.
The questions
which Elizabeth
had already asked
were, of course,
repeated by the others,
and they soon found that
Jane had no intelligence
to give.
The sanguine
hope of good, however,
which the benevolence
of her heart suggested
had not yet
deserted her.
She still expected that
it would all end well,
and that every morning
would bring some letter
either from Lydia
or her father
to explain
their proceedings
and perhaps announce
their marriage.
Mrs.
Bennet, to
whose apartment
they all repaired
after a few minutes
conversation together,
received them exactly
as might be expected
with tears
and lamentations
of regret in
against the
villainous conduct
of Wickham.
And.
Complaints of her own
sufferings
and ill usage.
Blaming everybody
but the person to
whose ill
judging indulgence
the heirs of
her daughter
must principally be own.
If I had been able,
said she, to carry
my point
in going to Brighton
with all my family,
this would not
have happened.
But poor dear
Lydia had nobody
to take care of her.
Why did the forced
as ever
let go out
of their sight?
I am sure
there was some
great neglect
or other on that side,
for she is not the kind
of girl
to do such a thing.
If she had been
well looked after.
I always thought
they were very unfit
to have the
charge of her.
But I was overruled,
as I always am.
Dear child.
And now his Mr.
Bennett gone away.
And I know he will
fight Wicked
whenever he meets him.
And then he would
be killed.
I would just become
this all the colonies
will turn us out
before he is
cold in his grave.
And if you
are not kind to
us, brother,
I do not know
what we shall do.
They all.
Exclaimed.
Against such
terrific ideas.
And Mr.
Gardner,
after general assurances
of his affection for her
and all her family,
told her
that he meant to be
in London
the very next day
and would assist Mr.
Bennett
in every endeavor
for recovering Lydia.
Do not give way
to useless alarm, added
he though
it is right
to be prepared
for the worst.
There is no occasion
to look on it.
A certain
It is not quite a week
since they
left Brighton.
In a few days more
we may gain
some news of them
until we know
that they are
not married
and have no design
of marrying.
Do not let us give
the matter over as lost.
As soon as I get
to town.
I shall go to my brother
and make him come home
with me to Grace
Church Street.
And then we may
consult together
as to what is
to be done.
Oh, my
dear brother,
replied Mrs.
Bennett.
That is exactly
what I could
most wish for.
Now, do you,
when you shall
get to town,
find them out
wherever they may be.
And if they are
not married already,
make them marry
and ask for
wedding clothes.
Do not let them
wait that.
But tell Lydia
she shall have
as much money
as she chooses
to buy them
after they married.
And above all, keep Mr.
Bennett from fighting.
Tell him what
a dreadful state
I am in that
I am frightened
out of my wits
and have such trembling,
such fluttering all over
me, such spasms
in my side
and pains in my head
and such beatings
at heart
that I can get no rest
by night or day.
And tell my dear Lydia
not to give
any directions
about her clothes
till she has seen me,
because she
does not know
which are the
best warehouses.
So rather
how kind you are.
I know you will contrive
it all.
But Mr.
Gardiner, though
he assured her again
of his earnest endeavors
in the cause.
Could not avoid.
Recommending moderation
her as well
in her hopes
as her fear.
And after
talking with her
in this manner
till dinner
was on the table,
they all left her
to vent
all her feelings
on the housekeeper
who attended.
In the absence.
Her daughters,
though her brother
and sister,
were persuaded
that there was
no real occasion
for such a seclusion
from the family.
They did not attempt
to oppose it, for.
They knew that
she had not prudence
to hold her tongue
before the servants,
while they waited.
At the table and judged.
It better that one
only of the household
and the one whom
they could most trust
should comprehend
all her fears
and solicitude
on the subject.
In the dining room,
they were soon
joined by
Mary and Kitty,
who had been too busily
engaged
in their
separate apartments
to make their
appearance before
one came from her books
and the other
from her toilette.
The faces of both,
however,
were tolerably calm.
And no.
Change was visible
in either,
except that the loss,
her favorite sister
or the anger
which she had herself
incurred in
this business.
Had.
Given
more of fruitfulness
than usual
to the accents of Kitty.
As for Mary, she.
Was mistress.
Of herself to whisper
to Elizabeth
with a countenance
of grave reflection.
Soon after,
they were seated
at the table.
This is a most
unfortunate affair
and will probably be
much of.
But we must stem
the tide of malice
and pour
into the wounded bosoms
of each other.
The bottom of sisterly
consolation.
Then, perceiving
Elizabeth
had no intention
of replying, she added.
Unhappy as the event
must be for Lydia.
We may draw from it
this useful lesson
that loss of.
Virtue in a.
Female irretrievable.
That one false
step involves
an endless ruin.
That reputation
is no less brittle
than it is beautiful,
and that she cannot
be too guarded in her
behavior towards the.
Undeserving of
the other sex.
Elizabeth lifted up
her eyes in amazement,
but was too
much oppressed
to make any reply.
Mary, however,
continued to
console herself
with such kind
of moral extractions
from the evil
before them.
In the afternoon,
the two elder
Miss Bennetts
were able to be
for a half hour
themselves,
and Elizabeth instantly
availed herself
of the opportunity
of making any inquiries.
Which Jane.
Was equally eager
to satisfy.
After joining
in general,
Lamentations over,
the dreadful
sequel of this event,
which Elizabeth
considered as all
but certain and Mr.
Bennett could not assert
to be wholly impossible.
The former
continued the subject
by saying,
But Tell me all
and everything about it,
which I.
Have not already heard.
Give me further
particulars.
Watched it, Colonel.
Forced to say
How do they knew
apprehension of anything
before the elopement
took place?
They must have seen
them together forever,
kind of forced to do it.
And that he has
often suspected
some partiality,
especially on
Lydia's side.
But nothing to
give him any.
I am so
grieved for him.
His behavior
was attentive
and kind to the utmost.
He was coming to us
in order
to assure us
of his concern
before he had
any idea of
then not being gone
to Scotland.
When that apprehension
first got abroad.
It hastened his journey
and was deeply convinced
that Wickham
would not marry.
Did he know of there
intending to go off?
Had Colonel forced
to send any himself?
Yes.
But when
questioned by him,
Danny denied.
Knowing anything
of their.
Plans
and not give his real
opinion about it.
He did not repeat
his persuasion
of their not marrying.
And from that
I am inclined to.
Hope
he might have
been misunderstood
before
and till Colonel
Foster came himself.
Not one of you
entertained a doubt, I.
Suppose, of that.
Being really married.
How is it possible
that such an idea
should enter our brains?
I felt a little uneasy,
a little fearful of.
My sister's happiness.
With him in marriage,
because I know
that his conduct
had not been always
quite right.
My father
and mother knew
nothing of that.
They only felt
imprudent to match.
It must be.
Kitty, then owned
with a
very natural triumph
on knowing more
than the rest of us
that in Lydia's
last letter, she had.
Prepared for such a.
Step.
She had known, it.
Seems, of their
being in love with
each other many. Weeks,
but not before they
went to Brighton.
No, I believe not.
And did Colonel
Faust prepared
think Well,
if we can himself.
Does he know
his real character?
I must confess
that he did
not speak so
well of Wickham
as he formally did.
He believed him
to be imprudent
and extravagant.
And since.
This sad
affair has taken.
Place,
it is said that he left.
Meriton greatly in debt.
But I hope
this may be false.
How?
Jane, had we been
less secret.
Had we told what we
knew of him,
this could not
have happened.
Perhaps it would
have been better.
Replied her sister.
But to expose the former
faults
of any person without.
Knowing what
that present
feelings were.
Seemed unjustifiable.
We acted with
the best intentions.
Could Colonel
forced to repeat
the particulars
of Lydia's to his wife?
He brought it with him
for us to see.
Jane then
took it from
her pocketbook
and gave it to Lydia.
These were the contents
of my dearest Harriet.
You will laugh
and you know where I am
gone.
And I cannot help
laughing myself
at your surprise.
Tomorrow morning,
as soon as I am missed,
I am going to
Gretna green.
And if you cannot guess
with who
I shall think
you a simpleton.
But there is
but one man
in the world I love.
And he is an angel.
I should never be happy
without him.
So think it's
no harm to be off.
You need
to send the word
long one to by going.
If you do not like it
here,
it will make
the surprise
the greater.
When I write to them
and sign my name.
Lydia Wickham.
What a good joke
will be.
I can hardly write
for laughing, pray,
make my excuses to Pratt
for not keeping
my engagement
and dancing
with him tonight.
Tell him I hope he will
excuse me. What?
He knows all.
And tell him
I will dance with him.
At the next ball
We meet with
great pleasure.
I shall send
for my clothes
when I get along.
Born.
But I wish
you would tell
Sally to mend
a great slit
in my worked bosom gown.
They are packed up.
Goodbye.
Give my love
to Kyle Foster.
I hope you will drink
to our good Ajani,
your affectionate
friend.
Lydia Bennet.
Oh, thoughtless
thoughtless.
Lydia.
Cried Elizabeth
when she
had finished it.
What a letter
is this
to be written
at such a moment.
But at least
it shows that.
She was serious on
the subject
of that journey.
Whatever he might
afterwards
persuade her to.
It was not on her side.
A scheme of infamy.
My poor father.
How he must
have felt it.
I never saw anyone
so shocked.
He could not speak
a word for full
10 minutes.
My mother was taken
ill immediately
and the whole house,
in such confusion.
Oh, Jane.
Cried Elizabeth.
Was there a servant
belonging to it
to do not to know
the whole story
before
the end of the day?
I do not know.
I hope there was.
But to be guarded
at such a
time is very difficult.
My mother was
in hysterics,
and though I endeavored
to give her
every assistance
in my power,
I'm afraid I did not
so much as I
might have done.
But the horror
of what
might possibly happen
almost took from me
my faculties.
Your attendance upon her
has been too
much for you.
You do not look well.
Oh, that I had
been with you.
You have had every care
and anxiety
upon yourself alone.
Mary and Katie
have been very kind
and would have shat
in every fatigue.
I am sure.
But I did not think it
right for.
Either of them.
Katie is slight
and delicate,
and Mary studies
so much.
The 2 hours of repose
should not to
be broken in on.
My Aunt Philips
came too long.
Born on Tuesday
after my father
went away
and was so good
as to stay till.
Thursday with me.
She was of great.
Use and comfort
to us all.
And Lady
Lucas has been
very kind.
She walked here
on Wednesday
morning to cando with us
and offered her services
or any of her daughters
if they should be
of any use to us.
She had better.
Have stayed at home,
cried Elizabeth.
Perhaps she.
Meant.
Well,
but under
such a misfortune
as this, one cannot see
too little
of one's neighbors.
Assistance
is impossible.
Condolence insufferable.
Let them triumph over us
at a distance
and be satisfied.
She then proceeded
to inquire
into the measures
which her father
had intended
to pursue while in town
for the recovery
of his daughter.
He meant, I believe,
replied Jane.
To go to Epsom,
the place
where they
last changed horses,
see the Bostonians.
And try
if anything,
could be made.
Out from them.
His principal
must be to discover
the number
of the Hackney coach
which took
them from Clapham.
It had come with a
fare from London
and as he thought
that the circumstance
of a.
Gentleman and ladies
for moving from
one carriage into.
Another
might be remarked
he meant to make
inquiries at Clapham
if he could
anyhow discover
at what house
the coachman had before
set down his fare.
He determined
make inquiries there
and hoped
it might not
be impossible
to find out the stand
and number of the coach.
I do not know
of any other designs
that he had formed, but
he was in such a hurry
to gone and.
His spirit so great.
He just composed that
I had difficulty
in finding out,
even so much as this.
Chapter 48.
The whole party
were in hopes
of a letter from Mr.
Bennett
to the next morning,
but the Post came in
without bringing
a single line from him.
His Family knew
him to be on
all common occasions,
a most negligent
and dilatory
correspondent, but
at such a time
they had hoped
for exertion.
They were forced
to conclude
that he had no pleasing
intelligence to send.
But even of that
they would
have been glad
to be certain.
Mr.
Gardiner had waited
only for the letters
before he set off.
When he was gone,
they were certain
at least
of receiving
constant information
of what was going on,
and their uncle promised
at parting
to prevail on Mr.
Bennett
to return to Long Bourn
as soon as he.
Could.
To the great consolation
of his sister,
who considered it
as the only security
for her husband's
not being killed
in a duel.
Mrs.
Gardiner
and the children
were to remain
in Hertfordshire
a few days longer
as the former thought
her presence
might be serviceable
to her nieces.
She shared in
their attendance on Mrs.
Bennett
and was a great comfort
to them
in their hours
of freedom.
Their other aunt also
visited them frequently,
and as always,
as she said,
with the design
of cheering
and heartening them up,
though as she never came
without reporting
some fresh instance
of Wickham's
extravagance
or irregularity,
she seldom went away
without leaving them
more dispirited
than she found. Them.
All merit
and seemed striving
to blacken the man who.
But three months before
had been almost
an angel of light.
He was declared
to be indebted
to every tradesman
in the place,
and his intrigues,
all honored
with the title
of seduction,
had extended into
every tradesman family.
Everybody declared
that he was
the wickedest
young man in the world
and everybody began
to find out
that they had
always distrusted
the appearance
of his goodness.
Elizabeth,
though she did not
credit above
half of what was said,
believed enough
to make her
former assurance
of her sister's
ruin more certain.
And even Jane,
who still less of it,
became almost hopeless.
More especially
as the time
was now, come.
When if they had.
Gone to Scotland.
Which.
She had never before,
entirely despaired.
They must, in
all probability, have
gained some
news of them.
Mr.
Gardiner left
along born on Sunday.
On Tuesday,
his wife received
a letter from him.
It told them that
on his arrival
he had immediately
found out his brother
and persuaded him
to come to Grace
Church Street.
But Mr.
Bennett had been
to Epsom and Clapham
before his arrival, but
without getting any
satisfactory
information,
and that he was
now determined
to inquire
at all
the principal hotels
in town as Mr.
Bennett
thought it possible
that they
might have gone
to one of them
on their
first coming to London
before they
procured lodgings.
Mr.
Gardner himself
did not expect
any success
from this measure,
but as his brother
was eager in it,
he meant to assist him
in pursuing it.
He added that Mr.
Bennett seemed
wholly disinclined
at present
to leave London
and promised
to write again
very soon.
There was also
a postscript
to this fact.
I have written
to Colonel Foster
to desire him
to find out,
if possible,
from some of
the young men's
intimates in
the regiment,
whether Wickham has
any relations
or connections.
Who would be likely
to know
in what part of the town
he has now
concealed himself?
If there were anyone
that one could apply to
with the probability
gaining
such a clue as that
it might be
of essential
consequence.
At present, we have
nothing to guide us.
Colonel Foster will,
I daresay,
do everything
in his power
to satisfy us
on this head.
But on second thoughts.
Perhaps Lizzy
could tell us
what relations
he has
now living
better than any
other person.
Elizabeth
was at no loss
to understand
from whence
this deference
to her
authority proceeded.
But it was.
Not in her power
to give any information
of so satisfactory
a nature
as the compliment.
She had never
heard of his having
had any relations
except to father
and mother, both of whom
had been dead
many years.
It was possible,
however, that
some of his companions,
the blank share,
might be able
to give
more information.
And though
she was not
very sanguine
in expecting it,
the application
was something
to look forward to
every day as long born
was now
a day of anxiety.
But the most anxious
part of each was
when the post
was expected.
The arrival of letters
was the grand object
of every morning.
Some patience
through letters,
whatever of good or bad
was to be
told to be communicated.
And every succeeding day
was expected
to bring
some news of importance.
But before they heard
again, Mr.
Gardiner, a letter
arrived for their father
from a different quarter
from Mr.
Collins.
Which, as Jane, had.
Received directions
to open
all that came for him
in his absence.
She accordingly read
and Elizabeth
who knew
what curiosities
his letters always were
looked over her
and read it likewise.
It was as follows.
My dear sir,
I feel myself
called upon
by our relationship
and my situation in life
to condole with you
on the
grievous affliction
you are now under,
of which
we were yesterday
informed by a letter
from Hertfordshire.
Be assured, my dear
sir, that Mrs.
Collins and myself
sincerely sympathize
you and
all your
respectable family
in your
present distress,
which must be of the
bitterest kind,
because proceeding
from a cause
which no time
can remove,
no arguments
shall be wanting
on my part
that can alleviate
so severe a misfortune,
or that may comfort
you under a circumstance
that must be
of all others
the most
afflicting to a parent's
mind.
The death of
your daughter
would have been
a blessing
in comparison of this.
And it is the
more to be lamented
because there is reason
to suppose,
as my dear
Charlotte informs
me, that
this licentiousness
of behavior
in your daughter
has proceeded
from a faulty
degree of indulgence,
though at the same time,
for the consolation
of yourself and Mrs.
Bennett,
I am inclined to think
that her own disposition
must be naturally bad,
or she could not
be guilty
of such an enormity.
And so early in age,
howsoever that may be,
you are grievously
to be pitied,
in which opinion
I am not only joined
by Mrs.
Collins, but likewise
by Lady Catherine
and her daughter,
to whom I have related
the affair.
They agree with me
in apprehending
that this false step
in one daughter
would be injurious
to the fortunes
of all the others.
For who,
as Lady
Catherine herself
condescendingly says,
will connect themselves
with such a family.
And this consideration
leads me to reflect
with augmented
satisfaction
on a certain
event of last November
four.
Had it been otherwise,
I must have
been involved
in all
your sorrow
and disgrace.
Let me then advise
you, dear sir,
to console yourself
as much as possible
to throw off her
unworthy child
from your
affection forever
and leave her
to reap the fruits
of her own happiness.
Now I am
dear sir, etc., etc..
Mr.
Gardner did
not write again
till he had received
an answer
from Colonel Forrester.
And then he had nothing
of a pleasant
nature to send.
It was not known
that Wickham had a.
Single relationship
with whom
he kept up
any connection,
and it was certain
that he had
no one near living.
His former
acquaintances had
been numerous,
but since
he had been in the.
Militia it did not.
Appear that
he was on terms
of particular friendship
with any of them.
There was no one
there for
who could be pointed out
as likely
give any news of him.
And in the
wretched state.
Of his own finances,
there was a very
powerful motive
for secrecy.
In addition
to his fear of discovery
by Lydia's relations,
for it
had just transpired
that he had left
gaming debts behind him
to a very
considerable amount.
Colonel Forrester
believed that
more than ?1,000
would be necessary
to clear his expenses.
Brighton.
He owed a great
deal in town.
But his debts.
Of honor
were still
more formidable.
Mr.
Gardner did not attempt
to conceal
these particulars
from the long
born family.
Jane heard them
with horror.
Games after.
She cried.
This is
wholly unexpected.
I had not an idea of it.
Mr.
Gardner added
in his letter
that they might expect
to see their father
at home
on the following day,
which was Saturday,
rendered spiritless
by the
ill success
of all their endeavors.
He had yielded
to his brother
in law's entreaty
that he would
return to his family
and leave it to him
to do
whatever occasion
might suggest
to be advisable
for continuing
their pursuit.
When Mrs.
Bennett was
told of this,
she did not
express so much.
Satisfaction
as her children
expected,
considering what
her anxiety for his life
had been before.
What is he coming home
and without Lydia?
She cried.
Sure,
he will not leave London
before
he has found them.
Who is to fight Wickham
and make him marry her?
If he comes away as.
Mrs. Gardner to.
Wish to be at home.
It was settled
that she and
the children
should go to London
at the same time
that Mr.
Bennett came from it.
The coach
therefore took them
at the first stage
of their journey
and brought Master
back to Long Bourne.
Mrs.
Gardner went away
in all the perplexity
about Elizabeth
and her
Derbyshire friend
that had
attended her from
that part of the world.
His name had never been
voluntarily mentioned
before them by her.
Niece and the kind.
Of half expectation
which Mrs.
Gardner had formed
of there
being followed
by a letter from him,
had ended in nothing.
Elizabeth had received
none since her return
that could come
from Pemberley.
The present unhappy
state of the family
rendered
any other excuse
for the onus
of her spirits
unnecessary.
Nothing, therefore,
could be
fairly conjectured
from that, though.
Elizabeth,
who was by this time
tolerably
well acquainted with
her own feelings,
was perfectly aware
that had she know
nothing of Darcy,
she could have borne
the dread
of Lydia's infamy
somewhat better.
It would have
spared her, she thought,
one sleepless
night out of two.
When Mr.
Bennett arrived,
he all the appearance
of his usual
philosophic composure.
He said as little as
he had ever been
in the habit of saying,
made no mention
of the business
that had taken him away.
And it was some time
before his daughters
had courage
to speak of it.
It was not until
the afternoon
when he had joined them
at tea
that Elizabeth ventured
to introduce.
The subject.
And then on her
briefly
expressing her sorrow
for what
he must have endured,
he replied.
Say nothing of that.
Who should suffer
but myself?
It has been my own doing
and I ought to feel it.
You must not be too
severe upon yourself.
Replied Elizabeth.
You may well warn me
against such an evil.
Human nature
is so prone
to fall into it.
No, Lizzie,
let me once in my life
feel how much I have
been to blame.
I'm not afraid of
being overpowered
by the impression
it will pass away soon
enough.
Do you suppose, then,
to be in London?
Yes.
Where else
can they be so
well concealed?
And Lydia
used to want to
go to London.
Added Kitty.
She's happy then.
Said her father dryly.
And her residents
there will probably be
of some duration.
Then,
after a short silence,
he continued.
Lizzie,
I beg you no ill will
for being justified
in your advice to me
last May, which,
considering the event,
shows some greatness
of mind.
They were interrupted
by Miss Bennett,
who came to fetch her
mother's tea.
This is a parade.
Cried he,
which does one good.
It gives such elegance
to misfortune.
Another day
I will do the same.
I will sit
in my library,
in my nightcap
and powdering gown
and give as much trouble
as I can.
Or perhaps I may defer
it till Kitty runs away.
I am not
going to run away, Papa.
Said Kitty, frightfully.
If I should ever go
to Brighton.
I would behave
better than Lydia.
You go to Brighton.
I would not trust you
so near it as Eastbourne
for ?50.
No, Kitty,
I have at least
learned to be cautious.
And you will feel
the effects it.
No officer is ever
to enter my house again,
nor even to pass through
the village.
Bulls will be
absolutely prohibited
unless you stand up
with one of your sisters
and you are
never to
stir out of doors
till you can prove
that you have spent
10 minutes of every day
in a rational manner.
Kitty, who took.
All these threats
in a serious
began to cry.
Well, well, said he.
Do not make yourself
unhappy
if you are a good girl
for the next ten years.
I will take you to a
review at the
end of them.
Chapter 49.
Two days after Mr.
Bennett's return.
As Jane and Elizabeth
were walking together
in the shrubbery
behind the house.
They saw the housekeeper
coming towards them.
And.
Concluding that
she came to call them
to their mother,
went forward
to meet her.
But instead of
the expected summons
when they
approached her,
she said to
Miss Bennett.
I beg your.
Pardon, madam,
for interrupting you,
but I was in hopes
that you might have had
some good news
from town.
So I took the liberty
of coming to ask,
What do you mean?
We've nothing from town,
Dear Madam.
Cried Mrs.
Hale in
great astonishment.
Don't you know
there is an express
come for Master of Mr.
Gardner?
He's been here
this half hour
and Master
has had a letter.
A way round the girls
too eager to get in,
to have time for speech.
They ran through
the vestibule
into the breakfast room
from thence
to the library.
Their father
was in neither,
and they were
on the point
of seeking him upstairs
with their mother
when they were met
by the butler, who said.
If you were looking
for my master, ma'am,
he is walking
towards the
little copse.
Upon this information.
They instantly passed
through the hall
once more and ran
across the lawn
after their father.
He was deliberately
pursuing his way
towards the small wood
on one side
of the paddock.
Jane, who was not.
So light
nor so much in the habit
of running as Elizabeth,
soon lagged behind
while her sister
panting for breath.
Came up with him.
And eagerly out.
Her papa.
What news?
Have you heard
from my uncle?
Yes, I've had a letter
from him by Express.
Well, and
what news does it bring,
good or bad?
What is there of
good to be expected?
Said he,
taking the letter
from his pocket.
But perhaps
you would like
to read it.
Elizabeth impatiently
caught it from his hand.
Jane now came up.
Read it aloud.
Said their father.
For I hardly know myself
what it is about.
Grace Church Street,
Monday, August 2nd.
My dear
brother, at last,
I am able to send you
some tidings of my niece
and such as upon
the whole.
I hope
it will give
you satisfaction.
Soon after you
left me on Saturday,
I was fortunate enough
to find out in
what part of London
they were.
The particulars I was of
Till we meet.
It is enough to know
they are discovered.
I have seen them both.
Then it is
as I always hoped.
Cried Jane.
They are married.
Elizabeth.
Read on.
I have seen them both.
They are not married.
Nor can I find
there was any
intention of being so.
But if you are willing
to perform
the engagements
which I have ventured
to make on your side,
I hope it will
not be long
before they are.
All that is required
of you is to assure
to your daughter
by settlement her equal
share of the ?5,000
secured
among your children
after the decease
of yourself
and my sister.
And moreover, to enter.
Into an agreement of.
Allowing during her life
?100 per annum.
These are conditions
which considering
everything.
I had no hesitation
in complying with
as far as
I thought myself.
Privileged for.
I shall send this
by express that no time
may be lost
in bringing me
your answer.
You will
easily comprehend
from these particulars
that Mr.
Wickham circumstances
are not so hopeless
as they had
generally believed
to be.
The world
has been deceived
in that respect,
and I am happy to say
there would be
some little money.
Even when all his debts
are discharged.
To settle on my niece,
in addition
to her own fortune,
if, as I conclude,
will be the case,
you send me full powers
to act in your name
throughout the whole
of this business.
I will immediately
give directions
to Harrison
for preparing
a proper settlement.
There will not be
smallest occasion
for your coming
to town again.
Therefore,
stay quiet
at Long Bourne
and depend
on my diligence
and care.
Send back your answer
as fast as you can
and be careful
to write explicitly.
We have judged it's best
that my niece
should be married
from this house
of which
I hope you will approve.
She comes to us today.
I shall write again
as soon as anything more
is determined on
yours, etc..
Edward.
Is it possible?
Cried Elizabeth
when she had finished.
Can it be possible
that he will marry her?
Wickham is not
so undeserving
that as we thought him.
Said her sister.
My dear father,
I congratulate you.
And have you answered
the letter?
Cried Elizabeth.
No, but it must be done
soon,
most earnestly.
Did she then
and treat him to lose
no more time
before he wrote.
Oh, my dear
father, she cried.
Come back
and write immediately.
Consider how important
every moment is
in such a case.
Let me write
for you, said Jane.
If you dislike
the trouble yourself.
I dislike it very much,
he replied.
But it must be done.
And so saying
he turned back with them
and walked
towards the house.
And may I ask?
Asked Elizabeth.
But the terms,
I suppose,
must be complied with.
Complied with.
I'm only ashamed of his
asking so little.
And they
must marry.
Yet he is such a man.
Yes. Yes.
They must marry.
There
nothing else to be done.
But there are two things
that I want
very much to know.
One is how much money
your uncle has laid down
to bring it about.
And the other how
I am to pay him
money.
My uncle cried Jane.
What do you mean, sir?
I mean that no man
in his proper senses
would marry Lydia on
so a temptation
as 100 a year
during my life and 50
after I'm gone.
That is very true.
Said Elizabeth.
Though
it hadn't
occurred to me before
his debts
to be discharged
and something
still to remain.
How?
It must be
my uncle's doings.
Generous.
Good man.
I am afraid
he has distressed
himself.
A small
sum could
not do all this.
No, said her father.
Becomes a fool
if he takes it
with a farthing.
Less than ?10,000.
I should be sorry
to think so.
Ill of him
in the very beginning
of our relationship.
?10,000.
Heaven forbid.
How is half such a sum
to be repaid?
Mr.
Bennett made no answer,
and each of them, deep
in thought,
continued silence
till they reached
the house.
Their father
then went on to
the library to. Walk.
And the girls walked
into the breakfast room.
And they are really
to be married.
Cried Elizabeth,
as soon as they were
by themselves.
How strange this is.
And for this
we ought to be thankful
that they should marry
small, as
is their chance
of happiness.
And wretched, as
is his character.
We are forced
to rejoice.
How, Lydia?
I comfort myself for.
Thinking, replied Jane.
That he certainly
would not marry Lydia
if he had not a
real regard for her.
Though our kind
uncle has done
something towards
clearing him.
I cannot believe that
?10,000 or.
Anything like.
It has been advanced.
He has children
of his own
and may have more.
How could he
spare half ?10,000
if he were ever able
to learn what Wickham's
of being
said, Elizabeth, and
how much is settled
on his side
on our sister?
We shall.
Exactly.
Know what Mr.
Gardner has done
for them because Wickham
has not
a sixpence of his own.
The kindness in my uncle
and aunt
can never be requited.
Their taking her home
and affording her
their personal
protection
and countenance
is such a sacrifice.
Her advantage
as years of gratitude
cannot enough
acknowledge.
By this time
she is
actually with them.
If such goodness does
not make a
miserable now,
she will never
deserve to be happy.
What a meeting for her.
When she
first sees my aunt.
We must endeavor
to forget
all that is passed
on either
side, said Jane.
I hope and trust
will yet be happy.
His consenting to marry
her is a proof.
I will believe
that he has come to a
right way of thinking.
That mutual affection
will study them.
And I flatter myself,
will settle so quietly
and leave in so rational
a manner as may in.
Time make their past.
Imprudence forgotten.
That conduct has been.
Such, replied Elizabeth.
As neither you
nor I nor anybody.
Can ever. Forget.
It is useless
to talk of it.
It now
occurred to the girls
that their mother
was in all likelihood
perfectly ignorant
of what had happened.
They went to
the library, therefore,
and asked their father
whether he would not
wish them
to make it known to her.
He was writing
and without raising
his head.
Coolly replied.
Just as you please.
May we take my uncle's
letter to read to her?
Take whatever you like
and get away.
Elizabeth took
the letter
from his writing table,
and they went
upstairs together.
Mary and Kitty
were both with Mrs.
Bennett.
One communication
would therefore
do for all.
After a
slight preparation
for good news,
the letter was read
aloud.
Mrs.
Bennett could hardly
contain herself.
As soon as Jane
had read Mr.
Gardner's
hope of Lydia's
being soon married.
Her joy burst forth,
and every
following sentence
added to its exuberance.
She was now in
an irritation
as violent from delight
as she'd ever
been, fidgety
from alarm and vexation.
To know
that her
daughter would be.
Married was enough.
She was disturbed by no
fear for her Felicity,
nor humbled by
any remembrance
of her misconduct.
My dear, dear
Lydia, she cried.
This is delightful
indeed.
She will be married.
I shall see her again.
She will be married
at 16.
My good kind brother.
I knew how it would be.
I knew he would
manage everything.
How I loved to see her.
And to see Dear
Wickham, too.
Oh, but the clothes,
The wedding clothes.
I will write
to my sister
Gardner them directly.
Lizzie, my dear,
run down to your father
and ask him
how much
he will give her.
Stay. Stay.
I will go myself.
Ring the bell, Katie.
For Hill.
I will put on my things
in a moment.
My dear, dear Lydia,
how merry
we shall be together
when we meet.
Her eldest daughter
endeavored to give
some relief
to the violence
of these transports
by leading her thoughts
to the which Mr.
Gardner's behavior
laid them all under.
Well, we must attribute
this happy conclusion,
she added,
in a great measure
to his kindness.
We are.
Persuaded that
he has pledged himself.
To assist Mr.
Wickham with money.
Well,
cried her mother.
It is all very right.
You should do it.
But her own uncle.
If he had
not a family of his own,
I and my children
must have
had all his money,
you know.
And it is the.
First.
Time we'd ever
had anything.
From him
except a few presents.
Well, I am so happy
in a short
time,
I shall have a daughter
married Mrs.
Wickham.
How well it sounds.
And she was only 16
last June.
My dear Jane,
I am in such a flutter
that I am
sure I can't write.
So I will dictate.
And you will
write for me.
We will settle
with your father
about the money
afterwards.
But the thing
should be ordered
immediately.
She was then proceeding
to all the particulars
of Calico
Muslin and Cranbrook
and would shortly
have dictated
some very plentiful
orders had not.
Jane, though
with some difficulty,
persuaded her to,
until her father
was at leisure
to be consulted.
One day's delay,
she observed,
would be of
small importance,
and her mother
was too happy
to be quite
so obstinate as usual.
Other, too,
came into her head.
I will go to Meriton,
said she,
as soon as I am dressed
until the good,
good news
to my sister Philips,
and as soon
as I come back
I can call on Lady
Lucas and Mrs.
Long Kitty,
run down
and order the carriage
and would do me
a great deal of good,
I am sure.
Girls.
Can I do
anything for you
in Meriton?
Oh, here comes Hill.
My dear Hill.
Have you heard
the good news?
Miss Lydia
is going to be married
and you shall all have
a bowl of punch
to make merry
at a wedding.
Mrs.
Hill began instantly
to express her joy.
Elizabeth received her
congratulations
among the rest,
and then sick of
this folly,
took refuge
in her own room
that she might
think with freedom.
Poor Lydia.
Situation must at
best be bad enough,
but that it was
no worse.
She had need
to be thankful
she felt it so.
And though
and looking forward,
neither rational
happiness
nor worldly
prosperous tea
could be justly expected
for her sister.
In looking back to what
they had feared
only 2 hours ago,
she felt all
the advantages of what
they had gained.
Chapter 50.
Mr.
Bennett had very often
wished before
this period of his life
that instead of
spending his whole.
Income.
He had laid by an annual
sum for the
better provision
of his children
and of his wife
if she survived him.
He now wished it.
More than ever.
Had he done his duty.
In that respect.
Lydia need.
Not have.
Been indebted
to her
uncle for
whatever of honor
or credit could now
be purchased for her.
The satisfied action
of prevailing
on one of the
most worthless
young men in
Great Britain
to be her husband
might then have rested
in its proper place.
He was seriously
concerned
that a cause
of so little
advantage to anyone
should be forwarded
at the sole expense
of his brother in law,
and he was determined,
if possible, to find out
the extent
of his assistance
and to discharge
the obligation
as soon as he could.
When first Mr.
Bennett had married,
economy was held
to be perfectly.
Useless for, of course.
They were to have a son.
The son was to join
in cutting
off the entail
as soon as
he should be of age
and the widow
and younger
children would by
that means be provided.
Five daughters
successively entered
the world, but yet
the son was to come.
And Mrs.
Bennett, for many years
after Lydia's birth,
had been certain that.
He would.
This event had at last
been despaired of.
But it was then too late
to be saving.
Mrs.
Bennett had no
turn for economy
and her husband's
love of independence
had alone prevented
their exceeding
their income.
?5,000 was settled
by marriage articles
on Mrs.
Bennett, the children.
But in what proportions
it should be divided
amongst the latter
depended on the will
of the parents.
This was.
One point with regard
to Lydia at least.
Which was.
Now to be settled,
and Mr.
Bennett
could have no hesitation
in acceding
to the proposal
before him
in terms of grateful
acknowledgment
for the kindness of his.
Though expressed
most concisely,
he then delivered
on paper
his perfect approbation
of all that was done
at his willingness
to fulfill
the engagements
that had been
made for him.
He had never.
Before supposed
that could Wickham be
prevailed on
to marry his daughter.
It would be done
with so
little inconvenience
to himself
as by the
present arrangement.
He would scarcely be ?10
a year.
The loser by the hundred
that was to be paid them
for what with her board
and pocket allowance
and the
continual presents
money
which passed to her
through her
mother's hands.
Lydia's expenses
had been very little
within that.
Sum
that it would be done
with.
Such trifling exertion
on his side to
was another
very welcome surprise
for his wish at present
was to have
as little trouble
in the business
as possible.
When the first
transports of rage,
which had his activity
in seeking
her were over,
he naturally returned
to all his
former indolence.
His letter was
soon dispatched
for though dilatory
and undertaking.
He was quick
in its execution.
He begged to no further
particulars
of what he was
indebted to his brother.
But was.
Too angry
with Lydia
to send any message
to her.
The good news
spread quickly
through the house
and with proportionate
speed
through the neighborhood
it was born
and the latter
with decent philosophy.
To be sure.
It would have been more
for the advantage
of conversation had Ms..
Lydia Bennett
come upon the town,
or as the
happiest alternative.
Being secluded.
From the world
in some
distant farmhouse.
But there was much to be
talked of in
marrying her
and the good natured
wishes for her
well doing,
which had
proceeded before
from all the spiteful
old ladies in Meriton.
Lost, but a.
Little of their spirit
in this change
of circumstances.
Because with
such a husband.
Her misery
was considered certain.
It was a.
Fortnight since Mrs.
Bennett had
been downstairs.
But on this.
Happy day,
she again
took her seat
at the head of the table
and in spirits,
oppressively high,
no sentiment of shame.
It damped her triumph.
The marriage
of a daughter,
which had been the first
object of her wishes
since Jane was 16.
Was now on the point
of accomplishment,
and her.
Thoughts and her words
ran wholly on those.
Attendance.
Of elegant nuptials,
fine Muslins,
new carriages
and servants.
She was busily
searching
through the neighborhood
for a proper situation
for her daughter
and without knowing
or considering
what their income
might be rejected,
many as deficient
in size and importance.
Hey, Park
might do,
said she.
If the Goldings
could quit it.
Or the great house
at Stoke.
If the drawing room were
but Ashworth
is too far off,
I could not bear
to have her
ten miles from me
and ask for
pull this lodge.
The attics.
Dreadful.
Her husband
allowed her to talk on
without interruption
while the
servants remained.
But when they had.
Withdrawn, he said to.
Her, Mrs.
Bennett,
before you take any or
all of these houses
for your son
and daughter.
Let us come to a
right understanding
into one house
in this neighborhood.
They shall never have.
I will not encourage
the imprudence of either
by receiving them
at long born.
A long dispute.
Followed
this declaration.
But Mr.
Bennett was firm.
It soon led to another.
And Mrs.
Bennett
found with amazement
and horror that her.
Husband would
not advance a guinea to.
Buy clothes
for daughter.
He protested
that she should
receive from him
no mark of affection,
whatever,
on the occasion.
Mrs.
Bennett
could hardly comprehend.
It that.
His anger
be carried to such.
A point of.
Inconceivable resentment
as to.
Refuse his daughter
a privilege
without which.
Her marriage
would scarcely
seem valid,
exceeded all,
she could
believe possible.
She was.
More alive
to the disgrace
which her want of new
clothes must reflect on.
Her daughter's nuptials
than to any sense.
Of shame at her eloping
and living
with Wickham a.
Fortnight before.
They took place.
Elizabeth was
now most heartily
sorry that she had,
from the distress
of the moment,
being led to make Mr.
Darcy, acquainted
with their fears
for her sister, for
since her marriage
would so shortly
give the
proper termination
to the elopement.
They might hope to.
Conceal its unfavorable
beginning from all those
who were not immediately
on the spot.
She had no fear of
its spreading
father
through his means.
There were few people.
On whose secrecy
she would have
more confidently,
but at the same time
there was no one
whose knowledge
of a sister's frailty.
Would have mortified.
Her so.
Much, not, however.
From any fear
of disadvantage, from it
individually to herself.
For at any rate,
there seemed
a gulf impassable
between them.
Had Lydia's marriage.
Been concluded on the.
Most honorable terms?
It was not be.
Suppose that Mr..
Darcy would
connect himself
with a family where
to every other
objection.
Would now be.
Added an alliance
and relationship
of the nearest kind.
With a man whom he so
justly scorned.
From such a connection.
She could not wonder
that he would shrink.
The wish of.
Procuring her regard.
Which she had.
Assured herself
of his feeling,
and Derbyshire.
Could not, in rational.
Expectation, survive
such a blow as.
This.
She was humbled.
She was grieved.
She repented.
Though she hardly knew
of what she became
jealous of his esteem
when she could
no longer hope
to be benefited by it.
She wanted to
hear. Of him
when there seemed
the least chance
of gaining intelligence.
She was.
Convinced that
she could
have been happy
with him.
When it.
Was no longer
likely they.
Should meet.
What a triumph for him,
as she often thought.
Could he know
the proposals
which she had
proudly spurned
only four months ago.
Would now
have been most.
Gladly
and gratefully received?
He was as generous.
She doubted.
Not as the
most generous.
Of his sex.
But while he was mortal.
There must be a triumph.
She began now to
comprehend that
he was exactly the man
who in disposition
and talents.
Would most suit.
Her.
His understanding
and temper,
though unlike her own,
would have answered
all her wishes.
It was union
that must have
been to the
advantage of.
Both.
By her ease
and liveliness.
His mind might have
been soft
and his
manners improved.
And from his.
Judgment, information
and knowledge
of the world.
She must have received.
A benefit
of greater importance.
But no such
happy marriage
could now teach
the admiring.
Multitude
what connubial.
Felicity really was
and union
of a different tendency
and precluding
the possibility
of the other.
Was soon.
To be formed
in their family.
How Wickham.
And Lydia
to be supported
intolerable
independence.
She could not imagine.
But how little of
permanent happiness
could belong to a couple
who were
only brought together
because their passions
were stronger,
their virtue.
She could easily
conjecture.
Mr.
Gardner soon wrote again
to his brother, to Mr.
Bennett's
acknowledgments.
He briefly replied
with assurance
of his eagerness
to promote the welfare
of any of his family
and concluded
with entreaties
that the subject
might never be
mentioned to him again.
The principal purport
of his letter.
Was to.
Inform them that Mr.
Wickham had resolved
on quitting the militia.
It was greatly my wish
that he should do
so, he. Added.
As soon as his marriage
was fixed on.
And I think
he will agree with me
in considering a removal
from that corps
as highly advisable,
both on his account
and my niece's.
It is Mr.
Wickham's intention
to go into the
and among
his former friends.
There are still some
who are able and willing
to assist him
in the Army.
He has the promise
of an insurgency
in regiment
now quartered
in the north.
It is an advantage
to have it
so far
from this part
of the kingdom.
He promises fairly,
and I hope
among different people
where they may each
have a character
to preserve.
They will
both be more prudent.
I have written
to Colonel Foster
to inform him of our
present arrangements
and to request
that he will satisfy
the various
creditors of Mr.
Wickham
in a near Brighton
with assurances
of speedy payment
for which
I have pledged myself.
And will you
give yourself the
of carrying
similar assurances
to his creditors
in Meriton, of whom
I shall sub join a list?
According to
his information
he has
given in all his debts,
I hope at least
he has not deceived us.
Augustin has
our directions
and all will be
completed in a week.
They will
then join his regiment
unless they are first
invited too long born.
And I understand
from Mrs.
Gardner that my niece
is very desirous
of seeing you all
before she leaves
the South.
She is well and begs
to be
dutifully remembered
to you and her mother.
Yours, etc..
E Gardner.
Mr.
Bennett
and his daughters
saw all the advantages
of Wickham's removal
from the blank shore
as clearly as Mr.
Gardiner could.
Do.
But Mrs.
Bennett was not so well
pleased with it.
Lydia's
being settled
in the north
just when she
had expected
most pleasure
and pride in her.
Company for.
Had by no means
given up.
Her plan
of their residing
in Hertfordshire
was a
severe disappointment.
And besides,
it was such a pity that.
Lydia should be taken
from her regiment
where she was
acquainted with.
Everybody had had.
So many favorites.
She is so fond of Mrs.
Foster, said she.
It will be
quite shocking
to send her away
and are several
of the young men too,
that she likes
very much.
The officers may not be
so pleasant
in general
Blanc's regiment.
His daughter's
request for such
it might be considered
of being admitted
into her family again
before she set off
for the North, received
at first
in absolute negative.
But Jane and Elizabeth,
who agreed in wishing
for sake
of their sister's
feelings in consequence
that she should
be noticed
on her marriage
by her parents,
urged him so
earnestly, yet
so rationally
and so mildly.
To.
Receive her
and her husband
that long born
as soon as they were
married. That.
He was prevailed on
to think as.
They thought.
And act as they wished.
And their mother
had the satisfaction
knowing that
she would be able
to show her
married daughter
in the neighborhood
before she was banished
to the north.
When Mr.
Bennett wrote again
to his brother,
therefore he sent his
permission for them
come, and it was settled
that as soon as the
ceremony was over.
They should.
Proceed to long born.
Elizabeth was surprised,
however, that Wickham
should consent to.
Such a scheme, and.
Had she consulted
only her own.
Inclination,
any meeting with.
Him would have been
the last object of
her wishes.
Chapter 51.
Their sister's
wedding day arrived
and Jane
and Elizabeth
felt for her probably
more than she
felt for herself.
The carriage was sent
to meet them at blank
and they were to return
in it by dinnertime.
Their arrival
was dreaded by the elder
Miss Bennetts
and Jane
more, especially,
who gave Lydia
the feelings
which would have
attended herself
had she been the culprit
and was wretched in
the thought of what
her sister must endure.
They came.
The family
were assembled
in the breakfast room
to receive them.
Smiles
decked the face of Mrs.
Bennett as the carriage
drove up to the door.
Her husband looked
impenetrable.
Grave.
Her daughters.
Alarmed.
Anxious.
Uneasy.
Lydia's voice
was heard
in the vestibule.
The door was thrown open
and she
ran into the room.
Her mother stepped
forward, embraced her,
and welcomed her
with rapture.
Gave her hand
with affectionate
smile to.
Wickham, who followed.
His.
Lady and wished.
Them both joy
with an alacrity
which showed no doubt
of their happiness.
Their reception from Mr.
Bennett to whom they
then turned
was not quite
so cordial.
His countenance rather
gained in austerity,
and he scarcely
opened his lips.
The easy.
Assurance of
the young couple
was enough to provoke.
Him.
Elizabeth was disgusted,
and even Miss
Bennett was shocked.
Lydia was.
Lydia still untamed,
unabashed, wild,
noisy and fearless.
She turned from sister
to sister,
demanding their
congratulations,
and when at length
they all sat down.
Looked.
Eagerly round the room,
took notice
of some alteration
in it,
and observed
with a laugh
that it was a great
while
since she had
been there.
Wickham was not at all
more distressed
than herself.
But his manners
were always so pleasing.
Had his character
and his marriage
been exactly
what they ought.
His smiles
and his easy address
while he claimed
their relationship.
Would have.
Delighted them all.
Elizabeth had not before
believed him quite equal
to such assurance.
But she sat down,
resolving within herself
to draw no limits
and future
to the impudence
of an impudent man.
She blushed and.
Jane blushed,
but the cheeks of the
two who.
Caused their confusion
suffered no
variation of color.
There was
no want of discourse.
The bride
and her mother could.
Neither of them
talk fast enough.
And Wickham,
who happened to sit
near Elizabeth, began
inquiring
after his acquaintance
in that neighborhood.
With a good.
Humored ease,
which she felt
very unable to equal
in her replies.
They seemed.
Each of them,
to have
the happiest
memories in the world.
Nothing of the past
was recollected
with pain and led Lydia
in voluntarily
to subjects
which her sisters
would not have
alluded to.
For the world.
Only think of it
being three months.
She cried.
Since I went away,
it seems.
But a fortnight,
I declare.
And yet
there have been things.
Enough
happened in the time.
Good gracious.
When I went away,
I am sure
I had no more idea
of being married
till I came back again.
There
I thought it would be
very good fun if I was.
Her father lifted up
his eyes.
Jane was distressed.
Elizabeth
looked expressively
at Lydia.
But she, who never heard
or saw anything of which
she chose
to be insensible.
Cayley continued,
Oh, Mama,
do the people here
about to know
I am married today?
I was afraid
they might not.
And we overtook William
Golding and his coracle.
So I was determined
he should know.
And so
I let down the side.
Glass next to him
and took off my glove
and let my hand
just rest
upon the window frame
so that he might
see the ring.
And then I bowed
and smiled.
Anything.
Elizabeth could bear it
no longer.
She got up
and ran out of the room
and returned no more
till she heard them
passing through the hall
to the dining parlor.
She then joined them
soon enough to see Lydia
with Anxious Parade
walk up to her mother's
right hand
and hear her say to her
eldest sister.
Oh, Jane,
I take your place.
Now and you must.
Go lower because I
am a married woman.
It was not to be.
Suppose
the time would
give Lydia
that embarrassment
from which she had been
so wholly free at first.
Her ease and good
spirits increased.
She longed to see Mrs.
Phillips, the Lucas's
and all their
other neighbors,
and to hear herself
called Mrs.
Wickham by each of them.
And in the meantime,
she went after dinner
to show her ring
and boast
of being married to Mrs.
Hale and the
two housemaids.
Well, Mama said.
She, when
they were all returned
to the breakfast room.
And what do you think
of my husband?
Is he
not a charming man?
I am sure my sisters
must all envy me.
I only hope they may
have half my good luck.
They must all
go to Brighton.
That is the place.
Get husbands.
What a pity it is, Mama.
We did not all go.
Very true.
And if I had my will,
we should.
But, my dear
Lydia, I don't at all
like your going
such way off.
Must it be so?
Oh, Lord, yes.
There is
nothing in that.
I should like it.
Of all things,
you and Papa
and my sisters
must come down
and see us.
We shall be at Newcastle
all the winter.
And I dare say
there will be
some bulls.
And I will take
good care
to get partners
for them all.
I should like it
beyond anything.
Said her mother.
And then.
When you go away,
you may leave.
One or two of my sisters
behind you.
And I daresay I.
Shall get
husbands for them
before the
winter is over.
I thank you for my.
Share the
favor, said Elizabeth.
But I
do not particularly
like your way
of getting husbands.
Their visitors
were not to remain above
ten days with them.
Mr.
Wickham had received
his commission
before he left London,
and he was to join
his regiment
at the end of
a fortnight.
No one but.
Mrs.
Bennett regretted
that their stay
would be so short.
And she.
Made the most
of the time
by visiting about
with her daughter
and having very frequent
parties at.
Home.
These parties
were acceptable to all
to avoid a family
circle was even more
desirable too.
Such as
did think
than such as did not.
Wickham's affection
for Lydia was just what
Elizabeth had expected
to find.
It not.
Equal to Lydia's.
For him,
she had scarcely
needed her
present observation
to be satisfied
from the reason
of things
that their elopement
had been brought on
by the strength
of her love
rather than by his.
And she would
have wondered why,
without violently
caring for her,
he chose to elope
with her at all.
Had she not felt certain
that his flight
was rendered
necessary
by distress
of circumstances?
And if that were
the case.
He was not the young.
To resist an opportunity
of having a companion.
Lydia was exceedingly
fond of him.
He was her dear
Wickham on
every occasion.
No one was to be put in
competition with him.
He did everything
best in the world,
and she was sure
he would kill more birds
on the 1st of September
than anybody else
in the country.
One morning, soon
after, their arrival
as she was
sitting with her two
older sisters,
she said to Elizabeth.
Lizzie,
I never gave you
an account of
my wedding.
I believe
you were not by
when I told Mama
and the others
all about it.
Are not you curious
to hear
how it was managed?
Not really.
Replied Elizabeth.
I think that cannot be
too little.
Said on the. Subject.
You were
so strange, but I
must tell you
how it went off.
We were married,
you know,
at St Clement's,
because Wickham's
lodgings
were in that parish
and it was settled that
we should all be there
by 11:00.
My uncle and aunt
and I
were to go together
and the others
were to meet us
at the church.
Well, Monday
morning came
and I was in
such a fuss.
I was so afraid,
you know.
That something would.
Happen to put it off.
And then
I should have gone
quite distract it.
And that was my aunt.
All the time
I was dressing,
preaching and
talking away,
just as if
she was reading
a sermon.
However, I did not
hear about
one word and ten for
I was thinking,
you may suppose,
of my dear Wickham.
I longed to know
whether he would
be married.
And his blue coat.
Well,
and so we breakfast
did at ten, as usual.
I thought
it would never be over
for by.
By.
You want to understand
that my uncle and aunt
were horrid, unpleasant.
All the time
I was with them.
If you believe me,
I did not once
put my foot
out of doors,
though I was there
a fortnight.
No one party or scheme
or anything, to be sure.
London was rather.
Thin,
but however,
the little
theater was open.
Well,
and so just
as the carriage
came to the door.
My was called away
upon business
to that horrid man, Mr.
Stone.
And then, you know,
when once
they got together,
there is no end of it.
I was so frightened,
I did not know
what to do.
My was to give me away.
And if we were
beyond the hour,
we could not be married
all day.
But luckily.
He came back again
in 10 minutes time.
And then we all set out.
However,
I recollected
afterwards,
if he had been prevented
going,
the wedding need
not be put off for Mr.
Darcy.
Might have done as well.
Mr.
Darcy repeated Elizabeth
in utter amazement.
Oh, yes,
he was to come there
with Wickham, you know.
Oh, good gracious me.
I quite forgot.
I ought not to have said
a word about it.
I promised them
so faithfully.
What Wickham?
Say it
was to be such a secret.
If it
was to be secret,
said Jane.
Say not another word
on the subject.
You may depend
upon my seeking
no further.
Oh, certainly.
Said Elizabeth,
though, burning with.
Curiosity,
We will ask you
no questions.
Thank you, said Lydia.
For if you did,
I should certainly
you all.
And then we can
be angry.
On such encouragement
to ask.
Elizabeth was forced
to put it
out of her power
by running away.
But to live in ignorance
on such
point was impossible.
Or at least
it was impossible
not to try.
For information.
Mr.
Darcy had been at her
sister's wedding.
It was exactly a scene
and exactly among people
where he had apparently.
Least to do
and least temptation
to go.
Conjectures
as to the meaning of it.
Rapid and wild
hurried into her brain,
but she was satisfied.
None.
Those that best
pleased her as placing
his conduct
in the noblest light.
Seemed most.
Improbable.
She could.
Not bear such suspense.
And hastily seizing.
Sheet of paper, wrote
a short letter
to her aunt to request
an explanation
of what
Lydia had dropped
If it were compatible
with the secrecy
which had been intended.
You may
readily comprehend.
She added,
What my curiosity
must be to know
how a person.
Unconnected with any of.
Us and comparatively
speaking,
a stranger
to our family,
should have been
amongst you at.
Such time.
Pray write.
Instantly and.
Let me understand it.
Unless it is
for very cogent.
Reasons
to remain in secrecy,
which Lydia seems
to think necessary,
and that I must endeavor
to be satisfied
with ignorance.
Not that I shall,
though.
She added to herself
as she finished
the letter.
And my dear aunt,
if you do not
tell me
in an honorable manner,
I shall suddenly
be reduced
to tricks and stratagems
to find it out.
Jane's delicate
sense of honor
would not allow her
to speak
to Elizabeth
privately of what
Lydia had let fall.
Elizabeth was glad of it
till it appeared
whether her inquiries
would receive
any satisfaction.
She had rather be
without a confidant.
Chapter 52
Elizabeth had
the satisfaction
of receiving an answer
to her letter
as soon as
she possibly could.
She was no sooner
in possession of it
than hurrying
into the little copse
where she was
least likely
to be interrupted.
She sat down on
one of the benches
and prepared to be happy
for the length
of the letter,
convinced her
that it did
not contain a denial.
Grace Church Street,
September 6th.
My dear niece,
I have just received
your letter
and shall devote
this whole morning
to answering it
as I foresee that
a little writing
will not comprise.
What I have to tell.
You. I must.
Confess myself.
Surprised
by your application?
I did not
expect it from you.
Don't think me.
Angry.
However, for I only mean
to let you know that
I had not imagined
such inquiries
to be necessary
on your side.
If you do not choose
to understand me,
forgive my impertinence.
Your uncle is.
As much surprised
as I am.
And nothing
but the belief
of your being a party
concerned
would have allowed him
to act as he has done.
But if you are really
innocent and, ignorant,
I must be more explicit.
On the very day
of my coming home
from London.
Your uncle had a most
unexpected visitor.
Mr.
Darcy called and was
shut up with him
several hours.
It was all over
before I arrived,
so my curiosity
was not so
dreadfully wrapped
as yours
seems to have been.
He came to town, Mr.
Gardner.
He had found out
where your sister
and Mr.
Wickham were,
and that he had seen
and talked with them.
Both Wickham repeatedly.
Lydia Once
from what I can collect,
he left Derbyshire
only one day.
After ourselves and.
Came to. Town with the.
Resolution
of hunting for them.
The motive professed
was his conviction
of its
being owing to himself
that Wickham's
worthlessness
had not been so well
known as.
To make it.
Impossible
for any young woman
of character to love or
confide in him.
He generously
imputed the whole
to his mistaken pride
and, confessed
that he had before
thought it beneath him
to lay
his private actions
open to the world.
His character
was to speak for itself.
He called it,
therefore his duty
to step forward
and endeavor
to remedy an evil
which had been
brought on by himself.
If he had
another motive,
I am sure it would never
disgrace him.
He had been some
in town before.
He was able to
discover them,
but he had something
to direct his search,
which was more
than we had.
And the consciousness.
Of this
was another reason
for his resolving.
To follow us.
There is a lady,
it seems, are Mrs.
Young,
who was some time ago
governess to Miss Darcy
and was dismissed
from her charge
on some cause
of disapprobation,
though
he did not say what.
She then took a large
house in Edward Street
and has
since maintained herself
by letting lodgings.
This Mrs.
Young was
he knew intimately
with Wickham
and he went to her
for intelligence of him
as soon as he
got to town.
But it was two.
Or three days before he.
Could get from her
what he wanted.
She would not betray her
trust, I suppose,
without bribery
and corruption.
For she really did know
where her friend was
to be found.
Wickham, indeed, had.
Gone to her
on their first
arrival in London.
And had she been able
to receive them
into her house.
They would have
taken up their abode
with her.
At length,
however, our kind
friend procure
the wished
for direction.
They were
in blank street.
He saw Wickham
and afterwards insisted
on seeing Lydia.
His first object
with her,
he acknowledged,
had been to persuade her
to quit, to present
disgraceful situation
and return to friend
as soon as
they could be prevailed
on to receive her,
offering his assistance
as far as it would go.
But he found Lydia
absolutely resolved
on remaining
where she was.
She cared
none of her friends.
She wanted
no help of his.
She would not hear
of leaving Wickham.
She was sure
they should be married
sometime, rather.
And it did not
much signify.
When.
Seems
such were her feelings.
It only remained,
he thought, to secure
and expedite a marriage,
which in his very
first conversation
with Wickham,
he easily learned it
never been his design.
He Confessed himself
obliged
to leave the regiment
on account of some.
Debts of honor
which are very.
Pressing and scruple
not to know
the ill consequences
of Lydia's flight
and her own folly alone.
He meant to resign
his commission
immediately
and asked to his future
a situation
He could conjecture
very little about it.
He must go somewhere,
but he did not
know where.
And he knew
he should have
nothing to live on.
Mr.
Darcy asked him why he
had not married
your sister at once.
Though Mr.
Bennett was not imagined
to be very rich.
He would have been able
to do something.
Him and his situation
must have been
benefited by marriage.
But he found in
reply to this question
that Wickham
still cherished
the hope
of more effectually.
Making his fortune
by marriage
in some other country.
Under
such circumstances,
however,
he was not likely
to be proved
against the temptation
of immediate relief.
They met several times,
but there was much
to be discussed.
Wickham, of course,
wanted more
than he could get,
but at length
was reduced.
To be reasonable.
Everything being
settled between them.
Mr.
D'Arcy's
next step was to make.
Your uncle
acquainted with it,
and he first called
in Grace Church Street
the evening
before I came home.
But Mr.
Gardner could
not be seen.
At Mr.
Darcy found on further.
Inquiry
that your father
was still with him, but
would quit town
the next morning.
He did not judge
your father
to be a person whom
he could
so properly
consult as your uncle
and therefore
readily postpone
seeing him
till after
the departure
of the former.
He did not
leave his name until.
The next. Day.
It was only known
that a gentleman
had called on business.
On Saturday
he came again.
Your father was gone.
Your uncle at home.
And as I said before,
they had a great
deal of talk together.
They met again on Sunday
and then I saw him too.
It was not all
settled before Monday.
As soon as it was,
the Express was
sent off to London.
But our visitor was
very obstinate.
I fancy, Lizzie,
that obstinacy
is the real defect
of his character.
After all,
he has been accused
of many fools
at different times.
But this is
the true one.
Nothing was to be done
that he did
not do himself,
though I am sure,
and I do not speak it
to be thanked.
Therefore
say nothing about it.
Your uncle would
most readily
have settled the whole.
They battled it
together for
a long time.
Which was more
than either
the gentleman
or lady concerned.
And it deserved.
But at last
your uncle
was forced to yield.
And instead of being.
Allowed to be.
Of use to his niece
was forced
to put up with
only having
the probable
credit of it,
which went
solely against
the grain.
And I really believe
your letter this morning
gave him great pleasure
because it required
an explanation
that had robbed him
of his borrowed feathers
and gave the praise
where it was due.
But, Lizzie,
this must go
no farther than yourself
or Jane at most.
You know pretty well,
I suppose,
what is being done
for the young people.
His debts are to be
paid amounting,
I believe, to
considerably more
than ?1,000.
Another thousand,
in addition to her own,
settled upon
her and his commission
purchased.
The reason why all
this was
to be done by him alone
was such as I have
given above.
It was owing to him,
to his reserve
and want of proper
consideration
that Wickham's character
had been
so misunderstood
and consequently
that he had
been received
and noticed he was.
Perhaps there was
some truth in this,
though
I doubt
whether his reserve
or anybody's
reserve
can be answerable.
For the event.
But in spite of all
this talking,
my dear Lizzie,
you may rest
perfectly assured that
your uncle would
never have yielded
if we had not given him
credit for.
Another interest
in the affair.
When all this was
resolved, he.
Returned.
Again to his friends.
Who was still
staying at Pemberley.
But it was agreed
that he should be
in London once more.
When the wedding
took place
and all money matters.
Were then to
receive the last.
Finish.
I believe I have now
told you everything.
It is a relation
which you tell me
is to give you
a great surprise.
I hope at least it will
not afford you
any displeasure.
Lydia came to us and.
Wickham had constant
admission to the house.
He was exactly
what he had been
when I knew him
in Hertfordshire.
But I would not tell you
how little
I was
satisfied with
her behavior
while she
stayed with us.
If I had not perceived
by Jane's
letter last Wednesday
that her conduct on
coming home
was exactly
of a peace with it,
and therefore
what I now tell
you can give you
no fresh pain.
I talked to her
repeatedly
in the most
serious manner,
representing to her,
all the wickedness
of what she had done
and all the unhappiness
she had
brought in a family.
If she heard me,
it was by good luck, for
I am sure she did
not listen.
I was sometimes
quite provoked.
But then I recollected
my dear.
Elizabeth and Jane,
and for their sakes,
had. Patience with her.
Mr.
Darcy was
punctual in his return,
and as Lady informed,
you attended
the wedding.
He dined with.
Us the next.
Day and was to leave
town again on Wednesday
or Thursday.
Will you be very angry
with me, my dear Lizzie,
if I take
this opportunity
of saying what
I was never bold enough
to say before.
How much I like him.
His behavior
to us
has in every respect
been as pleasing
as when we were
in Derbyshire.
His understanding
and opinions
all please me.
He wants nothing
but a
little more liveliness
and that if he
marry prudently,
his wife may teach him.
I thought him very sly.
He hardly ever
mentioned your name,
but slyness
seems the fashion.
Pray forgive me.
If I have been
very presuming,
or at least
do not punish me so far
as to
exclude me from me.
I shall never be
quite happy to live.
Been all round the park.
A low
with a
nice little
pair of ponies
would be the very thing.
But I must try to know
more.
The children have been.
Wanting me this half.
Hour.
Yours very sincerely.
Am gardener.
The contents of this
letter threw Elizabeth
into a
flutter of spirits
in which
it was difficult
to determine
whether pleasure
or pain.
The greatest share.
The vague
and unsettled suspicions
which uncertainty
had produced of what Mr.
Darcy might
have been doing
to forward her
sister's match.
Which she had.
Feared to encourage
as an exertion
of goodness.
Too great to be probable
and at the same time
dreaded to be just from
the pain of obligation.
Were proved.
Beyond their greatest
extent to be true.
He had followed them
purposely to town.
He had taken on himself.
All the trouble
and mortification
attended on
such a research.
In which
supplication had.
Been necessary
to a woman
whom he must
abomination, despise
and where he was.
Reduced to meet
frequently meet
reason with persuade.
And finally bribe.
The man whom he always
most wished to avoid,
whose very name
it was punishment to.
Him to pronounce.
He had done all this
for a girl
whom he could
neither regard
nor esteem.
Her heart did whisper
that he had
done it for her,
but it was a hope.
Shortly checked
by other considerations.
And she soon.
Felt that even
her vanity
was insufficient
when required to depend
on his affection
for her.
For a woman
who had
already refused him
as able
to overcome
a sentiment
so natural
as abhorrence against.
Relationship
with Wickham.
Brother in.
Law of Wickham.
Every kind of.
Pride must revolt
from the connection.
He had to be
sure done much.
She was ashamed to think
how much, but he had.
Given a reason
for his interference,
which no extraordinary
stretch of belief.
It was reasonable
that he should feel
he had been wrong.
He had liberality
and he had the means
of exercising it.
And though she would.
Not place herself
his principal
inducement,
she could
perhaps believe
that remaining
partiality for her
might assist
his endeavors in a cause
where her peace of mind
must be
materially concerned.
It was painful,
exceedingly painful
to know
that they were
under obligations
to a person
who could never receive
a return.
They owed
the restoration.
Of Lydia, her character,
everything to him.
Oh, how.
Heartily
did she grieve over
every ungracious
sensation
she had ever encouraged.
Every saucy speech.
She had ever directed
towards. Him?
For herself was.
Humbled.
But she was
proud of him.
Proud
that in a cause
of compassion and honor,
he had been able
to get
the better of himself.
She read over her
aunt's commendation
of him again and again.
It was hardly enough.
But it pleased her.
She was even.
Sensible
of some pleasure, though
mixed with regret
on finding
how steadfastly she and
her uncle
had been persuaded
that affection
and confidence subsisted
between Mr.
Darcy and herself.
She was roused from her
seat and her reflections
by someone's approach
and Before
she could strike
into another path,
she was overtaken
by Wickham.
I am afraid
I interrupt
your solitary ramble,
my dear sister.
Said he,
as he joined her.
You certainly do.
She replied
with a smile.
But it does
not follow that
the interruption
must be unwelcome.
I should be sorry.
Indeed, if it were,
we were always
good friends.
And now we are better.
True.
Are the others
coming out?
I do not know.
Mrs.
Bennett and Lydia
are going
in the carriage
to Meriton.
And so, my dear sister,
I find from my uncle
and aunt
that you have
actually seen Pemberley.
She replied
in the affirmative.
I almost envy you
the pleasure.
And yet I believe
it would be
too much for me.
Or else I could take it
in my way to Newcastle.
And you saw the
old housekeeper,
I suppose.
Poor Reynolds.
She was very fond of me.
But of course,
she did not mention
my name to you.
Yes, she did.
And what did she say?
That you were gone into.
The army.
And she was afraid.
Had not turned out well
at such a distance
as that.
You know,
things are
strangely
misrepresented.
Certainly.
He replied,
biting his lips.
Elizabeth hoped
she had silenced him.
But he soon afterwards
said.
I was surprised to see
Darcy in town
last month.
We passed each other
several times.
I wonder what he can be
doing there.
Perhaps
preparing for his
marriage with Mr.
Berg, said Elizabeth.
It must be
something particular
to take him there
at this time of year.
Undoubtedly.
Did you see him
while you were
at Lambton?
I thought I understood
from the gardeners
that you had.
Yes.
He introduced us
to his sister.
And do you like her?
Very much.
I have heard
indeed, that
she is
uncommonly improved
within this year or two.
When I last saw her,
she not very promising.
I'm very glad
you liked her.
I hope she will turn out
well.
I daresay she will.
She has got over
the most trying age.
Did you go by
the village of Kimpton?
I do not recollect
that we did.
I mention it
because it is the living
which I ought
to have
had the most
delightful place.
Excellent
parsonage house.
It would have suited me
in every respect.
How would you have liked
making sermons?
Exceedingly well.
I should have
considered it
as part of my duty
and the exertion soon
have been nothing.
One ought not to opine.
But to be
sure, it would have
been such a thing
for me.
The quiet,
the retirement of such
a life
would have answered
all my ideas
of happiness.
But it was not to be.
Did you ever hear
Darcy mention
the circumstance
when you were in Kent?
I have heard
from authority.
I thought as good
that it was left
you conditionally only,
and at the will of
the present patron
you have. Yes.
There was
something in that.
I told you so
from the first
you may remember.
I did hear, too, that
that was a time
when sermon making
was not so palatable
to you,
as it seems to be
at present,
that you
actually declared
your resolution
of never taking
and that the business
had been compromised
accordingly.
You did.
And it was not wholly
without foundation.
You may remember
what I told you
on that point when first
talked of it.
They were now
almost at the
door of the house,
for she had walked fast
to get rid of him
and unwilling
for her sister's
sake, to provoke him.
She only in reply
with a good
humored smile.
Come, Mr.
Wickham,
We are brother and.
Sister, you know.
Do not let us quarrel
about the past.
In future
I hope we shall always
of one mind.
She held out her hand.
He kissed it
with affectionate
gallantry,
though
he hardly knew
where to look.
And they entered
the house.
Chapter 53.
Mr.
Wickham was
so perfectly satisfied
with this conversation
that he never again
distressed himself
or provoked his dear
Elizabeth by introducing
the subject of it.
And she.
Was pleased to find that
she had said enough
to keep him.
Quiet.
The day of his
and Lydia's departure
soon came and Mrs.
Bennett was forced
to submit
to a separation.
Which, as.
Her husband by no means
entered
into her scheme of their
all going to Newcastle,
was likely to continue
at least a 12.
Oh, my
dear Lydia.
She cried.
When shall
we meet again?
Oh, Lord, I don't know.
Not these two
or three years, perhaps
I'll write to me
very often, my dear.
As often as I can.
But, you know,
married women
have never much time
for writing.
My sisters
may write to me.
They will have
nothing else to do.
Mr.
Wickham's views
were much
more affectionate
than his wife's.
He smiled.
Looked handsome,
and said many
pretty things.
He is as fine a fellow.
Said Mr.
Bennett,
as soon as they were
out of the house.
As ever,
I saw his sympathy
and smirks and makes
love to us all.
I am prodigious
silly, proud of him.
I defy even Sir
William Lucas himself
to produce a more
valuable son in law.
The loss of her
daughter made Mrs.
Bennett very dull
for several days.
I often
think, said she,
that there is nothing
so bad
as parting
with one's friends.
One seems so forlorn
without them,
this is the consequence.
You see, madam, of
marrying a daughter?
Said Elizabeth.
It must make you
better satisfied
that your other four
are single.
It is no such thing.
Lydia does not leave me
because she is married,
but only because
her husband's
regiment happens
to be so far off.
If that had been nearer,
she would not have
so soon.
But the spiritless
condition,
which this event threw
her into,
was shortly relieved,
and her mind
opened again to the.
Agitation of hope.
By an article news
which then began
to be in circulation.
The housekeeper
at another field
had received orders
to prepare
for the arrival
of her master,
who was coming down
in a day or two to shoot
for several weeks.
Mrs.
Bennett was quite.
In the. Fidgets.
She looked at.
Jane and smiled
and shook her
head by turns.
Well. Well.
And so Mr.
Bingley is coming down.
Sister for Mrs.
Philips first
brought her the news.
Well, so
much the better.
Not that I care
about it, though
He is nothing to us,
you know.
And I am sure
I never want to
see him again.
But however,
he is
very welcome
to come to Netherfield
if he likes it.
And who knows
what may happen.
But that is
nothing to us.
You know, Sister,
we agreed long ago
never to mention
a word about it.
And so is it
quite certain
he is coming?
You may depend on it.
Replied the other.
For Mrs.
Nicholls was in Meriden
last night.
I saw her passing by
and went out myself
on purpose
to know the truth of it,
and she told me
it was certainly true.
He comes down on
Thursday at the latest,
very likely
on Wednesday.
She was going
to the butcher,
she told me on purpose
to order
in some meat
on Wednesday
and she has got three
a couple of duck
just fit to be killed.
Miss Bennett
had not been able
to hear of his coming
without changing color.
It was many months
and she had mentioned
his name to Elizabeth.
But now,
as soon as they
were alone together,
she said.
I saw you look at me
today, Lizzie,
when my aunt
told us
of the present report,
and I know
I appeared distress,
but imagine it was from
any silly cause.
I was only confused
for the moment
because I felt
that I should be
looked at.
I do assure you
that the news does
not affect
me, either with
pleasure or.
I am glad of one thing
that he comes alone.
Because we shall see
the less of him.
Not that I am
afraid of myself,
but I dread
other people's remarks.
Elizabeth did not know
what to. Make of it.
Had she not seen him
in Derbyshire.
She might have supposed.
Him capable
of coming there
with no other view
than what
was acknowledged.
But she still
thought him.
Partial to Jane.
And she wavered as
to the greater
probability
of his coming there
with his friend's
permission
or being bold enough
to come without it.
Yet it is hard.
She sometimes thought
that this poor man
cannot come to a house
which he is
legally hired
without raising
all this speculation.
I will leave him
to himself.
In spite of.
What her sister declared
and really believed
to be her feelings
in the expectation
of his arrival,
Elizabeth could
easily perceive
that her spirits
were affected by.
They were more
disturbed, more unequal
than she had often
seen them.
The subject.
Which had
been so warmly canvased
between their parents
about a 12 month ago,
was now brought again.
As soon as ever.
Mr.
Bingley comes,
my dear, said Mrs.
Bennett.
You will wait on him,
of course.
No, no.
You forced me
into visiting last year
and promised
if I went to see him,
he should marry
one of my daughters.
But it ended in nothing.
And I will not be sent
on a fool's
errand again.
His Wife
represented to him
how absolutely necessary
such an attention
would be
from all
the neighboring
gentlemen.
On his returning
to Netherfield.
To Connecticut.
I despise.
Said he.
If he wants our society,
let him seek it.
He knows where we live.
I will not
spend my hours
in running
after my neighbors
every time they go away
and come back again.
Well, all I know
is that
it will be impossible
to be rude
if you do not
wait on him.
But, however, that
shan't prevent
my asking him
to dine here.
I am determined.
We must have Mrs.
Long and the Goldings
soon.
That will make 13
with ourselves.
So there will be
just room at the table
for him.
Consoled by this.
Resolution.
She was.
The batter, able
to bear her
husband's incivility.
Though
it was very mortifying.
To know
that her neighbors
might all see Mr.
Bingley in
consequence of it
before they did.
As the day.
Of his arrival.
Junior.
I begin to be sorry
that he comes at all.
Said Jane to her sister.
It would be nothing.
I could see him
with perfect
indifference.
But I can hardly bear
to hear it
thus perpetually
talked of.
My mother means well,
but she does not know.
No one can know
how much I suffer from
what she says.
Happy shall I be?
When his.
Stay at.
Netherfield? Over.
I wish I could
say anything
to comfort you,
replied Elizabeth.
But it is wholly
out of my power.
You must feel it.
And the
usual satisfaction
of preaching patience
to a sufferer
is denied me.
Because you have always
so much.
Mr.
Bingley arrived.
Mrs.
Bennet,
through the assistance
of servants, to
have the earliest
tidings of it,
that the period
of anxiety
and fruitfulness
on her side
might be
as long as it could.
She counted the days
that must intervene
before their invitation
could be sent.
Hopeless
of seeing him before.
But on the third
morning,
after his arrival
in Hertfordshire,
she saw him from her
dressing room
window, enter
the paddock and ride
towards house.
Her daughters
were eagerly called
to partake of her joy.
Jane resolutely
kept her place
at the table.
But Elizabeth.
To satisfy her mother,
went to the window.
She looked.
She saw Mr.
Darcy with. Him.
And sat down again
by her sister.
There is a gentleman
with your mama,
said Kitty.
Who can it be?
Some acquaintance,
rather.
My dear,
I suppose
I am sure I do not know,
Lah replied Kitty.
It looks just like
that man
that used to be
with him before. Mr.
What's.
His name
that tall, proud man.
Good gracious, Mr.
Darcy.
And so it does, I vow.
Well, any friend of Mr.
Bing,
this will always be
welcome here to be sure.
But I must say that
I hate the very
sight of him.
Jane looked.
At Elizabeth
with surprise and.
Concern.
She knew
but little of their
meeting in Derbyshire
and therefore felt
for the awkwardness
which must
attend her sister
in seeing him
almost for
the first time
after receiving
his explanatory letter.
Both sisters
were uncomfortable
enough.
Each felt for the other
and of course,
for themselves.
And their mother talked
on of her dislike of Mr.
Darcy and her resolution
to be civil to him
only as Mr.
Bingley friend.
Without.
Being heard
by either of them.
But Elizabeth.
Had sources
of uneasiness
which could not
be suspected by.
Jane.
To whom she had
never yet
had courage to show Mrs.
Gardner's
or to relate
her own change
of sentiment
towards him.
To Jane,
he could only be a man
whose proposal.
She had refused and.
Whose merit
she had undervalued.
But to her more
extensive information.
He was the person
to whom
the whole family
were indebted
for the
first of benefits.
And whom.
She regarded herself
with an interest,
if not quite so tender,
at least as reasonable,
and just as what
Jane felt for Bingley.
Her astonishment.
At his coming at his.
Coming
to Netherfield
too long,
born and voluntarily
seeking her again.
Was almost equal.
To what she had known.
On first witnessing
his altered
behavior in Derbyshire,
the color
which had been
driven from her face,
returned for
half a minute
with an additional
and a smile of delight,
added luster to her eyes
as she thought for that
space of time
that his affection
and wishes
must still be unshaken.
But she would
not be secure.
Let me first
see how he behaves,
said she.
It will then
be early
enough for expectation.
She sat intently
at work,
striving to be composed
without daring to lift
up her eyes.
Till anxious.
Curiosity carried them
to the face
of her sister
as the servant
was approaching
the door.
Jane looked a.
Little paler than usual,
but more sedate
than Elizabeth
had expected.
On the gentleman's.
Appearing,
her color increased.
Yet she received.
Them with tolerable ease
and with the
propriety of behavior
equally
from any symptom
of resentment
or any unnecessary
complacence.
Elizabeth said
as little to either
as civility would allow,
and sat down again
to her work
with an eagerness
which it did not
often command.
She had ventured.
Only one
glance at Darcy.
He looked
serious as usual.
And she thought.
More as he had
been used
to look in Hertfordshire
than as she had
seen him at Pemberley.
But perhaps
he could not,
in her mother's
presence, be what he was
before her
aunt and uncle.
It was a painful
but not an
improbable conjecture.
Bingley she had likewise
seen for an instant,
and in that short period
saw him looking
both pleased
and embarrassed.
He was received by Mrs.
Bennet
with a degree
of civility,
which made her
two daughters ashamed,
especially
when contrasted
with the cold
and ceremonious
politeness
of her curtsey
and addressed
to his friend
Elizabeth,
particularly knew
that her mother
owed to the latter.
The preservation
of her favorite daughter
from irremediable infamy
was hurt and distressed
to a most painful degree
by a distinction
so ill applied.
Darcy,
after inquiring of her,
how Mr. and Mrs.
Gardner did.
A question which she.
Could not answer
without confusion,
said scarcely anything.
He was not seated
by her.
Perhaps that was the
reason of his silence.
But it had not.
Been so in Derbyshire.
There
he had talked
to her friends
when he could,
not to herself.
But now.
Several minutes elapsed,
bringing the
sound of his.
Voice.
And when.
Occasionally unable
to resist
the impulse of.
Curiosity, she raised.
Her eyes.
To his face.
She, as often found him
looking at Jane
as at herself.
And.
Frequently on no object
but to the ground.
More thoughtfulness
and less anxiety
to pleas
than when they had
last met were
plainly expressed.
She was
and angry with
herself for being so.
Could I expect it
to be otherwise?
Said she. Yet.
Why did he come?
She was in no.
Humor for conversation
with anyone but himself.
And to him
she had hardly courage
to speak.
She inquired
after his sister, but
could do no more.
It is a long time, Mr.
Bingley,
since you went away,
said Mrs.
Bennet.
He readily agreed to it.
I began to be afraid
you would
never come back again.
People did
say you meant
to quit the place
entirely, Nicholas.
But, however,
I hope it is not true.
A great many changes.
Have happened
in the neighborhood.
Since you went away.
Miss Luke is.
Is married and settled.
And one of
my own daughters.
I suppose
you've heard of it.
Indeed.
You must have seen it
in the papers.
It was in The Times
and the Courier.
I know, but it was not
put in
as it ought to be.
It was only said
George became a squire
to miss Lydia Bennet
without there
being a syllable
said of her father
or the place
where she lived
or anything.
It was my brother.
Gardener's
drawing up too,
and I wonder how he came
to make such
an awkward
business of it.
Did you see it?
Bingley replied
that he did and made
his congratulations.
Elizabeth dared
not lift up her eyes
how Mr.
Darcy looked, therefore,
she could not tell.
It is a delightful thing
to be sure
to have a daughter
well married.
Continued her mother.
But at the same
time, Mr.
it is very hard
to have had taken
such a way from me.
They are gone
down to Newcastle,
a place quite northward,
it seems,
and there
they are to stay.
I do not know how long
as regiment
is there for.
I suppose
you've heard of his
leaving the blank
and of his being gone
into the regulars.
Thank heaven
he has some friends,
though
perhaps not so many
as he deserves.
Elizabeth,
who knew this
to be leveled at Mr.
Darcy was in such
a misery of shame
that she could
hardly keep her seat.
It drew from her,
however,
the exertion of speaking
which else had so have
actually done before.
And she asked Bingley
whether he meant
to make any stay
in the country
at present.
A few weeks,
he believed.
When you have killed
all your own birds, Mr.
Bingley.
Said her mother.
I beg you,
will come here and shoot
as many
as you please on Mr.
Bennett's manner.
I am sure
he will be vastly
happy to oblige
you and will save
all the best the Colbys
for you.
Elizabeth's misery
increased
at such
unnecessary, such
officious attention
were the same
fare prospect
to arise at present, as
had flattered
them a year ago.
Everything
she was persuaded
would be hastening
to the same
vexatious conclusion.
At that instant.
She felt
that years of happiness
could not make Jane
or herself
amends for moments
of such painful.
Confusion.
The first
wish of my heart.
Said she, to herself.
Is never more
to be in company
with either of them.
Their society afford no
pleasure that will atone
for such wretchedness
as this.
Let me never see
either one
or the other again.
Yet the misery
for which years
of happiness
were to offer no
received soon
afterwards
material relief
from observing
how much the beauty
of her sister rekindled
the admiration
of her former lover.
When first he came,
then he had
spoken to her,
but little
but every 5 minutes
seemed to be giving her
more of his attention.
He found her as handsome
as she had
been last year,
as good natured
and as unaffected.
Though not so chatty.
Jane was anxious
that no difference
should be perceived
in her at all
and was really persuaded
that she talked
as much as ever.
But her mind was so
busily engaged
that she did
not always know
when she was silent.
When the gentleman
rose to go away.
Mrs.
Bennett was mindful
of her
intended civility,
and they were invited
and engaged
to dine at Long Bourne
in a few days time.
You are quite a visited
my debt, Mr.
Bingley, she added.
But when you
went to town
last winter,
you promised to
take a family dinner
with us
as soon as you returned.
I have not forgot.
Do you see?
And I assure you,
I was very
much disappointed
that you did
not come back
and keep
your engagement.
Bingley looked
a little silly
at this reflection
and said something
of his concern
at having been
prevented by business.
Then they went away.
Mrs.
Bennett had been
strongly inclined
to ask them
to stay and dine there
that day.
But though
she always kept
a very good table.
She did not.
Think anything
less than two courses
could be good enough
for a man on whom
she had such
anxious designs
or satisfy
the appetite
and pride of one who
had 10,000 a year.
Chapter 54.
As soon as
they were gone,
Elizabeth walked out
to recover her spirits,
or, in other words, to
dwell
without interruption
on those subjects
that must
deaden them more.
Mr.
Darcy's
behavior, astonished
and vexed her.
Why, if he came
only to be silent,
grave and indifferent
said she, did
he come at all.
She could settle it in
no way.
That gave her pleasure.
He could be
still amiable,
still pleasing
to my uncle
and aunt
when he was in town.
And why not to me?
If he fears me,
why come hither?
If he no longer cares
for me?
Why?
Silent, teasing,
teasing man,
I will think
no more about him.
Her resolution
was for a short
time, involuntarily kept
by the approach
of her sister,
who joined her
with a cheerful
look which showed
her better
satisfied
with her visitors
than Elizabeth.
No, said she,
that this first meeting
is over.
I feel perfectly easy.
I know my own strength
and I shall never be.
Embarrassed again
by his coming.
I am glad he dines
here on Tuesday.
It will
then be publicly seen
that on both sides
we meet only as common.
An indifferent
acquaintance.
Yes Very indifferent
indeed, said
Elizabeth laughingly.
Oh, Jane, Take
care.
My dear
Lizzie,
you cannot think me
so weak
as to be in danger Now.
I think you are
in very great danger
of making him
as much in love
with you as ever.
They did not.
See the gentleman again
until Tuesday.
And Mrs.
Bennett, in
the meanwhile, was way
to all the
happy schemes,
which the good humor
and common
politeness of Bingley
in half an hour's
visit had revived.
On Tuesday,
there was a large party
assembled at Long Bourne
and the two,
who are most
anxiously expected
to the credit
of their punctuality
as sportsman,
were in very good time
when they repaired
to the dining room.
Elizabeth eagerly
watched to
whether Bingley
would take the place,
which in
all their former parties
had belonged to him
by her sister,
her prudent mother,
occupied
by the same ideas
for board to invite him
to sit by herself.
On.
Entering the room,
he seemed to hesitate.
But Jane happened
to look round
and happened to smile.
It was decided
he placed himself
by her.
Elizabeth,
with a
triumphant sensation,
looked towards
his friend.
He bought with noble
indifference,
and she would
have imagined that
Bingley had received
his sanction
to be happy.
Had she not seen.
His eyes
likewise turned
towards Mr.
Darcy
with an
expression of half
laughing alarm.
His behavior
to her sister
was such
during dinnertime
as showed
an admiration of her,
which, though
more guarded
than formally persuaded
Elizabeth
that if left
wholly to himself.
Jane's.
Happiness and his own
would be
speedily secured,
though she dared not
depend upon
the consequence,
she yet
received pleasure
from observing
his behavior.
It gave her all
the animation
that her spirits
could boast for.
She was in no cheerful
humor. Mr.
Darcy was almost
as far from her
as the table
could divide them.
He was on
one side of her mother.
She knew how little
such a situation
would give pleasure to
or make
either appear
to advantage.
She was not near enough
to hear
any of their discourse,
but she could
see how seldom
they spoke to each other
and how formal and cold
was their manner.
Whenever did.
Her mother's
on graciousness,
made the sense
of what
they owed him
more painful
to Elizabeth's mind.
And she would at.
Times have give anything
to be privileged
to tell him that
his kindness
neither unknown
nor un felt
by the whole
of the family.
She was in hopes
that the.
Evening would afford
some opportunity
of bringing
them together,
that the whole of
the visit would not pass
without enabling them
to enter into something
more of conversation
than the mere
ceremonious salutation
attending his entrance.
Anxious and uneasy,
the period
which passed
in the drawing room
before the
gentleman came
was wearisome and dull
to a degree
that made her
almost uncivil.
She looked forward to
their entrance
as the point on which
all her chance
of pleasure
for the evening
must pend.
If he does
not come to me.
Then she said
I shall give him
up forever.
The gentleman came
and she thought
he looked.
As if he would
have answered her hopes.
But alas, the ladies
had crowded
round the table
where Miss Bennett
was making
tea and Elizabeth
pouring out the coffee
in so close
a confederacy
that there was not
a single vacancy near
which would
admit of a chair.
And on the
gentleman's approaching,
one of the girls
moved closer
to her than ever
and sat in a whisper.
The men shan't.
Come, in part,
as I am determined.
We want
none of them, do we?
Darcy had walked away
to another
part of the room.
She followed him
with her eyes, envied
everyone to whom
he spoke,
had scarcely patience
enough to help
anybody to coffee,
and then was enraged
against herself
for being so silly.
A man who.
Was once been refused.
How could I ever be
foolish enough to expect
a renewal of his love?
Is there one
among the sex
who could not
protest against
such a weakness
as a second.
Proposal
to the same woman?
There is no
indignity so.
Abhorrent
to that feelings.
She was revived
a little, however,
by his
bringing back
his coffee cup.
Himself and she.
Seized
the opportunity
of saying.
Is your sister
at Pemberley still?
Yes.
She will remain there
Christmas.
And quite alone.
Have all her
friends left her?
Mrs.
Amis's with her.
The others have gone
to Scarborough
these three weeks.
She could
think of nothing to say.
But if he wished
to converse with her,
he might have
better success.
He stood by.
Her, however,
for some minutes
in silence.
And at last
on, the young lady's
whispering to
Elizabeth again.
He walked away
when the two things.
Were removed
and the card
tables placed
and the ladies all rose.
And Elizabeth was then
hoping to be
joined by him
when all her views
were overthrown
by seeing him
fall victim
to her mother's rapacity
for whist players.
And in a few moments
after seated
with the rest
of the party,
she now lost
every expectation
of pleasure.
They were confined
for the evening
at two different tables,
and she had
nothing to hope
but that his eyes were
so often
turned towards her
side of the room
as to make him play
as unsuccessfully
as herself.
Mrs.
Bennett had designed
to keep the
two Netherfield
gentlemen to supper,
but their carriage
was unluckily ordered
before any
of the others,
and she had no
opportunity
of detaining.
Well, girls, said.
She, as
soon as they were
left to themselves.
What say you to the day?
I think everything
is passed off
uncommonly well,
I assure you that dinner
was as well dressed
as any I ever saw.
The venison
was roasting to a turn
and everybody said
they never saw
so fat a haunch.
The soup was 50 times
better than what
had at the Lucas's
last week.
And even Mr.
Darcy acknowledged
that the Partridges
was remarkably
well done.
And I suppose
he has two or three
French cooks
at least had my.
Jane, I never saw
you looking great.
A beauty.
Mrs.
Long said so too, for
I asked her
whether you did not.
And what do you think
she said besides?
Oh, Mrs.
Bennet, we shall have to
the field at last.
She did indeed.
I do think Mrs.
Long is as good
a creature
as ever lived,
and her nieces are
very pretty
behaved girls.
And not at all handsome.
I like them
prodigiously.
Mrs.
Bennet, in short,
was in
very great spirits.
She had seen enough of
Bayley's behavior
to Jane to be convinced
that she would
get in at last.
And her expectations
of advantage
to her family,
when in a happy humor,
were so far
beyond reason
that she was
quite disappointed at
not seeing him
there again the next day
to make his proposals.
It has
a very agreeable day.
Said Mrs.
Bennet to Elizabeth.
The party seemed so
well selected,
so suitable
with one another.
I hope we may
often meet again.
Elizabeth smiled.
Lizzie,
you must not do so.
You must not suspect me.
It mortified me.
I assure you
that I have now
learned to enjoy
this conversation
as an agreeable
and sensible young man
without having a
wish beyond it.
I am perfectly satisfied
from what.
His man is now.
That he had never
any design.
Of engaging my.
Affection.
It is only that
he is blessed
with greater
sweetness of address
and a stronger desire
of generally pleasing
than any other man.
You are very cruel.
Said her sister.
He will not let me smile
and to
provoking me to
at every moment
how hard it is
in some cases
to be believed
and how impossible
in others.
But why should you wish
to persuade me
that I feel more
than I acknowledge?
That is the question
which I hardly know
how to answer.
We all love to instruct
that we can teach only
what is not
worth knowing.
Forgive me.
And if you persist
in indifference,
do not make
me your confident.
Chapter 55.
A few days
after this visit, Mr.
Bingley called again
and alone.
His friend had left him
that morning for London,
but was to return home
in ten days time.
He sat with them
above an hour
and was in remarkably
good spirits.
Mrs.
Bennett
invited him to dine
with them. But.
With expressions
of concern.
He confessed himself
engaged elsewhere.
Next time
you call, said she.
I hope we shall be
more lucky.
He should be
particularly.
Happy at any time,
etc., etc..
And if she would
give him
leave,
would take
an early opportunity
of waiting on them.
Can you come tomorrow?
Yes.
He had no engagement
at all for tomorrow,
and her invitation
was accepted
with alacrity.
He came
and in such
very good time
that the ladies were
none of them dressed
in ran Mrs.
Bennett
to her daughter's room
in her dressing gown
and with her hair half
finished, crying out.
My dear Jane,
make haste
and hurry down.
He has come.
Mr.
Bingley has come.
He is indeed.
Make haste.
He is Sarah.
Come to miss.
Spend at this moment
and help her on
with her gown.
Never mind this
Lizzie's hair.
We will be down
as soon as we can,
said Jane.
But I dare say
Kitty is forward
it in either of us
because she
went upstairs
half an hour ago.
Oh, hang, Kitty.
What has she
to do with it?
Come, be quick.
Be.
When is your sash,
my dear?
But when her
mother was gone,
Jane would not
be prevailed
on to go down
without one of
her sisters.
The same anxiety
to get them by
themselves was
was visible again
in the evening
after tea, Mr.
Bennett retired
to the library,
as was his custom,
and Mary went upstairs
to her instrument
to obstacles of the
five being removed.
Mrs.
Bennett sat down
and winking at Elizabeth
and Catherine
for a considerable time
without making
any impression on them.
Elizabeth would not
observe her.
And when at last.
Kitty did, she.
Very innocently said.
What's the matter, Mama?
What do you keep
winking at me for?
What am I to do?
Nothing, child.
Nothing.
I did not wink at you.
She then sat
still 5 minutes longer,
but unable to waste
such a
precious occasion.
She suddenly got up
and saying to Kitty.
Come here, my love.
I want to speak you.
Took her
out of the room.
Jane instantly
gave a look
at Elizabeth,
which spoke her distress
at such premeditation
and her entreaty
that she would
not give in to it
in a few minutes.
Mrs.
Bennett half
opened the door
and called out.
Lizzie, my dear,
I want to speak
with you.
Elizabeth was
forced to go.
We may as well
leave them
by themselves.
You know.
Said her mother,
as soon as she was
in the hall.
Kitty
and I are going upstairs
to sit
in my dressing room.
Elizabeth made
no attempt to reason
with her mother,
but remained
quietly in the hall
till she
and Kitty
were out of sight,
then returned
to the drawing room.
Mrs.
Bennett's schemes for
the day
were ineffectual.
Bingley was everything
that was charming,
except The professed
lover of her daughter.
His ease
and cheerfulness
rendered him
a most
agreeable addition
to their evening party.
And he.
Bore with the
ill judged officious
ness of the mother
and heard
all her silly remarks
with a forbearance
and command
of countenance,
particularly grateful
to the daughter,
he scarcely needed
an invitation
to stay supper,
and before he went away
an engagement was formed
chiefly through his own
and Mrs.
Bennett's means
for his coming
next morning
to shoot
with her husband.
After this day,
Jane said
no more of indifference.
Not a word passed
between the sisters
concerning Bingley.
But Elizabeth
went to bed
in the happy belief
that all must speedily
be concluded unless Mr.
Darcy returned
within the stated time.
Seriously, however,
she felt
tolerably persuaded
that all
this must have
taken place
with that
gentleman's concurrence.
Bingley was punctual
to his appointment,
and he and Mr.
Bennett spent
the morning together,
as had been agreed on.
The latter was much
more agreeable
than his companion
expected.
There was nothing
of presumption
or folly in Bingley
that could provoke
his ridicule
or disgust him
into silence,
and he was
more communicative
and less eccentric
than the other
had ever seen him.
Bingley, of course,
returned with him
to dinner.
And in the.
Evening Mrs.
Bennett's invention
was again at work
to get everybody
away from him
And her
daughter Elizabeth,
who had a letter
to write,
went into the
breakfast room
for that purpose.
Soon after tea.
For as the others
all going
to sit down to cards.
She could not be wanted.
To counteract her
mother's schemes.
But on returning.
To the drawing room
when her letter
was finished, she saw,
to her
infinite surprise,
there was reason to fear
that her mother
had been too ingenious
for her.
On opening the door,
she perceived her
sister and Bingley,
standing together
over the hearth
as if engaged in
earnest conversation,
and had this led
to no suspicion.
The faces of both,
as they
hastily turned round
and moved away
from each other,
would have told it all.
Their situation
was awkward enough,
but hers
thought was still worse.
Not a syllable
was uttered by either,
and Elizabeth
was on the point
of going away.
Again when.
Bingley,
who as well
as the other, had
sat down, suddenly
rose and whispering
a few words
to her sister,
ran out of the room.
Jane could have
no reserves
from Elizabeth,
where confidence
would give pleasure
and instantly
embracing her,
acknowledged
the liveliest emotion
that she was
the happiest creature
in the world.
Tis too much,
she added, By
far too much.
I do not deserve it.
Why Is everybody
not as happy?
Elizabeth's
congratulations
were given
with a sincerity,
a warmth, a delight
which words could
but poorly express.
Every sentence of
was a fresh source
of happiness to Jane.
But she would not.
Allow herself
to stay with her sister
or say
half that
remained to be said
for the present.
I must go instantly
to my Mother, she cried.
I would
not on any
account trifle
with her
affectionate solicitude
or allow her to hear
from anyone but myself.
He has gone
to my father already.
Oh, Lizzie
To know that
what I have to relate to
will give such pleasure
to all my dear family.
How shall I bear so much
happiness?
She then hastened
away to her mother,
who had purposely
broken up card party
and was sitting upstairs
with Kitty Elizabeth,
who was left by herself.
Now smiled at
the rapidity and ease
with which
such an affair
was finally settled.
That had given them
so many
previous months of.
Suspense and.
Vexation.
And this said
She is the end
of all his friends,
anxious circumspection
of all his sisters
falsehood
and contrivance.
The happiest, wisest,
most reasonable end.
In a few minutes,
she was joined
by Bingley,
whose conference
with her
father had been short
and to the purpose.
Where is your sister?
Said he hastily,
as he opened the door.
With my mother upstairs.
She would be down
in a moment, I daresay.
He then shut the door
and coming up
to her claimed
the good wishes
and affection
of a sister.
Elizabeth honestly
and heartily
expressed her delight
in the prospect
of their relationship.
They shook hands
with great cordiality
and then till her sister
came down,
she had to listen to all
he had to say
of his own happiness
and of Jane's
perfections.
And in spite of his
being a lover.
Elizabeth
really believed
all his expectations
of Felicity
to be
rationally founded.
Because.
They had four basis,
the excellent
understanding and super
excellent
disposition of Jane,
and a general similarity
of feeling and taste
between her and himself.
It was an evening
of no common
delight to them all
the satisfaction of Mr.
Bennett's Mind
gave a glow
of such sweet animation
to her face as made her
look handsomer
than ever.
Kitty Simper
and smiled and hoped her
turn was coming soon.
Mrs.
Bennett could
give her consent
or speaker
approbation in terms
warm enough
to satisfy her feelings,
though she talks
to Bingley
of nothing else
for half an hour,
and when Mr.
Bennett joined him
at supper.
His voice.
Manner plainly showed
how really happy he was.
Not a word,
however,
passed his lips
in allusion to it,
till their visitor
took his leave
for the night.
But as soon as
he was gone,
he turned to
his daughter and said.
Jane,
I congratulate you.
You will be a very happy
woman.
Jane went to him,
instantly, kissed him,
and thanked him
for his goodness.
You a good girl?
He replied.
And I have
great pleasure
in thinking
you will be so
happily settled.
I have not a doubt
of your doing
very well together.
Your tempers are by
no means unlike
who you are,
each of you
so complying
that nothing
will be ever resolved on
so easy
that every servant
will cheat you
and so generous that
you will always
exceed your income.
I hope not.
So imprudence
or thoughtlessness
in money
matters
would be unpardonable
in me.
Exceed that income.
My dear Mr.
Bennett.
Cried his wife.
What are you talking of?
Why?
He has four
or 5000 a year
and very likely more.
Than addressing
her daughter.
How?
My dear, dear Jane,
I am so happy.
I am sure
I shan't get a
wink of sleep all night.
I knew how it would be.
I always said
it must be so at last.
I was sure
you could not be so
for nothing.
I remember
as soon as ever
I saw him
when he first came
into Hertfordshire
last year,
I thought how likely
it was that
you should
come together.
Oh, he is the
handsomest young
that ever was seen.
Wickham, Lydia.
Were all.
Forgotten.
Jane was
beyond competition.
Her favorite child.
At that moment,
she cared for no other.
Her younger sisters
soon began
to make interest
with her
for objects
of happiness,
which she
might in future be able
to dispense.
Mary petitioned
for the use
of the library
at Netherfield,
and Kitty
begged very hard
for a few balls there
every winter.
Bingley
from this time was,
of course, a
daily visitor at Long.
Bourne.
Coming frequently before
breakfast and always
till after supper.
Unless when
some barbarous neighbor
who could not be enough
detested, had given him
an invitation to dinner,
which he thought
himself obliged
to accept.
Elizabeth Had
now but little time
for conversation
with her sister.
For while
he was present,
Jane had no attention
to bestow on
anyone else.
But she found herself
considerably useful.
To both of them
in those hours
of separation
that must
sometimes occur
in the absence of Jane.
He always
attached himself
to Elizabeth
for the pleasure
of talking with her.
And when Bingley
was gone.
Jane.
Constantly
sought the same
means of relief.
He has made me
so happy,
said she one evening
by telling me
that he was
totally ignorant
of my being in town.
Last spring.
I had not believed it
possible.
I suspected as much,
said Elizabeth.
But how do you account
for it?
It must have been
his sister's doing.
They were certainly
no friends.
His acquaintance
with me,
which I cannot
wonder at,
since he might
have chosen
so much
more advantageously
in many respects.
But when they see,
as I trust.
They will,
that the brother is.
Happy with me.
They will
learn to be contented
and we shall be
on good terms again.
Though we can never be
what we.
Once were to each other.
That is the most
unforgiving speech,
said Elizabeth
that I ever heard
you utter.
Good girl.
It would vex me indeed,
to see you again.
The dupe of miss
being these pretended
regard.
Would you believe it,
Lizzie
That when you
went to town
last November,
he really loved me
and nothing
but a dissuasion
of my being indifferent
would have prevented
is coming down again.
He made a little,
to be sure, but it is.
To the credit
of his modesty.
This naturally
introduced a panegyric
from Jane
on his diffidence
and the little value
he put on his own
good qualities.
Elizabeth was pleased
to find that
he had not betrayed
the interference
of his friend.
For, though,
Jane had the
most generous
and forgiving
heart in the world.
She knew it was
a circumstance
which must prejudiced
her against him.
I am certainly the most
fortunate creature
that ever existed,
cried Jane.
How, Lizzie?
Why am I thus
singled from my family
and blessed above all?
If I could
but see you as happy.
If there were
but such another
man for you.
If you were to
give me 40 such men.
I could.
Never be so happy as.
You till I
have your disposition.
Your goodness.
I can never
have your happiness.
No, no.
Let me shift for myself.
And perhaps
if I have very
good luck,
I meet with another Mr.
Collins in time.
The situation of affairs
in the long
born family
could not be long
a secret.
Mrs.
Bennet was privileged
to whisper it to Mrs.
Phillips,
and she ventured
without any permission
to do the same
by all her neighbors
in Maritain.
The bayonets
were speedily
pronounced to be
the luckiest
family in the world,
though
only a few weeks Before,
when Lydia had
first run away.
They had been.
Generally proved
to be marked out
for misfortune.
Chapter 56.
One.
About a week
after Bailey's
engagement with Jane
had been formed, as he
and the females
of the family
were sitting together
in the dining room,
their attention
was suddenly drawn
to the window
by the
sound of a carriage,
and they perceived
a shares
and for
driving up the lawn.
It was too early
in the morning
for visitors.
And besides,
the equipage
did not answer to that
of any of
their neighbors.
The horses
were purchased
and neither the carriage
nor the livery
of the servant
who preceded it
were familiar to them.
As it was certain,
however, that
somebody was coming.
Bingley instantly
prevailed on
Miss Spanish
to avoid the confinement
of such an intrusion
and walk away with him
into the shrubbery.
They both set off
and the conjectures
of the remaining
three continued.
Though.
With little satisfaction
till the door
was thrown open
and their
visitor entered.
It was Lady
Catherine de Berg.
They were of course
all intending
to be surprised,
but their astonishment
was beyond
their expectation.
And on the part of Mrs.
Bennet and.
Kitty, though.
She was
perfectly unknown
to them, even to what
Elizabeth felt,
she entered the room
with an error
more than
usually ungracious.
Made.
No other reply
to Elizabeth's
salutation,
then a slight
inclination of the head
and sat down
without saying a word.
Elizabeth had
mentioned her
name to her mother
on her
Ladyship entrance,
though
no request
of introduction
had been made.
Mrs.
Bennet all amazement,
though flattered
by having a guest
of such high importance,
received her
with the
utmost politeness.
After sitting for
a moment in silence,
she said very stiffly,
Elizabeth.
I hope you are well,
Miss Bennet.
That lady,
I suppose,
is your mother.
Elizabeth replied
very concisely
that she was.
And that, I.
Suppose, is
one of your sisters.
Yes, madam.
Said Mrs.
Bennet, delighted
to speak
to Lady Catherine.
She is my youngest girl,
but one.
My youngest of all
is lately married
and my eldest
is somewhere
about the grounds.
Walking
with the young man
who I believe will soon
become a part
of the family.
You have a
very small park here.
Returned Lady Catherine,
after a short silence.
It is nothing in
comparison of
two things, my lady.
I daresay, but
I assure you
it is much larger
than Sir
William Lucas's.
This must be
most inconvenient
sitting room
for the evening
and summer.
The windows are full
west.
Mrs.
Bennett assured her
that they never
sat there after dinner
and then added.
May I take the liberty
of asking your Ladyship
whether you left Mr.
and Mrs.
Collins? Well.
Yes, very well.
I saw them the night
before last.
Elizabeth now
expected that
she would
produce a letter
for her from Charlotte,
as it seemed
the only probable motive
for her calling.
But no letter appeared,
and she was
completely puzzled.
Mrs.
Bennett,
with great civility,
begged her ladyship
to take
some refreshment.
But Lady Catherine,
very resolutely
and not very
politely declined
eating.
Anything
and then rising.
Up, said to Elizabeth.
Miss Bennett,
the seem to be
a pretty ish
kind of a
little wilderness
on one side
of your lawn.
I should be glad
to take a turn in it,
if you will favor me
with your company.
Go, my dear.
Cried her mother,
and show her
ladyship about.
The various walks.
I think she will
be pleased
with the Hermitage.
Elizabeth obeyed
and running
into her own room
for her
parasol, attended her
noble guest downstairs
as they passed
through the hall.
Lady Catherine
opened the doors
into the dining parlor
and drawing room
and pronouncing them.
After a short survey.
Be decent looking rooms.
Walked on her carriage,
remained at the door,
and Elizabeth saw that
her waiting
woman was in it.
They proceeded
in silence along
the gravel walk
led to the corpse.
Elizabeth was determined
to make no effort
for conversation
with a woman
who was now more
than usually insolent
and disagreeable.
How could I ever think.
Her like a.
Nephew?
Said she, as she looked
in her face.
As soon.
As they entered
the corpse Lady.
Catherine began
in the following manner.
You can be at
no loss, Miss Bennet,
to understand the reason
of my journey hither.
Your own heart,
your own conscience
must tell you why
I come.
Elizabeth
with unaffected
astonishment.
Indeed.
You are
mistaken, Madame.
I have not been at
all able
to account for the honor
of seeing you here.
Miss Bennet
replied her Ladyship,
in an angry tone.
You ought to know
that I am not to
be trifled with.
But however insincere
you may choose to be,
you shall not find me.
My character
has ever been celebrated
for its sincerity
and frankness.
And in a cause of
such moment as this,
I shall certainly not
depart from it.
A report
of a most
alarming nature
reached me.
Two days ago
I was told that
not only was your sister
on the point
of being most
advantageously married,
but that you
that Miss
Elizabeth Bennet
would in all likelihood
be soon afterwards.
United to my nephew,
my own nephew, Mr.
Darcy.
Though I know it
must be a scandalous
falsehood,
though
I would not injure him
so much as to suppose
the truth of it
is possible.
I instantly resolved
on setting off
for this place
that I might make my
sentiments known to you
if you believed it.
Impossible to be true.
Said Elizabeth, coloring
with astonishment
and disdain.
I wonder you
took the trouble
of coming so far.
What could Your Ladyship
propose by it
at once to insist
upon having
such a report
universally
contradicted?
You're coming
too long,
borne to see me
and my family?
Said Elizabeth coolly.
Will be rather
a confirmation of it,
if indeed such
a report
is in existence.
If do you
then pretend to be
ignorant of it?
Has it not been
industriously
by yourselves?
Do you not know
that such
a report
is spread about?
I never heard
that it was.
And can you likewise.
Declare.
That there is
no foundation for it?
I do not pretend
to possess
equal frankness
with your Ladyship.
You may ask questions
which I shall not
choose to answer.
This is not to be borne,
Miss Bennet.
I insist on
being satisfied.
Has he?
Has my nephew made
you an offer
of marriage?
Your Ladyship
has declared it
to be impossible.
It ought to be so.
It must be so.
While he retains
the use of his reason.
But to your
ought a lawman
to may,
in a moment
of infatuation,
have made him
forget what
he owes to himself
and to all his family.
You may have
drawn him in.
If I have,
shall be the last person
to confess it.
Miss Bennet,
do you know who I am?
I have not
been accustomed
to language
such as this?
I am almost
the nearest relation
he has in the world.
And I'm entitled to know
all his
dearest concerns.
But you are not entitled
to know mine.
Nor Will such behavior
as this ever induce me
to be explicit?
Let me be
rightly understood.
This match
to which
you have the presumption
to aspire
can never take place.
No, never.
Mr.
Darcy is
engaged to my daughter.
Now, what
have you to say?
Only This.
That.
If he is so,
you can have no reason
to suppose
he'll make an offer
to me.
Lady Catherine
hesitated for a moment
and then replied.
The engagement
between them
of a peculiar kind.
From their infancy,
they have been intended
for each other.
It was the favorite
wish of his mother,
as well as of hers.
While in their cradles.
We planned the union.
And now, with the moment
when the wishes
of both sisters
would be accomplished
in their marriage,
to be prevented
by a young woman
of inferior,
but of no importance
in the world,
and wholly
an ally to the family.
Do you pay
no regard to
the wishes
of his friends,
to his tacit
engagement with Mr.
Berg?
Are you lost to
every feeling
of, propriety
and delicacy?
Have you not
heard me say that
from his earliest hours
he was destined
for his cousin?
Yes, and
I had heard it before.
But is that to me?
If there is no
other objection
to my marrying
your nephew,
I shall
certainly not
be kept from it.
By knowing that
his mother and aunt.
Wished him to marry Mr.
Burke.
You both did
as much as you could
in planning
the marriage.
Its completion
depended on others.
If Mr.
Darcy.
Is neither by honor.
Nor inclination
confined to his cousin,
why is he not
to make another choice?
And if I am that choice,
why may I not
accept him?
Because.
Honor, decorum,
prudence, nay,
interest, forbid.
Yes, Miss Bennet.
Interest four
Do not expect to be.
Noticed by his family.
Or friends.
If you willfully act
against the inclinations
of all, you will be
censured, slighted,
and despised by everyone
connected with him.
Your alliance
will be a disgrace.
Your name will never
even be mentioned
by any of us.
These are heavy
misfortunes,
replied Elizabeth.
But the wife of Mr.
Darcy must have
such extraordinary
sources of happiness
necessarily attached
her situation
that she could, upon
the whole, have no cause
to opine.
Obstinate,
headstrong girl.
I am ashamed of you.
Is this your gratitude
for my attentions
to you?
Last spring
is nothing do to me
on that score.
Let us sit down.
You are to
understand, Mr. Bennett.
That I came here
with a determined.
Resolution
of carrying my purpose.
Nor will
I be dissuaded from it.
I have not been used
to submit
to any person's whims.
I have not in the habit
of Brooking
disappointment
that will make Your
Ladyship situation
at present
more pitiable.
But it will have
no effect on me.
I will be interrupted.
Hear me in silence.
My daughter
and my nephew are formed
for each other.
They are descended
on the maternal side
from the same noble line
and on the farthest
from respectable,
honorable and ancient,
though
one titled families.
Their fortune on both
sides is splendid.
They are destined
for each other
by the voice
of every member
of their
respective houses.
And what is to
divide them?
The upstart
pretensions
of a young woman
without family,
connections or fortune.
Is this to be endured?
But it must not.
Shall not be.
If you were
sensible of
your own good,
you would not
wish to quit the sphere
in which you have
been brought.
In marrying your nephew,
I should not
consider myself
as quitting that sphere.
He is a gentleman.
I am a
gentleman's daughter.
So far we are equal.
True.
You are a
gentleman's daughter.
But who was your mother?
Who are your uncles
and aunts?
Do not imagine me
ignorant of
their condition.
Whatever
my connections may be,
said Elizabeth.
If your nephew does
not object to them,
they can be
nothing to you.
Tell me once
and for all.
Are You engaged
to him?
Though
Elizabeth would not,
for the mere purpose
of obliging
Lady Catherine
have answered
this question.
She could not but.
Say after a moment's
deliberation.
I am not.
Lady Catherine
seemed pleased.
And will you promise me
never to enter into
such an engagement?
I will make
promise of the kind.
Miss Bennet,
I am shocked
and astonished.
I expected to find
a more reasonable
young woman.
But do not
deceive yourself
into a belief
that I will ever recede.
I shall not go away
till you have given me
the assurance I require.
And I certainly
never shall give it.
I am not to be
intimidated
into anything
so wholly unreasonable.
Your Ladyship wants Mr.
Darcy
to marry your daughter.
But would my giving you
the wished for promise
make that marriage
at all more probable?
Supposing him
to be attached to me?
What am I refusing
to accept his hand
to make him
wish to bestow it
on his cousin?
Allow me.
To say,
Lady Catherine,
that the.
Arguments
which you have
supported this
extraordinary
application have been
as frivolous
as the application
was ill judged.
You have
wisely mistaken.
My. Character.
If you think I
can be worked
by such persuasions
as these,
how far your nephew
might approve
of your interference in.
His affairs.
I cannot tell.
But do you
have certainly no right
to concern
yourself in mine?
I must. Beg.
Therefore, to
be important.
No father.
On the.
Subject.
Not so hasty,
if you please.
I have by no means done
to all the objection
I have already urged.
I have still
another to add.
I am no stranger
to the particulars
of your
youngest sister's
infamous elopement.
I know it all that
the young man's
marrying her
was a
patched up business
at the expense
of your father
and uncles.
And is such a girl to be
my nephew's sister.
Is her husband
is the son of his late
father Stewart.
To be his brother.
Heaven and earth.
Of What
are you thinking?
Are the.
Shades.
Of Pemberley
to be thus polluted?
You can now have.
Nothing further to say.
She resentfully.
Answered.
You have insulted me in
every possible method.
I must beg to return
the house.
And she rose
as she spoke.
Lady Catherine
Rose also.
And they turned back.
Her Ladyship was
highly incensed.
You have no regard.
Then, for honor
and credit of my.
Nephew.
Unfeeling, selfish girl.
Do you not consider
that a connection
with you?
Must disgrace him
in the eyes
of everybody.
Lady Catherine,
I have nothing further
to say.
You know my sentiments.
You are then
resolved to have him.
I have said no
such thing.
I am only resolved
to act in that manner,
which will,
in my own
opinion, constitute
my happiness
without reference to you
or to any person so
wholly unconnected
with me.
It is well,
he refused
then to oblige me.
You refuse to obey
the claims of duty,
honor and gratitude.
You are determined
to ruin him
and the opinion
of all his friends
and to make him the
contempt of the world.
Neither duty
nor honor, nor.
Gratitude,
replied Elizabeth.
Have any possible.
Claim on me
in the present.
Instance.
No principle.
Of either.
Would be violated
by my marriage with Mr.
D'Arcy and with regard
to the resentment
of his family
or the indignation
of the world.
If the former
were excited.
By his marrying.
Me, it would not give me
one moment's concern
and the world.
In general.
Would have
too much sense
to join in the scorn.
And this is
your real opinion.
This is final resolve.
Very well.
I shall now
know how to act.
Do not imagine,
Miss Bennet,
that your ambition
will ever be gratified.
I to try you.
I hoped to find
you reasonable,
but depend upon it.
I will carry my point.
In this manner.
Lady Catherine talked
till they were
at the door
of the carriage.
When turning
hastily round,
she added.
I take no leave of you,
Miss Bennet.
I send no
compliments to
your mother.
You deserve no such.
I am most seriously
displeased.
Elizabeth made
no answer, and without
attempting
to persuade her Ladyship
to return into,
the house.
Walked.
Quietly into it herself.
She heard the carriage
drive away
as she proceeded
upstairs.
Her mother impatiently
met her at the door
of the dressing room
to ask why
Lady Catherine
would not come in again
and rest herself.
She did not choose it.
Said her daughter.
She would go.
She is a very fine
looking woman
and her calling here
prodigiously.
Civil society
came,
I suppose, to tell us
the Collins's were well,
She is on her road
somewhere, I daresay.
And so passing
through Merritt
and thought she might
as well call on you.
I suppose
she had nothing
particular to say
to you, Dizzy.
Elizabeth was
forced to give in
to a little
falsehood here
for to acknowledge
the substance of
their conversation
was impossible.
Chapter 57
The dis
composure of spirits,
which this
extraordinary visit
through Elizabeth into,
could not be
easily overcome.
Nor could she
for many hours
learn to think of it
less than incessantly.
Lady Catherine,
it appeared,
had actually
taken the trouble
of this journey
from Rose ings
for the sole purpose
of breaking off her
supposed engagement
with Mr.
Darcy.
It was a rational
scheme, to be sure,
but from what the report
of their engagement
could originate.
Elizabeth was at a loss
to imagine
till she recollected
that his
being the intimate
friend of Bingley
and her being
the sister of Jane
was enough at a time
when the expectation
of one wedding
made everybody eager
for another
to supply the idea.
She had not herself
forgotten to feel
that the marriage
of her sister
must bring them
more frequently together
and her neighbors
at Lucas Lodge.
Therefore,
for through
their communication
with the Collins's,
the report she concluded
had reached.
Lady Catherine
had only sat that down
as almost certain
and immediate.
Which she had.
Looked forward
to as possible
at some future time.
In revolving
Lady Katherine's
expressions, however.
She could not help.
Feeling some uneasiness
as to the
possible consequence
of her persisting
in this interference
from what she had
said of her resolution
to prevent
their marriage.
It occurred to Elizabeth
that she must meditate
application to
her nephew
and how he might take
a similar representation
of the evils
attached to a connection
with her.
She dared not pronounce.
She knew
not the exact degree
of his affection
for his aunt
or his dependance
on her judgment, but
it was natural
to suppose
that he thought
much higher
of her ladyship
than she could do.
And it was certain
that in enumerating
miseries of a marriage
with one.
Whose immediate.
Connections
were so unequal to his.
Own.
His aunt would
address him
on his weakest.
Side with his.
Notions of dignity.
He would probably feel
that the arguments
which to Elizabeth
had appeared
weak and ridiculous.
Contained.
Much good sense
and solid reasoning.
If he had been wavering.
Before as
what he should do,
which had often
seemed likely,
the advice
and entreaty of so near
relation
might settle every doubt
and determine him
at once to be as happy
as dignity, unblemished
make him.
In that case,
he would return no more.
Lady Catherine might
see him in her way
through town
and his engagement
to Bingley.
If coming again to
Netherfield must
give way.
If therefore
an excuse
for not
keeping his promise
to come to his friend
within a few days.
She added,
I shall know how
to understand it.
I shall give over
every expectation,
every wish
of his constancy.
If he is satisfied
with only regretting me
when he might
have obtained
my affections and hand,
I shall cease to.
Regret him at all.
The surprise
of the rest
of the family on hearing
who their visitor
had been was very great,
but they obligingly
satisfied it
with the
same kind supposition
which had appeased Mrs.
Bennett's curiosity.
And Elizabeth was spared
from much teasing
on the subject.
The next morning,
as she was
going downstairs,
she was met her father,
who came out
of his library
with a letter
in his hand.
Lizzie said, here.
I was going to
look for you.
Come into my room.
She followed him
thither,
and her curiosity
to know
what he had to tell
her was heightened
by the supposition
of its
being in some manner
connected
with the letter he held.
It suddenly struck her
that it might be
from Lady Catherine,
and she anticipated,
with dismay,
all the
consequent explanations.
She followed her
father to the fireplace
and they both sat down.
He then said.
I have received
a letter this morning
that has astonished me
exceedingly,
as it principally
concerns yourself.
You ought
to know its contents.
I did not know
before that
had two daughters
on the
brink of matrimony.
Let me congratulate you
on a very
important conquest.
The color now
rushed into
Elizabeth's cheeks
and the
instantaneous conviction
of its being a letter
from the nephew
instead of the aunt.
And she
was undetermined,
whether most to be
pleased that
he explained
himself at all
or offended
that his letter
was not rather
addressed to herself.
When her
father continued.
You look conscious.
Young ladies
have great penetration
in such matters
as these.
But I think I may defy
even your sagacity
to discover
the name of
your admirer.
This letter is for Mr.
Collins.
For Mr.
And what can
he have to say?
Something Very much
to the purpose,
of course.
He begins
with congratulations
on the approaching
nuptials
of my eldest daughter,
of which it seems
he has been told
by some of the
good natured
Lucas's
I shall not sport
with your impatience
by reading what he says
on that point.
What relates to yourself
is as follows.
Having thus offered you
the sincere
congratulations of Mrs.
Collins and
myself on this
happy event,
let me now add a short
hint on
the subject of another
of which
we have been advertised
by the same authority.
Your daughter,
Elizabeth,
it is presumed,
will not long bear
the name of Bennett
after her
eldest sister
has resigned.
It and the chosen
partner of her fate
may be reasonably
looked up to as one of
the most
illustrious personages
in this land.
Can you possibly guess
Lizzie,
who is meant by this?
This young gentleman
is blessed
in a peculiar way,
with everything
the heart of mortal
can most desire,
splendid property,
noble kindred,
and extensive patronage.
Yet, in spite
of all
these temptations,
let me warn
my Cousin Elizabeth
and yourself
of what evils
you may incur
by a precipitate closure
with this
gentleman's proposals.
Which,
of course, you
will be inclined
to take immediate
advantage of.
Have you
any idea, Lizzie, who
this gentleman is?
But now it comes out.
My motive
for cautioning you
as follows.
We have reason to
imagine that his aunt
Lady Catherine Nyborg,
does not
look on the match
with a friendly eye.
Mr., you see,
is the man.
Now, Lizzie,
I think
I have surprised you.
Could he or
the Lucas's
have pitched on any man
within the circle
of our acquaintance
whose name
would have given
the lie more effectually
to what they related
to Mr.
D'Arcy,
who never looks
at any woman.
But to see a blemish
and who probably
never looked at you
in his life.
It is admirable.
Elizabeth tried to join
in her
father's pleasantry,
but could only force one
most reluctant smile.
Never had
his wit
been directed
in a manner
so little
agreeable to her.
Oh, you're not diverted.
Oh, yes.
Read on.
After mentioning
the likelihood
of this marriage
to Her ladyship
last night,
she immediately,
with her
usual condescension,
expressed what she felt
on the occasion
when it became
apparent
that on the score
of some family
objections on the part,
my cousin,
she would never give
her consent
to what she termed
so disgraceful a match.
I thought it my duty
to give
the speediest
intelligence of this
to my cousin that she,
her noble admirer,
may be aware
of what they are about
and not run hastily
into a marriage
which has not
been properly
sanctioned.
Mr.
Collins, moreover, adds.
I'm truly rejoice that
my cousin Lydia's
sad business
has been so well
hushed up,
and I'm only concerned
that they're
living together
before the
marriage took place
should be so
generally known.
I must not,
however, neglect
the duties of my station
or refrain
from declaring
my amazement at hearing
that you received
the young couple
into your house
as soon as they
were married.
It was an encouragement
of Vice, and had
I been
the rector of
Long Bourn,
I should very
strenuously have
opposed it.
You ought
certainly to
forgive them
as a Christian,
but never to admit them
in your sight
or allow their names
to be
mentioned in
your hearing.
That is his notion
of Christian
forgiveness.
The rest of his letter
is only about his dear
Charlotte situation
and his expectation
of a young olive branch.
But,
Lizzie, you look as if
you did not enjoy it.
You are not going
to be Mrs..
I hope and pretend
to be affronted
at an idle report
for what do we live
but to make sport
for our neighbors
and laugh
at them in our turn.
Oh, cried.
Elizabeth.
I am excessively
diverted.
But it is so strange.
Yes, that is
what makes it amusing.
Had they fixed on
any other man,
it would have been
nothing
but his
perfect indifference
and your pointed dislike
make it so
delightfully absurd.
Much dominate writing.
I would not give up Mr.
Collins correspondence
for any consideration.
Nay, when I read
a letter of his,
I cannot help
giving him
the preference
even over Wickham, much
as I value impudence
and hypocrisy of my son
in law.
And pray.
Lizzie.
What said Lady
Catherine about
this report?
Did she call to refuse
her consent
to this?
His daughter
replied only with a.
Laugh, and as it.
Had been asked
without the
least suspicion.
She was not.
Distressed by his
repeating it.
Elizabeth had never been
more at a loss
to make her feelings
what they were not.
It was necessary
to laugh
when she would
rather have cried.
Her father
had most
cruelly mortified her
by what he said of Mr.
Darcy's indifference.
And she could do nothing
but wonder
at such
a want of penetration.
Or.
Fear that perhaps
instead of his
seeing too little, she
might have
fancied too much.
Chapter 58
Instead of receiving
any such letter
of excuse
from his friend
as Elizabeth
have expected Mr.
Bingley to do,
he was able
to bring Darcy with him
too long.
Born before
many days had passed
after Lady
Katherine's visit.
The gentleman arrived
early and before Mrs.
Bennett had time
to tell him of their
having seen his aunt,
of which her
daughter sat in
momentary dread.
Bingley,
who wanted to be alone
with Jane,
proposed their
all walking out.
It was agreed.
To. Mrs.
Bennett was not
in the habit of walking.
Mary could spare time,
but the remaining five
set off together.
Bingley and Jane,
however, soon
allowed the others
to outstrip them.
They lagged behind
while Elizabeth,
Kitty and Darcy
to entertain each other.
Very little
was said by either.
Kitty
was too much afraid
of him to talk.
Elizabeth
was secretly forming
a desperate resolution,
and perhaps he might
doing the same.
They walked towards.
The Lucas's
because Kitty wished
to call upon Maria,
and as Elizabeth saw
no occasion
for making it
a general concern.
When Kitty them,
she went boldly
on with him alone.
Now was the moment
for her resolution
to be executed.
And while
her courage was high,
she immediately said.
Mr.
Darcy,
I am a very
selfish creature
and for the sake
of giving relief
to my own feelings,
can not how much
I may be wounding yours.
I can no longer help
thanking you for your
an example of kindness
to my poor sister.
Ever since I.
Have known it,
I have been most anxious
to acknowledge to you
how gratefully I feel it
where it's known to the.
Rest of my family.
I should not have merely
my own.
Gratitude to express.
I am sorry.
Exceedingly sorry.
Replied Darcy,
in a tone of surprise
and emotion.
That you have
ever been informed
of what may
in a mistaken light
have given
you uneasiness.
I did not think Mrs.
Gardiner was so
little to be trusted.
You must
blame my Aunt
Lydia's thoughtlessness
first betrayed to me
that you had been
concerned in the matter.
And of course,
I could not rest
till I knew
the particulars.
Let me thank again
and again in the name
of all my family,
for that
generous compassion
which induced you
to take so much trouble
and bear
so many mortification
for the sake of
discovering them.
If you will thank me.
He replied.
Let it be
for yourself alone
that the wish
of giving happiness
to you might add force
to the other inducements
led me on.
I shall not
attempt to deny,
but your family owe me
nothing
much as I respect them.
I believe
I thought only of you.
Elizabeth Was too much
embarrassed
to say a word.
After a short pause,
her companion added.
You are too generous
to trifle with me.
If your feelings
are still what
they were last April,
tell me so at once.
My affections
and wishes
are unchanged.
But one word from you
will silence me on
this subject forever.
Elizabeth Feeling
all the
more than
common awkwardness
and anxiety
of a situation now
forced herself to speak
and immediately, though
not very fluently,
gave him to understand
that her sentiments
had undergone
so materially change
since the period
to which he alluded.
As to make her receive
with gratitude
and pleasure
his present assurances.
The happiness
which this
reply produced,
such as he had
probably never
felt before,
and he expressed himself
on the occasion
as sensibly
and as warmly as a man
violently in love
can be supposed to do.
Had Elizabeth been able
to encounter his eye,
she might have seen
how well the expression
of heartfelt delight
diffused over
his face became him.
But though.
She could not look,
she could listen.
And.
He told her of feelings,
which, in
proving of
what importance
she was to him,
made his affection
every moment
more valuable.
They walked on
without knowing
in what direction.
There was too much
to be thought and felt
and said for attention
to any other objects.
She soon learned
that they were indebted
for their present
good understanding
to the efforts
of his aunt,
who did call on him
in her return
through London,
and there
relate her journey
to long born.
Its motive
and the substance
of her conversation
with Elizabeth.
Dwelling emphatically
on expression
of the latter,
which in her Ladyship
apprehension
particularly denoted her
perverse ness
and assurance
in the belief
that such a relation
must assist
her endeavors
to obtain that promise
from her nephew,
which she had refused
to give.
But unluckily
for her Ladyship,
its effect
had been
exactly contrariwise.
It taught me to hope.
Said he.
As I had scarcely ever
allowed myself
to hope before
I knew
enough of
your disposition
to be certain
that had you
been absolutely,
irrevocably decided
against me,
you would have
acknowledged it
to Lady Catherine,
frankly and openly.
Elizabeth colored
and laughed
as she replied.
Yes.
You know
enough of my frankness
to believe me
capable of that
after abusing you so
abominably to your face.
I could have
no scruple in
abusing you
to all your relations.
What did you say of me
that I did not deserve?
For though
your accusations were
ill founded,
Formed on
mistaken premises,
my behavior to you
at the time
had merited
the severest reproof.
It was unpardonable.
I cannot think of it
without abhorrence.
We will not quarrel
for the greater
shame of blame.
Next.
That evening,
said Elizabeth.
The conduct of neither,
if strictly.
Examined.
Will be a.
But since then,
we have both,
I hope,
improved in civility.
I cannot be so easily
reconciled to myself.
The recollection,
what I
then said of my conduct,
my manners,
my expressions
during the whole of it
is now and has been
many months
and expressively
painful to me.
Your reproof
so well applied.
I shall never forget,
had you behaved
in a more gentleman
like manner.
Those were your words,
you know. Not.
You can
scarcely conceive
how they have
tortured me,
though
it was some time,
I confess, before
I was reasonable enough
to allow that justice.
I was certainly very far
from expecting them
to make so strong
an impression.
I had not the
smallest idea
of their being
ever felt in such a way.
I can easily believe it.
You thought me
then, devoid
of every proper feeling.
I'm sure you did.
The tone of
your countenance.
I shall never forget,
as you said,
that I could not have
addressed you
any possible way
that would
induce you to accept me.
Oh, do not repeat
what I then said.
These recollections
will not do at all.
I assure you that
I have long
been most heartily
ashamed of it.
D'Arcy mentioned letter.
Did it?
Said he did it soon.
Make you think
better of me.
Did you, on reading it,
give any credit
to its contents?
She explained
what its effect on
her had been
and how gradually
all her former
prejudices had
been removed.
I knew, said he,
that what
I must give you pain,
but it was necessary.
I hope
you have destroyed
the letter.
There was one part,
especially the
opening of it,
which I should dread.
Your having the power
of reading again.
I can remember
some expressions
which might justly make
you hate me.
The latter
shall certainly
be burnt.
If you believe it
essential
to the preservation
of my. Regard.
But there
we have both reason
to think my opinions
not entirely
unalterable.
They are not,
I hope, quite so easily.
Changed as that.
Implies.
When I wrote
that letter.
Replied Darcy.
I.
Believed myself
perfectly calm and cool,
but I am since convinced
that it was written
in a dreadful
bitterness of spirit.
The letter perhaps began
in bitterness,
but it did not end.
So
the adieu is
charity itself.
But think no
more of the letter.
The feelings
of the person
who wrote and.
The person
who received it
are now so widely.
From what they.
Then were
that every
unpleasant circumstance
attending
it ought
to be forgotten.
You must learn
some of my philosophy.
Think only of the past
as remembrance
gives you pleasure.
I cannot give you credit
for any philosophy
of the kind.
Your retrospection
must be so totally void
of reproach
that the contentment
arising from
is not a philosophy.
But what is much
better of ignorance?
But with me,
it is not so
painful.
Recollections
will intrude,
which cannot which
not to be repelled.
I have been a
selfish being
all my life in practice,
though not in principle.
As a child, I was taught
what was right.
But I was not
taught to correct
my temper.
I was given
good principles,
but left to follow them
in pride and conceit.
Unfortunately,
and only son.
For many years,
an only child.
I was spoiled
by my parents,
who though
good themselves.
My father, particularly.
All that was benevolent
and amiable, allowed,
almost taught me
to be selfish
and overbearing,
to care for none beyond
my own family circle,
to think
meanly of
all the rest
of the world,
to wish
at least to think meanly
of their sense
and worth.
Compared with my own
such, I was
from 8 to 8 and 20
and such.
I might still have been,
but for you
dearest,
loveliest Elizabeth.
What do I not owe you?
You taught me a lesson.
Hard, indeed, at first,
but most advantageous
by you.
I was properly humbled.
I came to you
without a doubt
of my reception.
You showed me
how insufficient
were all my pretensions.
Please.
A woman
worthy of being pleased.
Had you
then persuaded yourself
that I should?
Indeed I had.
What will you
think of my vanity?
I believed you
to be wishing, expecting
my addresses.
My manners must have.
Been in fault.
But not intentionally,
I assure you.
I never meant to
deceive you.
But my spirits
might often be wrong.
How?
You must have hated me
after that evening.
Hate you?
I was angry,
perhaps at first,
but my anger soon began
to take a
proper direction.
I was
almost afraid of asking
what he thought of me
when we met
at Pemberley.
You blamed me
for coming?
No, indeed.
I felt nothing but
surprise.
Your surprise could not.
Be greater than mine
in being noticed.
By you.
My conscience told me
that I deserved
no extraordinary
politeness.
And I confess
that I did not expect
to receive
more than my due.
My object then.
Replied Darcy.
Was to show you
by every civility
in my power
that I was not so mean
as to resent the past.
And I hoped to obtain
forgiveness to lessen
your ill opinion
by letting
you see that
your reproof
had been attended to.
How soon any other
wishes
introduce themselves?
I can hardly tell.
But I believe
in about half an
hour after I
had seen you.
He then
told her of Georgina's
delight
in her acquaintance
and of her
disappointment at,
its sudden interruption,
which naturally leading
to the cause
of that interruption.
She soon learned
that his resolution
of following her
from Derbyshire
in quest of her sister
had been formed
before he quit
at the end,
and that his gravity
and thoughtfulness
there had arisen from
no other struggles
than what such a purpose
must comprehend.
She expressed her
gratitude again,
but it was too painful
a subject
to each to be dwelt
on further.
After walking
several miles
in a leisurely manner
and too busy
to know
anything about it,
they found at last
on examining
their watches
that it was time
to be at home.
What could become of Mr.
Bingley and Jane.
Was a wonder
which introduced
the discussion
of their affairs.
Darcy was delighted
with their engagement.
His friend had given him
the earliest
information of it.
I must ask
whether you
were surprised,
said Elizabeth.
Not at all.
When I went away,
I felt that it
would soon happen.
That is to
say, you had
given your permission.
I guessed as much.
And though he
exclaimed at the time,
she found that
it had been
pretty much the.
Case.
On the evening
before my going
to London.
Said he.
I made a confession
to him,
which I believe
I ought to have made
long ago.
I told him of all
that had occurred
to make
my former interference
in his affairs absurd
and impertinent.
His surprise was great.
He Had never had
the slightest suspicion.
I told him, moreover,
that I believed myself
mistaken in supposing,
as I had done, that
your sister
was indifferent to him,
and as I could
perceive that
his attachment to her
was unabated.
I felt no doubt of
their happiness
together.
Elizabeth could
not help, smiling
at his easy manner
of directing his friend.
Did you speak from
your own observation?
Said she,
when you told him
that my sister
loved him,
or merely
for my information.
Last spring
from the former?
I had narrowly
observed her
during the two visits,
which I had lately
made her here,
and I was convinced
of her affection.
And your assurance.
It, I suppose,
carried immediate
conviction to him.
It did.
Bingley is most
unaffected, Li modest.
His diffidence
had prevented
his depending
on his own judgment,
so anxious a case.
But his reliance on mine
made everything easy.
I was obliged
to confess one thing,
which for a time
and not unjustly
offended him.
I could not allow myself
to conceal
that your sister
had been in town
three months
last winter.
That I had known it
and purposely kept
it from him.
He was angry.
But his anger,
I am persuaded,
lasted no longer
than he remained
in any doubt
of your sister's
sentiments.
He has heartily
forgiven me now.
Elizabeth longed
to observe that Mr.
Bingley had been a most
delightful friend,
so easily guided that
his worth
was invaluable.
But she checked herself.
She remembered
that he had yet
to learn to be
laughed at,
and it was rather too
early to begin
in anticipating
the happiness
of Bingley,
which of course
was to be inferior
only to his own.
He continued
the conversation
till they reached
the house in the hall
they parted.
Chapter 59.
My dear Lizzie.
Where can you have been
walking to?
Was the question
which Elizabeth
received from Jane
as soon as
she entered their room
and from all the others
when they sat
down to table.
She had only to say
in reply
that they had
wandered about
till she was beyond
her own knowledge.
She colored
as she spoke, but
neither that nor
anything else
awakened to suspicion
of the truth.
The evening
passed quietly,
unmarked by anything
extraordinary.
The acknowledged lovers
talked and laughed.
The unacknowledged
were silent.
Darcy was not
of a disposition
in which happiness
overflows in mirth.
And Elizabeth
agitated and confused.
Rather knew that
she was happy,
then felt
herself to be so
for besides the
immediate embarrassment.
There were
other evils her.
She anticipated
what would be felt
in the family
when her situation
became known.
She was aware
that no one
liked him but.
Jane, and.
Even feared that
with the others
it was a dislike
which not all
his fortune
and consequence
might do away.
At night,
she opened her heart
to Jane, though
suspicion was very far
from Mr.
Bennett's habits.
She was
absolutely incredulous.
Here you are
choking, Lizzie.
This cannot be engaged
to Mr. Darcy.
No, no.
You shall not
deceive me.
I know it to
be impossible.
This is a
wretched beginning.
Indeed.
My soul
dependent was on you.
And I am sure
nobody else
will believe me
if you do not.
Yet indeed,
I am in earnest.
I speak
nothing with the truth.
He still loves me.
And we are engaged.
Jane looked at her
Doubting Lee.
Oh, Lizzie,
it cannot be.
I know how much
you dislike him.
You know
nothing of the matter.
That Is all
to be forgot.
Perhaps I did
not always love him.
So well as I.
Do now.
But in such cases
as these good memories
unpardonable.
This is the last time.
I shall.
Ever remember it.
Myself.
Miss Bennet
still looked
all amazement.
Elizabeth again
and more
seriously assured her
of its truth.
Go to heaven.
Can it really be so?
It's now.
I must believe you,
cried Jane.
My dear, dear
Lizzie, I would.
I do congratulate you.
But are you certain?
Forgive the question.
Are you quite certain
that you can be
happy with him?
There can be
no doubt of that.
It is settled
between us already
that we ought to be
the happiest couple
in the world.
But are you
pleased, Jane?
Shall you like to have
such a brother?
Very, very much.
Nothing Could
give either
Bingley or myself
more delight.
But we considered it.
We talked of it
as impossible.
And
do you really love him
quite well enough?
Oh, Lizzie
do anything
rather than marry
without affection.
Are you quite sure
that you feel
what you ought to do?
Oh, yes.
You will only think
I feel more
than I ought
do when I tell you all.
What do you mean?
Why?
I must confess
that I love him
better than I do
Bingley.
I am afraid
you will be angry.
My sister.
Now be serious.
I want to talk
very seriously.
Let me know everything
that I am to know
without delay.
Will you tell me
how you have loved him?
It has been coming on
so gradually that I
hardly know
when it began.
But I believe
I must date it
for my first
seeing his
beautiful grounds
at Pemberley.
Another entreaty
that she would be
serious, however,
produced the
desired effect.
And she soon
satisfied Jane
by her solemn assurances
of attachment.
When convinced
on that article,
Miss Bennet had nothing
further to wish.
Now I am quite happy,
said she.
For you will be as happy
as myself.
I always had a
value for him.
Were it for nothing
but his love of you.
I must always
have esteemed him.
But now, as
Bigley's friend
and your husband,
that can only be Bingley
and yourself
more dear to me.
But, Lizzie,
you have been very sly,
very reserved with me.
How little
did you tell me
of what passed
at Pemberley Lambton?
I owe all that.
I know of it to another,
not to you.
Elizabeth told her
the motives
of her secrecy.
She had been unwilling
to mention Bingley
and the unsettled state
of her own
feelings
had made her equally
avoid the
name of his friend.
But now she would
no longer
conceal from her
his share,
and that his marriage
always acknowledged
and half the night spent
in conversation.
Good gracious!
Cried Mrs.
Bennet
as she stood at a window
the next morning.
If that disagreeable Mr.
Darcy
not coming here again
with our dear Bingley,
what can he mean
by being so tiresome
as to always
be coming here?
I had no notion,
but he would go
with shooting or
something or other.
And not disturb us
with his company.
What shall we do
with him, Lizzie?
You must walk
out with him again.
That he may not be
in big this way.
Elizabeth
could hardly
help laughing
so convenient.
A proposal yet
was really vexed
that her mother
should be always
giving him
such an epithet.
As soon as they entered,
Bingley looked at her
so expressively
and shook hands,
such warmth as left
no doubt of
his good information.
And he.
Soon afterwards
said aloud.
Mrs.
Bennet,
have you no more lanes
hereabouts
in which Lizzie may
lose her way
again today?
I advise Mr.
Darcy and
Lizzie and Kitty,
said Mrs.
Bennet,
to walk to Oakham
Mount this morning.
It is a nice long walk
and Mr.
Darcy has
never seen the view.
It may do very well
for the others.
Replied Mr.
Bingley, but I am.
Sure it will be
too much for Kitty,
won't it?
Kitty.
Kitty owned.
That she had
rather stay at.
Home.
Darcy professed
a great curiosity
to see the view
from the. Mount.
And Elizabeth
silently consented
as she went upstairs
to get ready.
Mrs.
Bennett followed
her, saying.
I am quite
sorry Lizzie,
that you should
be forced
to have that
disagreeable man
or do yourself, but
I hope you will
not mind it.
It is all for Jane
sake, you know.
And there is no occasion
for talking to him
except just
now and then.
So do not put yourself
to inconvenience.
During their walk,
it was resolved that Mr.
Bennet's consent
should be asked
in the course
of the evening.
Elizabeth reserved
to herself
the application
for her mother's.
She could not.
Determine
how her mother
would take it,
sometimes doubting
whether all his wealth
and grandeur
would be enough
to overcome
her abhorrence
of the man.
But whether she
were violently set
against the match
or violently
delighted with it,
it was certain
that her manner
would be
equally ill
adapted to due
credit to her sense
that she could
no more bear that Mr.
Darcy should hear
the first
raptures of her joy
than the first vehemence
of her disapprobation.
In the
evening, soon after Mr.
Bennett
withdrew to the library,
she saw Mr.
Darcy rise
also and follow him,
and her agitation on
seeing it was extreme.
She did not.
Fear her father's.
Opposition, but he.
Was going to
be made unhappy
and that it should be
through her.
Means that she.
His favorite child
should be
distressing him
by her choice,
should be filling him
with fears and regrets
and disposing of her
was a
wretched reflection.
And she sat in misery
till Mr.
Darcy appeared.
When looking at him,
she was a
little relieved
by his smile.
In a.
Few minutes,
he approached the table
where she was sitting
with Kitty
and while pretending
to admire her work,
said in a whisper.
Go to your father.
He wants you
in the library.
She was gone directly.
Her father was walking
about the room,
looking grave
and anxious.
Lizzie said he.
What are you doing?
Are you out
of your senses
to be accepting
this man?
Have not
you always hated him?
How earnestly
that she then
wished that her
former opinions
been more reasonable,
her expressions
more moderate.
It would have spared her
from explanations
and professions,
which it was exceedingly
awkward to give,
but they were now
necessary and
assured him
with some confusion
of her attachment to Mr.
Darcy.
Or in other words,
you are determined
to have him.
He is rich, to be sure,
and you may have more
fine clothes and fine
carriages than Jane,
but will
they make you happy?
Have you
any other objection?
Said Elizabeth.
Then your belief
of my indifference?
None at all.
We all know him to
a proud,
unpleasant sort of man.
But this would
be nothing
if you really liked him.
I do.
I do like him.
She replied
with tears in her eyes.
I love him.
Indeed.
He has no
improper pride.
He is perfectly amiable.
He do not know
what he really is.
Then pray,
do not pain me by of him
in such terms.
Lizzie said her father.
I have given him
my consent.
He is the kind
of man indeed, to whom
I should never dare
refuse anything
which he
condescended to ask.
I now give it to you
if you are resolved
on having him.
But let me advise you
to think better of it.
I know your
disposition, Lizzie.
I Know that you could be
neither happy
nor respectable
unless you
truly esteemed
your husband.
Unless you
looked up to him
as a superior.
Your lively talents
would place you
in greatest danger.
In an unequal marriage.
You could scarcely
escape, discredit,
and misery.
My child,
let me not
have the grief
of seeing you
to respect
your partner in life.
You know
not what you are about.
Elizabeth
still more affected
was earnest and solemn
in her reply
and at length
by repeated assurances
that Mr.
Darcy was really
the object
of her choice.
By explaining
the gradual change
which her
estimation of him
had undergone,
relating her
absolute certainty
that his affection
was not the
work of a day,
but had stood
the test of many months,
suspense. And.
Enumerating with energy
all his good qualities.
She did conquer her
father's incredulity
and reconcile him
to the match.
Well, my dear.
Said he,
when she sees speaking.
I have no more to say.
If this be the case,
he deserves.
I could not have parted
with you, my Lizzie,
to anyone less worthy.
To complete.
The favorable
impression.
She then told him
what Mr.
Darcy had
voluntarily done.
Lydia.
He heard her
with astonishment.
This is an evening
of wonders.
Indeed.
And so Darcy
did everything.
Made up the match.
Gave the money paid
the fellow's debts
and got him
his commission.
So much the better.
It will save me
a world of trouble
and economy.
Had it been
your uncle's doing,
I must have.
Would have paid him.
But These violent
young lovers
carry everything
their own way.
I shall offer
to pay him tomorrow.
He will rant and storm
about his love for you.
And there
will be an end
of the matter.
He then recollected
her embarrassment
a few days
before
on his reading Mr.
Collins letter and after
laughing at her
some time, allowed her
at last to go,
saying as she quitted
the room.
If any young men
come for Mary or Kitty,
send them in for
I am quite at leisure.
Elizabeth's mind
was now relieved
from a very
heavy weight,
and after half an hour's
quiet reflection
in her own.
Room,
she was able to join.
The others
with tolerable
composure.
Everything was too
recent for gaiety,
but the evening passed
tranquilly away.
There was no longer
anything material
to be dreaded,
and the comfort of ease
and familiarity
would come in time
when her mother went up
to her
dressing room at night.
She followed her
and made
the important
communication.
It's a fact
was most extraordinary
for on first hearing it.
Mrs.
Bennett sat quite
still and unable
to utter a syllable,
nor was it under many,
many minutes
that she
could comprehend
what she heard.
Though not in general,
backward to credit
what was for the
advantage of her family,
or that came
in the shape of a lover
to any of them.
She began at length
to recover,
to fidget
about in her chair.
Get up, sit down
again,
wonder and
bless herself.
Good gracious,
Lord, bless me.
Only think dear
me, Mr.
Darcy.
Who
would have thought it?
And is it really true?
Oh, my sweetest Lizzie.
How rich
and how great
you would be.
What pin money,
what jewels,
what carriages
you will have.
James is nothing to it.
Nothing at all.
I am so
pleased, so happy,
such A charming man.
So handsome, so tall.
Oh, my dear Lizzie,
pray, apologize.
My having disliked him
so much before.
I hope
you will overlook it.
Dear, dear Lizzie,
the house in town.
Everything
that is charming.
Three daughters
married 10,000 a year.
Oh, Lord.
What will become of me?
I shall go distracted.
This was enough
to prove
that her
approbation need.
Not be doubted.
And Elizabeth, rejoicing
that such an effusion
was heard
only by herself.
Soon went.
Away.
But before
had been 3 minutes
in her own room.
Her mother followed her.
My dearest
child, she cried.
I can think of
nothing else.
10,000 a year
and very likely more
tis is good as a lord
and a special license.
You must
and shall be married
by a special license.
But, my dearest love,
tell me what dish Mr.
Darcy is
particularly fond.
That I may
have it tomorrow.
This was a.
Sad omen of what
her mother's behavior
to the gentleman himself
might be.
And Elizabeth
found that, though,
in the search
and possession
of his
warmest affection.
And secure.
Of her relations.
Consent.
There was
still something
to be wished for.
But the morrow
passed off much better
than she expected.
For Mrs.
Bennett, luckily stood,
in search
of her intended son
in law,
that she ventured
not to speak to him
unless it was
in her power
to offer him
any attention or mark
her deference
for his opinion.
Elizabeth
had the satisfaction
of seeing her
father taking pains
to get acquainted
with him, and Mr.
Bennett soon assured her
that he was rising
every hour
in his esteem.
I admire
all my three sons
law highly, said he.
Wickham,
perhaps, is my favorite.
But I think I shall like
your husband
quite as well as Jane's.
Chapter 60
Elizabeth Spirit soon
rising to
playfulness again.
She wanted Mr.
Darcy to account
for his having
ever fallen
in love with her.
How could you begin?
Said she.
I can comprehend.
Your going on
charmingly, when.
Once you
had made a beginning.
But what could
set you off
in the first place?
I cannot fix
on the hour or the spot.
The look or the woods
which laid
the foundation.
It is too long ago.
I was in the middle
before I knew that
I had begun
my beauty.
You had early,
had asked
for my manners.
My behavior to you
was at least
always bordering
on the uncivil.
And I never spoke to you
without rather wishing
to give you
pain than not.
Now, be sincere.
Did you admire me
for my impertinence?
For the
liveliness of your mind?
I did.
You may as well call it
impertinence at once.
It was very little.
Yes.
The fact is
that you were sick
of civility,
of deference,
of officious attention.
You were disgusted
with the women
who were always
speaking, looking
and thinking
for your
approbation alone.
I roused
and interested you
because I was
so unlike them.
Had you not been
really amiable,
you would have hated
for it.
But in spite
of the pains
you took
to disguise yourself,
your feelings
were always noble
and just.
And in your heart
you thoroughly despised
the persons
you so assiduously
courted you
that I have saved you
the trouble
of accounting for it.
And really,
all things considered,
I begin to think
it's perfectly
reasonable
to be sure
you knew no
actual good of me.
But nobody
thinks of that
when they fall in love.
Was there
no good
in your affectionate
behavior to Jane
while she was
ill at Netherfield?
Dearest Jane,
who could have done
less for her,
but to make a virtue
of it by all means.
My good qualities
are under
your protection.
And you are to them
as much as possible.
And in return,
it belongs to me
to find occasions
for teasing
and quarreling with you
as often as may be.
And I shall begin
directly by asking you
what made you
so unwilling
to come to the
point at last?
What made you
so shy of me
when you first called
and afterwards
dined here?
Why?
Especially when
you called
did, you look as if
you did not
care about me.
Because you were
grave and silent
and gave me
no encouragement.
But I was embarrassed.
And so was I.
You might have
talked to me
more when you
came to dinner.
A man
who had felt less might.
How unlucky?
That you should have
a reasonable answer
to give.
And that I should be
so reasonable
as to admit it.
But I wonder how long
you would have gone on
if you had been
left to yourself.
I wonder when you would
have spoken
if I had not asked you.
My resolution
of thanking you
for your.
Kindness to.
Lydia had certainly
great effect.
Too much,
I am afraid for what
becomes of the morale
of our comforts
springs
from a
breach of promise.
For I ought not
to have mentioned
the subject.
This will never do.
You not
distress yourself.
The moral will be
perfectly fair.
Lady Katherine's
unjustifiable endeavors
to separate us were
the means of removing
all my doubts.
I am not indebted for
my present happiness
to your eager desire
of expressing
your gratitude.
I was not in the humor
to wait
for an opening of yours.
My aunt's intelligence
had given me hope,
and I was determined
at once
to know everything.
Lady Katherine
has been of
infinite use,
which ought to
make her happy.
Who she loves
to be of use.
But to tell me.
What did you come down
to Netherfield for?
Was it merely to ride
along, born
and be embarrassed?
Or had
you intended
any more
serious consequence?
My real purpose
to see you
and to judge,
if I could, whether
I might ever hope
to make you love me,
my avowed one
or what I have vowed to
myself
was to see
whether your sister
was still
partial to Bingley
and if she were
to make
the confession to him,
which I have since made.
Shall
you ever have courage
announce to.
Lady Katherine.
What is to befall her?
I am more likely
to want
time than
courage, Elizabeth.
But it ought to be done.
And if you will
give me a sheet
of paper,
it shall be
done directly.
And if I had not
a letter
to write myself,
I might sit.
By you
and admire the evenness.
Of your writing.
As another young lady
once did.
But I have an aunt, too,
who must not be longer
neglected.
From an unwillingness
to confess
how much her intimacy
with Mr.
Darcy had
been overrated.
Elizabeth had never yet
answered Mrs.
Gardner's long letter,
but now having
that to
communicate, which.
She knew
would be most welcome,
she was.
Almost ashamed to find
that her uncle
and aunt
had already lost
three days of happiness
and immediately
wrote as follows.
I would have thanked you
before, my dear aunt,
as I ought to have done
for your long kind,
satisfactory detail
of particulars.
But to say the truth,
I was too
cross to write.
You supposed
more than Mary existed.
But now, suppose
as much as you choose.
Give a loose
rein to your fancy.
Indulge your imagination
in every possible flight
which the
subject will afford.
And unless
you believe me,
actually married,
you cannot greatly.
Ah.
You must write again
very soon
and praise him
a great deal
more than you did
on your last.
I thank you again
and again
for not going
to the lakes.
How could I be so silly
as to wish it?
Your idea of the ponies
is delightful.
We will go
round the park
every day.
I am the happiest
creature in the world.
Perhaps other people
have said so before,
but not one with
such justice.
I am happier
even than Jane.
She only smiles.
I laugh.
Mr.
Darcy send you.
All the love
in the world
that he can
spare for me.
You are all to come
to Pemberley
at Christmas.
Yours, etc..
Mr.
Darcy's letter to Lady
Katherine was in
a different style
and still different from
either was what Mr.
Bennett to Mr.
Collins in reply to
his last
Dear sir.
I must trouble you
once more
for congratulations.
Elizabeth
will soon be
the wife of Mr.
Darcy console Lady
Katherine
as well as you can.
But if I were you,
I would stand
by the nephew.
He has more to give
your sincerely,
etc..
Miss Bingley
is congratulations
to her brother
on his approaching
marriage.
Were all
that was affectionate
and insincere.
She wrote even to
Jane on the
to express her delight
and repeat
all her former
professions of regard.
Jane was not.
Deceived,
but she was affected.
And though feeling no
reliance on her.
Could not.
Help writing her
a much kinder
answer than she knew
was deserved.
The joy which Mr.
Darcy expressed
on receiving
similar information was
as sincere
as her brother's
and sending.
Four sides of paper
were insufficient
to contain
all her delight
and all her
earnest desire of being
loved by her sister
before any
answer could
arrive from Mr.
Collins
or any congratulations
to Elizabeth
from his wife.
The long born family
heard that the Collins's
were coming themselves
to Lucas Lodge.
The reason of the sudden
removal
was soon evident.
Lady Katherine
had been rendered
so exceedingly angry
by the contents
of her nephew's letter
that Charlotte, really
rejoicing in the match,
was anxious to get away
till the storm
was blown over.
At such a moment,
the arrival of
her friend was a sincere
pleasure to Elizabeth.
Though in the course
of their meeting,
she must sometimes
think the pleasure
dearly bought
when she saw Mr.
Darcy
to all the parading
and obsequious
civility of her husband.
He bought, however,
with admirable calmness.
He could even listen
to Sir William Lucas
when he complimented him
on carrying away
the brightest jewel
of the country
and expressed his hopes
of their all meeting
frequently at St James's
with very
decent composure.
If he did shrugged
his shoulders.
It was not
until Sir
William was
out of sight.
Mrs.
Phillips's vulgarity
was another,
and perhaps
a greater tax
on his forbearance.
And though Mrs.
Phillips,
as well as her sister,
stood in too much of him
to speak with
the familiarity
which Bayley's good
humor encouraged.
Yet whenever
she did speak,
she must be vulgar.
Nor was her respect
for him, though
it made more quiet
at all, likely
to make her
more elegant.
Elizabeth did
all she could
to shield him
from the frequent
notice of either
and was ever anxious
to keep him to herself
and those of her family
with whom
he might converse
without mortification.
And though
the uncomfortable
feelings arising
from all
this took from
the season of courtship,
much of its pleasure,
it added to
the hope of the future.
And she looked forward
with delight to the time
when they should be
removed from society.
So little
pleasing to either
to all the comfort
and elegance
of their family
party at Pemberley.
Chapter 61.
Happy for
all her
maternal feelings
was the day
on which Mrs.
Bennett got rid of
two most
deserving daughters.
With.
What delighted pride.
She afterwards
visited Mrs.
Bingley
and talked of Mrs..
Darcy may be guessed.
I wish I could.
Say for the
sake of her family
that the accomplishment
of her earnest desire
in the establishment
of so
many of her children
produced so happy,
in effect, to make her
a sensible, amiable,
well-informed woman
for the rest of her
life.
Though perhaps
it was lucky
for her husband,
who might not
have relished
domestic Felicity in
so unusual a form
that she was still
occasionally nervous
and invariably silly.
Mr.
Bennett missed
his second
daughter exceedingly.
His affection for her
drew him oftener
from home
than anything else
could do.
He delighted
in going to Pemberley,
especially when he
was least expected.
Mr.
Bingley and Jane
at Netherfield,
only a 12 month.
So near
vicinity to her
mother and
Meriton relations.
Was not.
Desirable
even to his easy temper
or her affection heart.
The darling
wish of his sisters
was then gratified.
He bought an estate
in a neighboring county
to Derbyshire.
And Jane and Elizabeth,
in addition
to every
source of happiness,
were within 30
miles of each other.
Kitty to her very
material advantage.
Spend the chief
of her time with her
two elder sisters
in society
so superior
to what she had
generally known.
Her improvement
was great.
She was not of.
So ungovernable
a temper as Lydia,
and removed
from the influence
of Lydia's example,
she became by proper
attention
and management,
less irritable,
less ignorant,
and less insipid
from the
further disadvantage
of Lydia society.
She, of course,
carefully kept,
and though Mrs.
Wickham frequently
invited her
to come and stay
with her
with the promise
of balls and young men,
her father would never
consent to her going.
Mary was the
only daughter
who remained at home,
and she was necessarily
drawn
from the pursuit
of accomplishments
by Mrs.
Bennett's
being quite unable
to sit alone.
Mary was obliged
to mix
more with the world, but
she could still
moralize over
every morning visit,
and as she was no longer
mortified by comparisons
between her sister's
and her own.
It was.
Suspected by her father
that she submitted
to the change
without much.
Reluctance.
As for Wickham
and Lydia,
their character
suffered, no revolution
from the marriage
of her sisters.
He bore with philosophy
the conviction
that Elizabeth must now
become acquainted with
whatever
of his ingratitude
and falsehood had before
been unknown to her,
and in
spite of everything,
was not wholly without
hope that Darcy might
had to be prevailed
on to make his fortune.
The congratulatory
letter which Elizabeth
from Lydia
and her marriage,
explained to her
that by his wife,
at least.
If not by himself,
such a hope
was cherished.
The letter was to
this effect.
My dear Lizzie,
I wish you joy.
If you love.
Mr.
Darcy half
as well as I do.
My dear Wickham,
you must be very happy.
It is a great comfort
to have you so rich.
And when you
have nothing else to do,
I hope
you will think of us.
I am sure Wickham
would like a place
at court very much.
And I do not think
we shall have
quite money enough
to live upon.
Without some help.
Any place.
Would do.
Of about three
or 400 a year.
But to have.
I do not speak to Mr.
Darcy about it,
if you would
rather not yours,
etc..
As it happened
that Elizabeth had much.
Rather not.
She endeavored.
In her
answer to put an end
to every entreaty
and expectation of the.
Kind.
Such relief,
however as it was
in her power to afford
by the practice of what
might be called economy
in her own
private expenses,
she frequently
sent them.
It had always
been evident to her
that such an income
as theirs,
under the direction of
two persons
so extravagant
in their wants
and heedless of
the future,
must be
very insufficient
to their support.
And whenever
they change
their quarters.
Either Jane or herself
were sure of
being applied to
for some
little assistance
towards discharging
their bills.
Their manner of living,
even the restoration
of peace
dismissed them to a.
Home was unsettled
in the extreme.
They were.
Always moving from place
to place in
quest of a
cheap situation
and always
more than they.
Ought.
His affection
for her soon
sunk into indifference.
Hers lasted
a little longer,
and in spite of her
youth and her manners,
she retained
the claims to reputation
which her marriage had
given her.
Though Darcy
could never receive him
at Pemberley, yet,
for Elizabeth's sake,
he assisted him
further in
his profession.
Lydia was occasionally
a visitor there
when her husband
was gone
to enjoy himself
in London or Bath.
And.
With the Bingley,
say both of them
frequently
stayed so long.
That even.
Bingley
good humor was overcome.
And he proceeded so far
as to talk
of giving them
a hint to be gone.
Miss Bingley
was very
deeply mortified
by Darcy's marriage.
But as she thought.
It advisable
to retain
the right of
visiting at Pemberley,
she dropped all her
resentment was fonder
than ever of Georgiana
almost as attentive
to Darcy as heretofore,
and paid off
every area of civility
to Elizabeth.
Pemberley
was now Georgie
on his home and.
The attachment
of the sisters
was exactly what Darcy
had hoped to see.
They were able to
love each other
even as well as
they intended.
Georgiana had
the highest opinion
in the
world of Elizabeth,
though at first
she often listened
with an astonishment
bordering on alarm
at her lively sportive
manner of talking
to her brother.
He, who had always
inspired herself
a respect
which almost overcame
her affection.
She now saw the object
of open pleasantry.
Her mind
received knowledge
which had never before
fallen in her way
by Elizabeth's
instructions.
She began
to comprehend
that a woman
may take liberties
with her husband,
which a brother
will not always allow
in a sister
more than ten
years younger
than himself.
Lady Catherine was
extremely indignant
on the marriage
of her nephew,
and as she gave
way to all the genuine
frankness
of her character
in her reply
to the letter
which announced
its arrangement,
she sent him language
so very abusive,
especially of Elizabeth,
that for some time
all intercourse
was at an end.
But at length.
By Elizabeth's
persuasion,
he was prevailed on
to overlook the offense
and seek
her reconciliation.
And after a little
further resistance
on the part of his aunt,
her resentment
gave way either
to her affection for him
or her curiosity
to see how his wife
conducted herself.
And she.
Condescended to wait
on them at Pemberley
in spite of
that pollution.
Which its woods
had received,
not merely.
From the presence
of such a mistress.
But the visits.
Of her uncle and.
Aunt from the city
with.
The gardeners,
they were
always on
the most intimate terms.
Darcy,
as well as Elizabeth,
really loved them,
and they were both ever
sensible of the warmest
gratitude towards
the persons who.
By bringing her.
Into Derbyshire,
had been the means
of uniting them
and of Pride
and Prejudice
by Jane Austen reporting
by Elizabeth Klatt.